<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Roy F. Baumeister on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/roy-f.-baumeister/</link><description>Recent content in Roy F. Baumeister on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/roy-f.-baumeister/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Consider It done! Plan Making Can Eliminate the Cognitive Effects of Unfulfilled Goals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/masicampo2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/masicampo2011/</guid><description>Study 1 73 undergraduates (49 women; 24 men) Random assignments to one of three conditions: Unfulfilled tasks: thinking of two important tasks that participants need to complete in the next few days Plan: as the previous condition, but participants were asked to make completion plans Control: as the first condition, but participants were asked to think of two tasks they had already completed Reading comprehension task: first 3200 words of &amp;ldquo;The Case of the Velvet Claws&amp;rdquo; by Erle Stanley Gardner One word at a time (hitting the space bar to reveal the next word) Four participants suspected (only four?) relations between parts of the study and were excluded from the analysis Eight reading comprehension questions Discussion claim: Participants who reflected on two important but unfinished tasks were distracted during a later attempt to read a novel. General Discussion The present research examined a phenomenon known to psychology for almost a century: The persistence in the mind of unfulfilled tasks and goals. Our findings suggest the pattern has not been fully understood. Quite reasonably, the standard assumption has been that incomplete goals remain active in the mind until they are fulfilled, but the present studies showed that goal activation can cease much sooner. Once a specific plan for a goal is made, goal-related cognitive activity is drastically reduced.
Statistical Notes Student-t test on 1-7 digital scale No proper speculations on the effect size No available raw data Reference E. J. Masicampo, Roy F. Baumeister “Consider it done! Plan making can eliminate the cognitive effects of unfulfilled goals” (2011) // Journal of Personality and Social Psychology. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 101. No 4. Pp. 667–683. DOI: 10.1037/a0024192
Abstract Unfulfilled goals persist in the mind, as asserted by ample theory and evidence (e.g., the Zeigarnik effect). The standard assumption has been that such cognitive activation persists until the goal is fulfilled.</description></item><item><title>Goal Planning</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7146fe49-6fe2-4848-9091-85f3d71181ac/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7146fe49-6fe2-4848-9091-85f3d71181ac/</guid><description>The human mind is remarkably persistent in its pursuits, often even disturbingly so. Intrusive thoughts remind people of their unfulfilled goals, including to the point of interfering with other tasks. The present results, however, suggest an alternative possibility.
By planning for their goals, people can better manage their multiple pursuits. It has been well documented that specific plans increase success (Gollwitzer, 1999), doing so in part by making goal pursuit more automatic. Once a detailed plan has been made, one no longer has to think about the goal to execute it (Brandsta¨tter et al., 2001). Apparently, a plan reduces the amount of thoughts and attention that are typically recruited in service of an unfulfilled goal. Thoughts of an incomplete goal will not interfere with current concerns so long as a plan has been made to see the goal through later on.</description></item></channel></rss>