<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Geoff Cumming on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/geoff-cumming/</link><description>Recent content in Geoff Cumming on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/geoff-cumming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Editors Can Lead Researchers to Confidence Intervals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fidler2004/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fidler2004/</guid><description>Reference Fiona Fidler, Neil Thomason, Geoff Cumming, Sue Finch, Joanna Leeman “Editors Can Lead Researchers to Confidence Intervals” (2004) // Psychological Science. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 15. No 2. Pp. 119–126. DOI: 10.1111/j.0963-7214.2004.01502008.x
Bib @Article{fidler2004, title = {Editors Can Lead Researchers to Confidence Intervals}, volume = {15}, issn = {1467-9280}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.0963-7214.2004.01502008.x}, doi = {10.1111/j.0963-7214.2004.01502008.x}, number = {2}, journal = {Psychological Science}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Fidler, Fiona and Thomason, Neil and Cumming, Geoff and Finch, Sue and Leeman, Joanna}, year = {2004}, month = {feb}, pages = {119–126} }</description></item><item><title>High Impact = High Statistical Standards? Not Necessarily So</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/tressoldi2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/tressoldi2013/</guid><description>Reference Patrizio E Tressoldi, David Giofré, Francesco Sella, Geoff Cumming, Hills “High Impact = High Statistical Standards? Not Necessarily So” (2013) // PLoS ONE. Publisher: Public Library of Science (PLoS). Vol. 8. No 2. Pp. e56180. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0056180
Bib @Article{tressoldi2013, title = {High Impact = High Statistical Standards? Not Necessarily So}, volume = {8}, issn = {1932-6203}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0056180}, doi = {10.1371/journal.pone.0056180}, number = {2}, journal = {PLoS ONE}, publisher = {Public Library of Science (PLoS)}, author = {Tressoldi, Patrizio E and Giofré, David and Sella, Francesco and Cumming, Geoff}, editor = {Hills}, year = {2013}, month = {feb}, pages = {e56180} }</description></item><item><title>Introduction to the New Statistics: Estimation, Open Science, and Beyond</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/cumming-introduction-to-the-new-statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/cumming-introduction-to-the-new-statistics/</guid><description>The second edition was published in 2024. Announcement: Brian Nosek Weighs in on the 2nd Edition of ITNS.</description></item><item><title>Misunderstanding of Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/22a80e19-4456-4510-8a14-7415b537a7da/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/22a80e19-4456-4510-8a14-7415b537a7da/</guid><description>Little is known about researchers’ understanding of confidence intervals (CIs) and standard error (SE) bars. Authors of journal articles in psychology, behavioral neuroscience, and medicine were invited to visit a Web site where they adjusted a figure until they judged 2 means, with error bars, to be just statistically significantly different (p &amp;lt; .05). Results from 473 respondents suggest that many leading researchers have severe misconceptions about how error bars relate to statistical significance, do not adequately distinguish CIs and SE bars, and do not appreciate the importance of whether the 2 means are independent or come from a repeated measures design. Better guidelines for researchers and less ambiguous graphical conventions are needed before the advantages of CIs for research communication can be realized.</description></item><item><title>Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/belia2005/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/belia2005/</guid><description>Reference Sarah Belia, Fiona Fidler, Jennifer Williams, Geoff Cumming “Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars” (2005) // Psychological Methods. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 10. No 4. Pp. 389–396. DOI: 10.1037/1082-989x.10.4.389
Bib @Article{belia2005, title = {Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars}, volume = {10}, issn = {1082-989X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/1082-989X.10.4.389}, doi = {10.1037/1082-989x.10.4.389}, number = {4}, journal = {Psychological Methods}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Belia, Sarah and Fidler, Fiona and Williams, Jennifer and Cumming, Geoff}, year = {2005}, pages = {389–396} }</description></item><item><title>Statistical practices in high-impact journals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8120cd40-f648-47d8-ac65-45509e4262af/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8120cd40-f648-47d8-ac65-45509e4262af/</guid><description>What are the statistical practices of articles published in journals with a high impact factor? Are there differences compared with articles published in journals with a somewhat lower impact factor that have adopted editorial policies to reduce the impact of limitations of Null Hypothesis Significance Testing? To investigate these questions, the current study analyzed all articles related to psychological, neuropsychological and medical issues, published in 2011 in four journals with high impact factors: Science, Nature, The New England Journal of Medicine and The Lancet, and three journals with relatively lower impact factors: Neuropsychology, Journal of Experimental Psychology-Applied and the American Journal of Public Health. Results show that Null Hypothesis Significance Testing without any use of confidence intervals, effect size, prospective power and model estimation, is the prevalent statistical practice used in articles published in Nature, 89%, followed by articles published in Science, 42%.</description></item><item><title>Statistical Reform in Psychology: Is Anything Changing?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cumming2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cumming2007/</guid><description>Reference Geoff Cumming, Fiona Fidler, Martine Leonard, Pavel Kalinowski, Ashton Christiansen, Anita Kleinig, Jessica Lo, Natalie McMenamin, Sarah Wilson “Statistical Reform in Psychology: Is Anything Changing?” (2007) // Psychological Science. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 18. No 3. Pp. 230–232. DOI: 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01881.x
Bib @Article{cumming2007, title = {Statistical Reform in Psychology: Is Anything Changing?}, volume = {18}, issn = {1467-9280}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01881.x}, doi = {10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01881.x}, number = {3}, journal = {Psychological Science}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Cumming, Geoff and Fidler, Fiona and Leonard, Martine and Kalinowski, Pavel and Christiansen, Ashton and Kleinig, Anita and Lo, Jessica and McMenamin, Natalie and Wilson, Sarah}, year = {2007}, month = {mar}, pages = {230–232} }</description></item><item><title>The inappropriateness of significance tests</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/441a516a-9f37-46bc-afb1-fd6165503b80/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/441a516a-9f37-46bc-afb1-fd6165503b80/</guid><description>All references to statistical hypothesis testing and statistical significance should be removed from the paper. I ask that you delete p values as well as comments about statistical significance. If you do not agree with my standards (concerning the inappropriateness of significance tests), you should feel free to argue the point, or simply ignore what you may consider to be my misguided view, by publishing elsewher.</description></item><item><title>Understanding The New Statistics (Multivariate Applications Series)</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/cumming-understanding-the-new-statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/cumming-understanding-the-new-statistics/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>