<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Björn Brembs on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/bj%C3%B6rn-brembs/</link><description>Recent content in Björn Brembs on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/bj%C3%B6rn-brembs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Conclusions on Journal Impact Factor</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2526af27-e9d4-4a82-a5d3-e95b8af58146/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2526af27-e9d4-4a82-a5d3-e95b8af58146/</guid><description> While at this point it seems impossible to quantify the relative contributions of the different factors influencing the reliability of scientific publications, the current empirical literature on the effects of journal rank provides evidence supporting the following four conclusions:
Journal rank is a weak to moderate predictor of utility and perceived importance; Journal rank is a moderate to strong predictor of both intentional and unintentional scientific unreliability Journal rank is expensive, delays science and frustrates researchers; Journal rank as established by IF violates even the most basic scientific standards, but predicts subjective judgments of journal quality.</description></item><item><title>Deep impact: Unintended Consequences of Journal Rank</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brembs2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brembs2013/</guid><description>Reference Björn Brembs, Katherine Button, Marcus Munafò “Deep impact: unintended consequences of journal rank” (2013) // Frontiers in Human Neuroscience. Publisher: Frontiers Media SA. Vol. 7. DOI: 10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291
Bib @Article{brembs2013, title = {Deep impact: unintended consequences of journal rank}, volume = {7}, issn = {1662-5161}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291}, doi = {10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291}, journal = {Frontiers in Human Neuroscience}, publisher = {Frontiers Media SA}, author = {Brembs, Björn and Button, Katherine and Munafò, Marcus}, year = {2013} }</description></item></channel></rss>