<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Eric-Jan Wagenmakers on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/eric-jan-wagenmakers/</link><description>Recent content in Eric-Jan Wagenmakers on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/eric-jan-wagenmakers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Tutorial on Fisher Information</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ly2017/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ly2017/</guid><description>Alexander Ly, Maarten Marsman, Josine Verhagen, Raoul Grasman, Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “A Tutorial on Fisher Information” (2017) // arXiv.
Abstract In many statistical applications that concern mathematical psychologists, the concept of Fisher information plays an important role. In this tutorial we clarify the concept of Fisher information as it manifests itself across three different statistical paradigms. First, in the frequentist paradigm, Fisher information is used to construct hypothesis tests and confidence intervals using maximum likelihood estimators; second, in the Bayesian paradigm, Fisher information is used to define a default prior; lastly, in the minimum description length paradigm, Fisher information is used to measure model complexity.
Bib @Misc{ly2017, title = {A Tutorial on Fisher Information}, url = {http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.01064}, abstract = {In many statistical applications that concern mathematical psychologists, the concept of Fisher information plays an important role. In this tutorial we clarify the concept of Fisher information as it manifests itself across three different statistical paradigms. First, in the frequentist paradigm, Fisher information is used to construct hypothesis tests and confidence intervals using maximum likelihood estimators; second, in the Bayesian paradigm, Fisher information is used to define a default prior; lastly, in the minimum description length paradigm, Fisher information is used to measure model complexity.}, urldate = {2023-11-05}, publisher = {arXiv}, author = {Ly, Alexander and Marsman, Maarten and Verhagen, Josine and Grasman, Raoul and Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan}, month = {oct}, year = {2017}, note = {arXiv:1705.01064 [math, stat]}, arxiv = {1705.01064}, keywords = {Mathematics - Statistics Theory, 62-01, 62B10 (Primary), 62F03, 62F12, 62F15, 62B10 (Secondary)} }</description></item><item><title>Erroneous analyses of interactions in neuroscience: a problem of significance</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nieuwenhuis2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nieuwenhuis2011/</guid><description>Sander Nieuwenhuis, Birte U Forstmann, Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “Erroneous analyses of interactions in neuroscience: a problem of significance” (2011) // Nature Neuroscience. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 14. No 9. Pp. 1105–1107. DOI: 10.1038/nn.2886
Bib @Article{nieuwenhuis2011, title = {Erroneous analyses of interactions in neuroscience: a problem of significance}, volume = {14}, issn = {1546-1726}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2886}, doi = {10.1038/nn.2886}, number = {9}, journal = {Nature Neuroscience}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Nieuwenhuis, Sander and Forstmann, Birte U and Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan}, year = {2011}, month = {aug}, pages = {1105–1107} }</description></item></channel></rss>