<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Eric-Jan Wagenmakers on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/eric-jan-wagenmakers/</link><description>Recent content in Eric-Jan Wagenmakers on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/eric-jan-wagenmakers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Practical Solution to the Pervasive Problems of P Values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wagenmakers2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wagenmakers2007/</guid><description>Reference Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “A practical solution to the pervasive problems of p values” (2007) // Psychonomic Bulletin &amp;amp; Review. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 14. No 5. Pp. 779–804. DOI: 10.3758/bf03194105
Bib @Article{wagenmakers2007, title = {A practical solution to the pervasive problems of p values}, volume = {14}, issn = {1531-5320}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3758/BF03194105}, doi = {10.3758/bf03194105}, number = {5}, journal = {Psychonomic Bulletin &amp;amp;amp; Review}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan}, year = {2007}, month = {oct}, pages = {779–804} }</description></item><item><title>A Tutorial on Fisher Information</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ly2017/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ly2017/</guid><description>Reference Alexander Ly, Maarten Marsman, Josine Verhagen, Raoul Grasman, Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “A Tutorial on Fisher Information” (2017) // arXiv.
Abstract In many statistical applications that concern mathematical psychologists, the concept of Fisher information plays an important role. In this tutorial we clarify the concept of Fisher information as it manifests itself across three different statistical paradigms. First, in the frequentist paradigm, Fisher information is used to construct hypothesis tests and confidence intervals using maximum likelihood estimators; second, in the Bayesian paradigm, Fisher information is used to define a default prior; lastly, in the minimum description length paradigm, Fisher information is used to measure model complexity.
Bib @Misc{ly2017, title = {A Tutorial on Fisher Information}, url = {http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.01064}, abstract = {In many statistical applications that concern mathematical psychologists, the concept of Fisher information plays an important role. In this tutorial we clarify the concept of Fisher information as it manifests itself across three different statistical paradigms. First, in the frequentist paradigm, Fisher information is used to construct hypothesis tests and confidence intervals using maximum likelihood estimators; second, in the Bayesian paradigm, Fisher information is used to define a default prior; lastly, in the minimum description length paradigm, Fisher information is used to measure model complexity.}, urldate = {2023-11-05}, publisher = {arXiv}, author = {Ly, Alexander and Marsman, Maarten and Verhagen, Josine and Grasman, Raoul and Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan}, month = {oct}, year = {2017}, note = {arXiv:1705.01064 [math, stat]}, arxiv = {1705.01064}, keywords = {Mathematics - Statistics Theory, 62-01, 62B10 (Primary), 62F03, 62F12, 62F15, 62B10 (Secondary)} }</description></item><item><title>An Agenda for Purely Confirmatory Research</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wagenmakers2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wagenmakers2012/</guid><description>Reference Eric-Jan Wagenmakers, Ruud Wetzels, Denny Borsboom, Han L. J. van der Maas, Rogier A. Kievit “An Agenda for Purely Confirmatory Research” (2012) // Perspectives on Psychological Science. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 7. No 6. Pp. 632–638. DOI: 10.1177/1745691612463078
Bib @Article{wagenmakers2012, title = {An Agenda for Purely Confirmatory Research}, volume = {7}, issn = {1745-6924}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1745691612463078}, doi = {10.1177/1745691612463078}, number = {6}, journal = {Perspectives on Psychological Science}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan and Wetzels, Ruud and Borsboom, Denny and van der Maas, Han L. J. and Kievit, Rogier A.}, year = {2012}, month = {nov}, pages = {632–638} }</description></item><item><title>Erroneous Analyses of Interactions in neuroscience: A Problem of Significance</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nieuwenhuis2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nieuwenhuis2011/</guid><description>Reference Sander Nieuwenhuis, Birte U Forstmann, Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “Erroneous analyses of interactions in neuroscience: a problem of significance” (2011) // Nature Neuroscience. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 14. No 9. Pp. 1105–1107. DOI: 10.1038/nn.2886
Bib @Article{nieuwenhuis2011, title = {Erroneous analyses of interactions in neuroscience: a problem of significance}, volume = {14}, issn = {1546-1726}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2886}, doi = {10.1038/nn.2886}, number = {9}, journal = {Nature Neuroscience}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Nieuwenhuis, Sander and Forstmann, Birte U and Wagenmakers, Eric-Jan}, year = {2011}, month = {aug}, pages = {1105–1107} }</description></item><item><title>Incorrect Statistical Procedures in Neuroscience</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/4e6b0a2d-9a6c-4b97-9c15-b7009ef063a5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/4e6b0a2d-9a6c-4b97-9c15-b7009ef063a5/</guid><description>In theory, a comparison of two experimental effects requires a statistical test on their difference. In practice, this comparison is often based on an incorrect procedure involving two separate tests in which researchers conclude that effects differ when one effect is significant (P &amp;lt; 0.05) but the other is not (P &amp;gt; 0.05). We reviewed 513 behavioral, systems and cognitive neuroscience articles in five top-ranking journals (Science, Nature, Nature Neuroscience, Neuron and The Journal of Neuroscience) and found that 78 used the correct procedure and 79 used the incorrect procedure. An additional analysis suggests that incorrect analyses of interactions are even more common in cellular and molecular neuroscience.</description></item><item><title>The Fallacy of Placing Confidence in Confidence Intervals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/morey2015/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/morey2015/</guid><description>Reference Richard D. Morey, Rink Hoekstra, Jeffrey N. Rouder, Michael D. Lee, Eric-Jan Wagenmakers “The fallacy of placing confidence in confidence intervals” (2015) // Psychonomic Bulletin &amp;amp; Review. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 23. No 1. Pp. 103–123. DOI: 10.3758/s13423-015-0947-8
Abstract Interval estimates – estimates of parameters that include an allowance for sampling uncertainty – have long been touted as a key component of statistical analyses. There are several kinds of interval estimates, but the most popular are confidence intervals (CIs): intervals that contain the true parameter value in some known proportion of repeated samples, on average. The width of confidence intervals is thought to index the precision of an estimate; CIs are thought to be a guide to which parameter values are plausible or reasonable; and the confidence coefficient of the interval (e.g., 95 %) is thought to index the plausibility that the true parameter is included in the interval. We show in a number of examples that CIs do not necessarily have any of these properties, and can lead to unjustified or arbitrary inferences. For this reason, we caution against relying upon confidence interval theory to justify interval estimates, and suggest that other theories of interval estimation should be used instead.
Bib @Article{morey2015, title = {The fallacy of placing confidence in confidence intervals}, abstract = {Interval estimates – estimates of parameters that include an allowance for sampling uncertainty – have long been touted as a key component of statistical analyses. There are several kinds of interval estimates, but the most popular are confidence intervals (CIs): intervals that contain the true parameter value in some known proportion of repeated samples, on average. The width of confidence intervals is thought to index the precision of an estimate; CIs are thought to be a guide to which parameter values are plausible or reasonable; and the confidence coefficient of the interval (e.</description></item></channel></rss>