<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>David Hemenway on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/david-hemenway/</link><description>Recent content in David Hemenway on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/david-hemenway/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Addressing False Positives in Self-Report Surveys</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/6c23bac3-f06b-4234-8b0d-eb4c29388360/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/6c23bac3-f06b-4234-8b0d-eb4c29388360/</guid><description>Self-report surveys of rare events easily lead to huge overestimates of the true incidence of such events, particularly if the event in question has some potential social desirability. Researchers who claim that such survey incidence data are accurate must show how they have eliminated the enormous problem of false positives.</description></item><item><title>Survey Research and Self-Defense Gun Use: An Explanation of Extreme Overestimates</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hemenway1997/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hemenway1997/</guid><description>Reference David Hemenway “Survey Research and Self-Defense Gun Use: An Explanation of Extreme Overestimates” (1997) // The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology (1973-). Publisher: JSTOR. Vol. 87. No 4. Pp. 1430. DOI: 10.2307/1144020
Abstract Gary Kleck and Marc Gertz conducted a survey of civilian defensive gun use in 1992. In 1993, Kleck began publicizing the estimate that civilians use guns in self-defense against offenders up to 2.5 million times each year.&amp;rsquo; This figure has been widely used by the National Rifle Association and by gun advocates. It is also often cited in the media and even in Congress. The Kleck and Gertz (K-G) paper has now been published. It is clear, however, that its conclusions cannot be accepted as valid.
Bib @Article{hemenway1997, title = {Survey Research and Self-Defense Gun Use: An Explanation of Extreme Overestimates}, abstract = {Gary Kleck and Marc Gertz conducted a survey of civilian defensive gun use in 1992. In 1993, Kleck began publicizing the estimate that civilians use guns in self-defense against offenders up to 2.5 million times each year.&amp;#39; This figure has been widely used by the National Rifle Association and by gun advocates. It is also often cited in the media and even in Congress. The Kleck and Gertz (K-G) paper has now been published. It is clear, however, that its conclusions cannot be accepted as valid.}, volume = {87}, issn = {0091-4169}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1144020}, doi = {10.2307/1144020}, number = {4}, journal = {The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology (1973-)}, publisher = {JSTOR}, author = {Hemenway, David}, year = {1997}, pages = {1430} }</description></item></channel></rss>