<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Karl Popper on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/karl-popper/</link><description>Recent content in Karl Popper on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/karl-popper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Falsifiability and Reality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a755755a-4bf6-4dc8-81ba-b1d76438eb62/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a755755a-4bf6-4dc8-81ba-b1d76438eb62/</guid><description>In so far as a scientific statement speaks about reality, it must be falsifiable: and in so far as it is not falsifiable, it does not speak about reality.</description></item><item><title>Occult Effects</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a2c994b2-6063-4a15-b7a4-0d14f4ea5eee/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a2c994b2-6063-4a15-b7a4-0d14f4ea5eee/</guid><description>Every experimental physicist knows those surprising and inexplicable apparent ‘effects’ which in his laboratory can perhaps even be reproduced for some time, but which finally disappear without trace. Of course, no physicist would say in such a case that he had made a scientific discovery (though he might try to rearrange his experiments so as to make the effect reproducible). Indeed the scientifically significant physical effect may be defined as that which can be regularly reproduced by anyone who carries out the appropriate experiment in the way prescribed. No serious physicist would offer for publication, as a scientific discovery, any such ‘occult effect’, as I propose to call it — one for whose reproduction he could give no instructions. The ‘discovery’ would be only too soon rejected as chimerical, simply because attempts to test it would lead to negative results. (It follows that any controversy over the question whether events which are in principle unrepeatable and unique ever do occur cannot be decided by science: it would be a metaphysical controversy.)</description></item><item><title>The Game of Science</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/14ae475c-edf6-46a8-9bd4-e49f792adb71/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/14ae475c-edf6-46a8-9bd4-e49f792adb71/</guid><description>The game of science is, in principle, without end. He who decides one day that scientific statements do not call for any further test, and that they can be regarded as finally verified, retires from the game.</description></item><item><title>The Importance of the Critical Attitude</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/b9b10859-3a7a-49d0-9a3a-cfb9d9a16c3c/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/b9b10859-3a7a-49d0-9a3a-cfb9d9a16c3c/</guid><description>I have italicized the words ‘rational discussion’ and ‘critically’ in order to stress that I equate the rational attitude and the critical attitude. The point is that, whenever we propose a solution to a problem, we ought to try as hard as we can to overthrow our solution, rather than defend it. Few of us, unfortunately, practise this precept; but other people, fortunately, will supply the criticism for us if we fail to supply it ourselves. Yet criticism will be fruitful only if we state our problem as clearly as we can and put our solution in a sufficiently definite form — a form in which it can be critically discussed.</description></item><item><title>The Logic of Scientific Discovery</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/popper-the-logic-of-scientific-discovery/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/popper-the-logic-of-scientific-discovery/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Riddle of the World</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/3e2b099c-520a-40a2-b99b-f11d4ddad259/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/3e2b099c-520a-40a2-b99b-f11d4ddad259/</guid><description>For myself, I am interested in science and in philosophy only because I want to learn something about the riddle of the world in which we live, and the riddle of man’s knowledge of that world. And I believe that only a revival of interest in these riddles can save the sciences and philosophy from narrow specialization and from an obscurantist faith in the expert’s special skill, and in his personal knowledge and authority; a faith that so well fits our ‘post-rationalist’ and ‘post-critical’ age, proudly dedicated to the destruction of the tradition of rational philosophy, and of rational thought itself.</description></item><item><title>White Swans and Universal Statements</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a6d7b386-604a-4b5d-afaf-cc570da1ec87/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a6d7b386-604a-4b5d-afaf-cc570da1ec87/</guid><description>Now it is far from obvious, from a logical point of view, that we are justified in inferring universal statements from singular ones, no matter how numerous; for any conclusion drawn in this way may always turn out to be false: no matter how many instances of white swans we may have observed, this does not justify the conclusion that all swans are white.</description></item></channel></rss>