<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research: Building trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-thdqe/</link><description>Recent content in Research: Building trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-thdqe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Publication announcement: 'Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Since the beginning of previous year, I have been working on building a quantile estimator
that provides an optimal trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness.
At the end of the year, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/">published&lt;/a> the corresponding preprint
where I presented a description of such an estimator:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe">AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, the paper was published in &lt;em>Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation&lt;/em>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&lt;em>Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width,&lt;/em>
Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation,
DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396">10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update: the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/">final paper&lt;/a> was published in &lt;em>Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation&lt;/em> (DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396">10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396&lt;/a>).&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the beginning of this year, I have been working on building a quantile estimator
that provides an optimal trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness.
Finally, I have built such an estimator.
A paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe">AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2021)
Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width,
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-hdi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-hdi/</guid><description>&lt;p>Traditional quantile estimators that are based on one or two order statistics are a common way to estimate
distribution quantiles based on the given samples.
These estimators are robust, but their statistical efficiency is not always good enough.
A more efficient alternative is the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator which uses
a weighted sum of all order statistics.
Whereas this approach provides more accurate estimations for the light-tailed distributions, it&amp;rsquo;s not robust.
To be able to customize the trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness,
we could consider &lt;em>a trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/em>.
In this approach, we discard order statistics with low weights according to
the highest density interval of the beta distribution.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Optimal window of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator, Part 2: Trying Planck-taper window</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/">previous post&lt;/a>,
I discussed the problem of non-smooth quantile-respectful density estimation (QRDE)
which is generated by the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
based on the highest density interval of the given width.
I assumed that non-smoothness was caused by a non-smooth rectangular window
which was used to build the truncated beta distribution.
In this post, we are going to try another option: the Planck-taper window.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/img/qrde-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qrde">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/img/qrde-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/img/qrde-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qrde">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow2/img/qrde-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Optimal window of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator, Part 1: Problems with the rectangular window</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous post, we have obtained a nice version of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
which provides an opportunity to get a nice trade-off between robustness and statistical efficiency
of quantile estimations.
Unfortunately, it has a severe drawback.
If we build a &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimation&lt;/a> based on the suggested estimator,
we won&amp;rsquo;t get a smooth density function as in the case of the classic Harrell-Davis quantile estimator:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/img/qrde-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qrde">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/img/qrde-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/img/qrde-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qrde">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-ow1/img/qrde-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>In this blog post series, we are going to find a way to improve the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
so that it gives a smooth density function and keeps its advantages in terms of robustness and statistical efficiency.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Beta distribution highest density interval of the given width</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/beta-hdi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/beta-hdi/</guid><description>&lt;p>In one of &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe5/">the previous posts&lt;/a>, I discussed the idea of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
based on the highest density interval of the given width.
Since the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator uses the Beta distribution,
we should be able to find the beta distribution highest density interval of the given width.
In this post, I will show how to do this.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 8: Winsorized Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe8/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe8/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe7/">previous post&lt;/a>, we have discussed
the trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
based on the highest density interval of size $\sqrt{n}/n$.
This quantile estimator showed a decent level of statistical efficiency.
However, the research wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be complete without comparison with the winsorized modification.
Let&amp;rsquo;s fix it!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 7: Optimal threshold for the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe7/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe7/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe6/">previous post&lt;/a>, we have obtained a nice quantile estimator.
To be specific, we considered a trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
based on the highest density interval of the given size.
The interval size is a parameter that controls the trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness.
While it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have the ability to control this trade-off, there is also a need for the default value,
which could be used as a starting point
when we have neither estimator breakdown point requirements nor prior knowledge about distribution properties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a series of unsuccessful attempts, it seems that I have found an acceptable solution.
We should build the new estimator based on $\sqrt{n}/n$ order statistics.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to briefly explain the idea behind the suggested estimator and
share some numerical simulations that compare the proposed estimator
and the classic Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 6: Continuous trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe6/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe6/</guid><description>&lt;p>In my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe5/">previous post&lt;/a>,
I tried the idea of using the trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
based on the highest density interval of the given width.
The width was defined so that it covers exactly k order statistics (the width equals $(k-1)/n$).
I was pretty satisfied with the result and decided to continue evolving this approach.
While &amp;ldquo;k order statistics&amp;rdquo; is a good mental model that described the trimmed interval,
it doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually require an integer k.
In fact, we can use any real number as the trimming percentage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we are going to perform numerical simulations that check the statistical efficiency
of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator with different trimming percentages.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 5: Improving trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe5/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe5/</guid><description>&lt;p>During the last several months,
I have been experimenting with different variations of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">My original idea&lt;/a>
of using the highest density interval based on the fixed area percentage (e.g., HDI 95% or HDI 99%)
led to a set of problems with &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/">overtrimming&lt;/a>.
I tried to solve them with &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/customized-wthdqe/">manually customized&lt;/a> trimming strategy,
but this approach turned out to be too inconvenient;
it was too hard to come up with &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/">optimal thresholds&lt;/a>.
One of the main problems was about the suboptimal number of elements
that we actually aggregate to obtain the quantile estimation.
So, I decided to try an &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/">approach that involves exactly k order statistics&lt;/a>.
The idea was so promising,
but numerical simulations &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe4/">haven&amp;rsquo;t shown&lt;/a> the appropriate efficiency level.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bothered me the whole week.
It sounded so reasonable to trim the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator using exactly k order statistics.
Why didn&amp;rsquo;t this work as expected?
Finally, I have found a fatal flaw in &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe4/">my previous approach&lt;/a>:
while it was a good idea to fix the size of the trimming window,
I mistakenly chose its location following the equation from the Hyndman-Fan Type 7 quantile estimator!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we fix this problem and try another modification of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on
k order statistics &lt;strong>and&lt;/strong> highest density intervals at the same time.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 4: Adopting trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe4/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe4/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous posts, I discussed various aspects of
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/">quantile estimators based on k order statistics&lt;/a>.
I already tried a few weight functions that aggregate the sample values to the quantile estimators
(see posts about &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/">an extension of the Hyndman-Fan Type 7 equation&lt;/a> and
about &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe3/">adjusted regularized incomplete beta function&lt;/a>).
In this post, I continue my experiments and try to adopt the
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed modifications of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a> to this approach.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 3: Playing with the Beta function</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe3/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous two posts, I discussed the idea of quantile estimators based on k order statistics.
A already covered the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/">motivation behind this idea&lt;/a>
and the statistical efficiency of such estimators using the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/">extended Hyndman-Fan equations&lt;/a>
as a weight function.
Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to experiment with the Beta function as a primary way to aggregate k order statistics
into a single quantile estimation!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 2: Extending Hyndman-Fan equations</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/">previous post&lt;/a>,
I described the idea of using quantile estimators based on k order statistics.
Potentially, such estimators could be more robust than estimators based on all samples elements (like
Harrell-Davis,
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/sfakianakis-verginis-quantile-estimator/">Sfakianakis-Verginis&lt;/a>, or
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/navruz-ozdemir-quantile-estimator/">Navruz-Özdemir&lt;/a>)
and more statistically efficient than traditional quantile estimators (based on 1 or 2 order statistics).
Moreover, we should be able to control this trade-off based on the business requirements
(e.g., setting the desired breakdown point).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only challenging thing here is choosing the weight function
that aggregates k order statistics to a single quantile estimation.
We are going to try several options, perform Monte-Carlo simulations for each of them, and compare the results.
A reasonable starting point is an extension of the traditional quantile estimators.
In this post, we are going to extend the Hyndman-Fan Type 7 quantile estimator
(nowadays, it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most popular estimators).
It estimates quantiles as a linear interpolation of two subsequent order statistics.
We are going to make some modifications, so a new version is going to be based on k order statistics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Spoiler: this approach doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like an optimal one.&lt;/strong>
I&amp;rsquo;m pretty disappointed with its statistical efficiency on samples from light-tailed distributions.
So, what&amp;rsquo;s the point of writing a blog post about an inefficient approach?
Because of the following reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>I believe it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to share negative results.
Sometimes, knowledge about approaches that don&amp;rsquo;t work
could be more important than knowledge about more effective techniques.
Negative results give you a broader view of the problem
and protect you from wasting your time on potential promising (but not so useful) ideas.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Negative results improve research completeness.
When we present an approach, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to not only show why it solves problems well,
but also why it solves problems better than other similar approaches.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>While I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend my extension of the Hyndman-Fan Type 7 quantile estimator to the k order statistics case
as the default quantile estimator, there are some specific cases where it could be useful.
For example, if we estimate the median based on small samples from a symmetric light-tailed distribution,
it could outperform not only the original version but also the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
The &amp;ldquo;negativity&amp;rdquo; of the negative results always exists in a specific context.
So, there may be cases when negative results for the general case transform to positive results
for a particular niche problem.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Finally, it&amp;rsquo;s my personal blog, so I have the freedom to write on any topic I like.
My blog posts are not publications to scientific journals (which typically don&amp;rsquo;t welcome negative results),
but rather research notes about conducted experiments.
It&amp;rsquo;s important for me to keep records of all the experiments I perform regardless of the usefulness of the results.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So, let&amp;rsquo;s briefly look at the results of this not-so-useful approach.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/img/LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency-light.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/img/LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/img/LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe2/img/LightAndHeavy__N15_Efficiency-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Quantile estimators based on k order statistics, Part 1: Motivation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/kosqe1/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s not easy to choose a good quantile estimator.
In my previous posts, I considered several groups of quantile estimators:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Quantile estimators based 1 or 2 order statistics (Hyndman-Fan Type1-9)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quantile estimators based on all order statistics
(the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator,
the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/sfakianakis-verginis-quantile-estimator/">Sfakianakis-Verginis quantile estimator&lt;/a>, and
the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/navruz-ozdemir-quantile-estimator/">Navruz-Özdemir quantile estimator&lt;/a>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quantile estimators based on a variable number of order statistics
(the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">winsorized&lt;/a> modifications
of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, all of these estimators have significant drawbacks
(e.g., poor statistical efficiency or poor robustness).
In this post, I want to discuss all of the advantages and disadvantages of each approach
and suggest another family of quantile estimators that are based on k order statistics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avoiding over-trimming with the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/</guid><description>&lt;p>Previously, I already discussed the
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a> several times.
I performed several numerical simulations that compare the statistical efficiency of this estimator
with the efficiency of the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/">classic Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a> (HDQE)
and its &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">winsorized modification&lt;/a>;
I showed how we can improve the efficiency using &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/customized-wthdqe/">custom trimming strategies&lt;/a>
and how to choose a &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/">good trimming threshold value&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the heavy-tailed cases, the trimmed HDQE provides better estimations than the classic HDQE
because of its higher breakdown point.
However, in the light-tailed cases, we could get efficiency that is worse than
the baseline Hyndman-Fan Type 7 (HF7) quantile estimator.
In many cases, such an effect arises because of the over-trimming effect.
If the trimming percentage is too high or if the evaluated quantile is too far from the median,
the trimming strategy based on the highest-density interval may lead to an estimation
that is based on single order statistics.
In this case, we get an efficiency level similar to the Hyndman-Fan Type 1-3 quantile estimators
(which are also based on single order statistics).
In the light-tailed case, such a result is less preferable than Hyndman-Fan Type 4-9 quantile estimators
(which are based on two subsequent order statistics).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order to improve the situation, we could introduce the lower bound for the number of order statistics
that contribute to the final quantile estimations.
In this post, I look at some numerical simulations
that compare trimmed HDQEs with different lower bounds.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/img/LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency-light.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/img/LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/img/LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-overtrimming/img/LightAndHeavy__N05_Efficiency-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Optimal threshold of the trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/</guid><description>&lt;p>The traditional quantile estimators (which are based on 1 or 2 order statistics) have great robustness.
However, the statistical efficiency of these estimators is not so great.
The Harrell-Davis quantile estimator has much better efficiency (at least in the light-tailed case),
but it&amp;rsquo;s not robust (because it calculates a weighted sum of all sample values).
I already wrote a &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">post about trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a>:
this approach suggest dropping some of the low-weight sample values to improve robustness
(keeping good statistical efficiency).
I also perform a numerical simulations that &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/">compare efficiency&lt;/a>
of the original Harrell-Davis quantile estimator against its trimmed and winsorized modifications.
It&amp;rsquo;s time to discuss how to choose the optimal trimming threshold
and how it affects the estimator efficiency.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/img/LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency-light.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/img/LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/img/LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/thdqe-threshold/img/LightAndHeavy__N40_Efficiency-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Improving the efficiency of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator for special cases using custom winsorizing and trimming strategies</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/customized-wthdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/customized-wthdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say we want to
&lt;strong>estimate the median&lt;/strong>
based on a &lt;strong>small sample&lt;/strong> (3 $\leq n \leq 7$)
from a &lt;strong>right-skewed heavy-tailed distribution&lt;/strong>
with &lt;strong>high statistical efficiency&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The traditional median estimator is the most robust estimator, but it&amp;rsquo;s not the most efficient one.
Typically, the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator provides better efficiency,
but it&amp;rsquo;s not robust (its breakdown point is zero),
so it may have worse efficiency in the given case.
The &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">winsorized&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed&lt;/a>
modifications of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator provide a good trade-off
between efficiency and robustness, but they require a proper winsorizing/trimming rule.
A reasonable choice of such a rule for medium-size samples is based on the highest density interval of the Beta function
(as described &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">here&lt;/a>).
Unfortunately, this approach may be suboptimal for small samples.
E.g., if we use the 99% highest density interval to estimate the median,
it starts to trim sample values only for $n \geq 8$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we are going to discuss custom winsorizing/trimming strategies for special cases of the quantile estimation problem.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Efficiency of the winsorized and trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimators</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/</guid><description>&lt;p>In previous posts, I suggested two modifications of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator:
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">winsorized&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed&lt;/a>.
Both modifications have a higher level of robustness in comparison to the original estimator.
Also, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/hdqe-efficiency/">discussed&lt;/a> the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficiency_(statistics)">efficiency&lt;/a>
of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to continue numerical simulation and estimate the efficiency of
the winsorized and trimmed modifications.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/img/LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency-light.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/img/LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/img/LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/img/LightAndHeavy_N10_Efficiency-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Trimmed modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>In one of &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">the previous posts&lt;/a>, I discussed winsorized Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
This estimator is more robust than the classic Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
In this post, I want to suggest another modification that may be better for some corner cases:
the &lt;em>trimmed&lt;/em> Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Efficiency of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/hdqe-efficiency/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/hdqe-efficiency/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the most essential properties of a quantile estimator is
its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficiency_(statistics)">efficiency&lt;/a>.
In simple words, the efficiency describes the estimator accuracy.
The Harrell-Davis quantile estimator is a good option to achieve higher efficiency.
However, this estimator may provide lower efficiency in some special cases.
In this post, we will conduct a set of simulations that show the actual efficiency numbers.
We compare different distributions (symmetric and right-skewed, heavy-tailed and light-tailed),
quantiles, and sample sizes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Winsorized modification of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Harrell-Davis quantile estimator is one of my favorite quantile estimators
because of its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficiency_(statistics)">efficiency&lt;/a>.
It has a small mean square error which allows getting accurate estimations.
However, it has a severe drawback: it&amp;rsquo;s not robust.
Indeed, since the estimator includes all sample elements with positive weights,
its &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robust_statistics#Breakdown_point">breakdown point&lt;/a> is zero.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I want to suggest modifications of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
which increases its &lt;em>robustness&lt;/em> keeping almost the same level of &lt;em>efficiency&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>