<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joseph Berkson on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/joseph-berkson/</link><description>Recent content in Joseph Berkson on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/joseph-berkson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Any Series of Real Observations Does Not Actually Follow a Normal Curve</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/0d2cd179-ce5c-4fa0-a31e-c0e1c7d8189e/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/0d2cd179-ce5c-4fa0-a31e-c0e1c7d8189e/</guid><description>For we may assume that it is practically certain that any series of real observations does not actually follow a normal curve with absolute exactitude in all respects, and no matter how small the discrepancy between the normal curve and the true curve of observations, the chi-square P will be small if the sample has a sufficientlylarge numberof observationsin it.</description></item><item><title>No Black and White Balls</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ff0b2c37-5936-46d9-99ff-a9cc47b3ed64/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ff0b2c37-5936-46d9-99ff-a9cc47b3ed64/</guid><description>I have a considerable interest in mathematical statistics, but very little competency in it. You will not hear anything about cards or black and white balls from me. I shall speak as a practitioner who has frequently applied the test to real observations, made seriously for the solution of concrete scientific problems.</description></item><item><title>P-Value Beyond Any Usual Limit of Significance</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7d8010cb-c8b9-4878-801f-c267f591282d/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7d8010cb-c8b9-4878-801f-c267f591282d/</guid><description>I believe that an observant statistician who has had any considerable experience with applying the chi-square test repeatedly will agree with my statement that, as a matterof observation, when the numbersin the data are quite large, the P&amp;rsquo;s tend to come out small. Having observed this, and on reflection, I make the following dogmatic statement, referring for illustration to the normal curve: &amp;ldquo;If the normal curve is fitted to a body of data representingany real observations whatever of quantitiesin the physical world, hen if the number of observationsis extremely large - for instance, on the order of 200,000-the chi-square P will be small beyond any usual limit of significance.&amp;rdquo;</description></item><item><title>Some Difficulties of Interpretation Encountered in the Application of the Chi-Square Test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/berkson1938/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/berkson1938/</guid><description>Reference Joseph Berkson “Some Difficulties of Interpretation Encountered in the Application of the Chi-Square Test” (1938) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Publisher: JSTOR. Vol. 33. No 203. Pp. 526. DOI: 10.2307/2279690
Bib @Article{berkson1938, title = {Some Difficulties of Interpretation Encountered in the Application of the Chi-Square Test}, volume = {33}, issn = {0162-1459}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2279690}, doi = {10.2307/2279690}, number = {203}, journal = {Journal of the American Statistical Association}, publisher = {JSTOR}, author = {Berkson, Joseph}, year = {1938}, month = {sep}, pages = {526} }</description></item></channel></rss>