<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pseudoreplication on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/pseudoreplication/</link><description>Recent content in Pseudoreplication on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/pseudoreplication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Addressing Pseudoreplication in Experimental Studies</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/4c2a9774-48bc-42db-a035-c416e710ed01/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/4c2a9774-48bc-42db-a035-c416e710ed01/</guid><description>We believe that good investigators who are aware of the issue will find that eliminating pseudoreplication from their experiments is a relatively straightforward matter. The problems of pseudoreplication that we typically encounter in published studies are easily solvable, and we see no reason that reviewers and editors should accept studies that fail to eliminate pseudoreplication. We certainly do not believe that absence of pseudoreplication should be the sole, or even the main, criterion for evaluating experiments. Rather, we see the absence of pseudoreplication as representing a minimum requirement that should be met before the merits of an experiment are evaluated.</description></item><item><title>Pseudoreplication and the Design of Ecological Field Experiments</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hurlbert1984/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hurlbert1984/</guid><description>Reference Stuart H Hurlbert “Pseudoreplication and the Design of Ecological Field Experiments” (1984) // Ecological Monographs. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 54. No 2. Pp. 187–211. DOI: 10.2307/1942661
Bib @Article{hurlbert1984, title = {Pseudoreplication and the Design of Ecological Field Experiments}, volume = {54}, issn = {1557-7015}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1942661}, doi = {10.2307/1942661}, number = {2}, journal = {Ecological Monographs}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Hurlbert, Stuart H}, year = {1984}, month = {jun}, pages = {187–211} }</description></item><item><title>Pseudoreplication in Experimental Studies</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c5d9190f-aaaa-4d7b-96f6-84186076c145/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c5d9190f-aaaa-4d7b-96f6-84186076c145/</guid><description>Pseudoreplication is defined as the use of inferential statistics to test for treatment effects with data from experiments where either treatments are not replicated (though samples may be) or replicates are not statistically independent. In ANOVA terminology, it is the testing for treatment effects with an error term inappropriate to the hypothesis being considered. Scrutiny of 176 experimental studies published between 1960 and the present revealed that pseudoreplication occurred in 27% of them, or 48% of all such studies that applied inferential statistics. The incidence of pseudoreplication is especially high in studies of marine benthos and small mammals.</description></item><item><title>Pseudoreplication in Neuroscience Research:</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e9ebe56a-db58-4982-9d18-d15926814ecc/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e9ebe56a-db58-4982-9d18-d15926814ecc/</guid><description>Of the nineteen papers published in the August 2008 issue of Nature Neuroscience, seventeen papers (89%) used inferential statistics; of these, only three (18%) had sufficient information to assess whether there was pseudoreplication. Of these three, two appeared to have pseudoreplication. Of the fourteen papers that used inferential statistics but did not provide sufficient information, five (36%) were suspected of having pseudoreplication, but it was not possible to determine for certain.</description></item><item><title>Pseudoreplication in playback experiments</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/kroodsma2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/kroodsma2001/</guid><description>Reference Donald E Kroodsma, Bruce E Byers, Eben Goodale, Steven Johnson, Wan-Chun Liu “Pseudoreplication in playback experiments” (2001) // Animal Behaviour. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 61. No 5. Pp. 1029–1033. DOI: 10.1006/anbe.2000.1676
Bib @Article{kroodsma2001, title = {Pseudoreplication in playback experiments}, volume = {61}, issn = {0003-3472}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/anbe.2000.1676}, doi = {10.1006/anbe.2000.1676}, number = {5}, journal = {Animal Behaviour}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Kroodsma, Donald E and Byers, Bruce E and Goodale, Eben and Johnson, Steven and Liu, Wan-Chun}, year = {2001}, month = {may}, pages = {1029–1033} }</description></item><item><title>The problem of pseudoreplication in neuroscientific studies: is it affecting your analysis?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lazic2010/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lazic2010/</guid><description>Reference Stanley E Lazic “The problem of pseudoreplication in neuroscientific studies: is it affecting your analysis?” (2010) // BMC Neuroscience. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 11. No 1. DOI: 10.1186/1471-2202-11-5
Bib @Article{lazic2010, title = {The problem of pseudoreplication in neuroscientific studies: is it affecting your analysis?}, volume = {11}, issn = {1471-2202}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2202-11-5}, doi = {10.1186/1471-2202-11-5}, number = {1}, journal = {BMC Neuroscience}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Lazic, Stanley E}, year = {2010}, month = {jan} }</description></item></channel></rss>