<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nicolas Vayatis on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/nicolas-vayatis/</link><description>Recent content in Nicolas Vayatis on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/nicolas-vayatis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Selective review of offline change point detection methods</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/truong2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/truong2020/</guid><description>Charles Truong, Laurent Oudre, Nicolas Vayatis “Selective review of offline change point detection methods” (2020) // Signal Processing. Vol. 167. Pp. 107299. DOI: 10.1016/j.sigpro.2019.107299
Abstract This article presents a selective survey of algorithms for the offline detection of multiple change points in multivariate time series. A general yet structuring methodological strategy is adopted to organize this vast body of work. More precisely, detection algorithms considered in this review are characterized by three elements: a cost function, a search method and a constraint on the number of changes. Each of those elements is described, reviewed and discussed separately. Implementations of the main algorithms described in this article are provided within a Python package called ruptures.
Bib @Article{truong2020, title = {Selective review of offline change point detection methods}, volume = {167}, issn = {01651684}, url = {http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.00718}, doi = {10.1016/j.sigpro.2019.107299}, abstract = {This article presents a selective survey of algorithms for the offline detection of multiple change points in multivariate time series. A general yet structuring methodological strategy is adopted to organize this vast body of work. More precisely, detection algorithms considered in this review are characterized by three elements: a cost function, a search method and a constraint on the number of changes. Each of those elements is described, reviewed and discussed separately. Implementations of the main algorithms described in this article are provided within a Python package called ruptures.}, urldate = {2020-06-30}, journal = {Signal Processing}, author = {Truong, Charles and Oudre, Laurent and Vayatis, Nicolas}, month = {feb}, year = {2020}, note = {arXiv: 1801.00718}, keywords = {overview}, pages = {107299} }</description></item></channel></rss>