<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Exponential smoothing on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/exponential-smoothing/</link><description>Recent content in Exponential smoothing on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/exponential-smoothing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dispersion exponential smoothing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/dispersion-exponential-smoothing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/dispersion-exponential-smoothing/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/quantile-exponential-smoothing/">previous post&lt;/a>,
I showed how to apply exponential smoothing to quantiles
using the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/weighted-quantiles/">weighted Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a>.
This technique allows getting smooth and stable moving median estimations.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to discuss how to use the same approach
to estimate moving dispersion.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile exponential smoothing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/quantile-exponential-smoothing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/quantile-exponential-smoothing/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the popular problems in time series analysis is estimating the moving &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; value.
Let&amp;rsquo;s define the &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; as a central tendency metric like the mean or the median.
When we talk about the moving value, we assume that we are interested in
the average value &amp;ldquo;at the end&amp;rdquo; of the time series
instead of the average of all available observations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the most straightforward approaches to estimate the moving average is the &lt;em>simple moving mean&lt;/em>.
Unfortunately, this approach is not robust: outliers can instantly spoil the evaluated mean value.
As an alternative, we can consider &lt;em>simple moving median&lt;/em>.
I already discussed a few of such methods:
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mp2-quantile-estimator/">the MP² quantile estimator&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/partitioning-heaps-quantile-estimator2/">a moving quantile estimator based on partitioning heaps&lt;/a>
(a modification of the Hardle-Steiger method).
When we talk about &lt;em>simple moving averages&lt;/em>, we typically assume
that we estimate the average value over the last $k$ observations ($k$ is the &lt;em>window size&lt;/em>).
This approach is also known as &lt;em>unweighted moving averages&lt;/em> because
all target observations have the same weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an alternative to the simple moving average, we can also consider the &lt;em>weighted moving average&lt;/em>.
In this case, we assign a weight for each observation and aggregate the whole time series according to these weights.
A famous example of such a weight function is &lt;em>exponential smoothing&lt;/em>.
And the simplest form of exponential smoothing is the &lt;em>exponentially weighted moving mean&lt;/em>.
This approach estimates the weighted moving mean using exponentially decreasing weights.
Switching from the simple moving mean to the exponentially weighted moving mean provides some benefits
in terms of smoothness and estimation efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although exponential smoothing has advantages over the simple moving mean,
it still estimates the mean value which is not robust.
We can improve the robustness of this approach if we reuse the same idea for weighted moving quantiles.
It&amp;rsquo;s possible because the quantiles also can be estimated for weighted samples.
In one of my previous posts, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/weighted-quantiles/">showed&lt;/a> how to adapt
the Hyndman-Fan Type 7 and Harrell-Davis quantile estimators to the weighted samples.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to show how we can use this technique to estimate
the weighted moving quantiles using exponentially decreasing weights.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>