<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Anton Kühberger on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/anton-k%C3%BChberger/</link><description>Recent content in Anton Kühberger on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/anton-k%C3%BChberger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Comprehensive Review of Reporting Practices in Psychological journals: Are Effect Sizes Really enough?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fritz2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fritz2012/</guid><description>Reference Astrid Fritz, Thomas Scherndl, Anton Kühberger “A comprehensive review of reporting practices in psychological journals: Are effect sizes really enough?” (2012) // Theory &amp;amp; Psychology. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 23. No 1. Pp. 98–122. DOI: 10.1177/0959354312436870
Bib @Article{fritz2012, title = {A comprehensive review of reporting practices in psychological journals: Are effect sizes really enough?}, volume = {23}, issn = {1461-7447}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0959354312436870}, doi = {10.1177/0959354312436870}, number = {1}, journal = {Theory &amp;amp;amp; Psychology}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Fritz, Astrid and Scherndl, Thomas and Kühberger, Anton}, year = {2012}, month = {jun}, pages = {98–122} }</description></item><item><title>The 3% Usage of Power Analysis</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/b6157da6-8408-4226-a073-c1a0ac73fdb4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/b6157da6-8408-4226-a073-c1a0ac73fdb4/</guid><description>Over-reliance on significance testing has been heavily criticized in psychology. Therefore the American Psychological Association recommended supplementing the p value with additional elements such as effect sizes, confidence intervals, and considering statistical power seriously. This article elaborates the conclusions that can be drawn when these measures accompany the p value. An analysis of over 30 summary papers (including over 6,000 articles) reveals that, if at all, only effect sizes are reported in addition to p’s (38%). Only every 10th article provides a confidence interval and statistical power is reported in only 3% of articles.</description></item></channel></rss>