<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Quotes on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/quotes/</link><description>Recent content in Quotes on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/quotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Anderson on statistical literacy training for obstetrics-gynecology residents</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/58d4e333-4344-4fef-be8a-61e319433780/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/58d4e333-4344-4fef-be8a-61e319433780/</guid><description>Methods In 2011 we surveyed US obstetrics-gynecology residents participating in the Council for Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology In-Training Examination about their statistical literacy and statistical literacy training.
Results Our response rate was 95% (4713 of 4961). About two-thirds (2980 of 4713) of the residents rated their statistical literacy training as adequate. Female respondents were more likely to rate their statistical literacy training poorly, with 25% (897 of 3575) indicating inadequate literacy compared with 17% (141 of 806) of the male respondents (P &amp;lt; .001). Respondents performed poorly on 2 statistical literacy questions, with only 26% (1222 of 4713) correctly answering a positive predictive value question and 42% (1989 of 4173) correctly defining a P value. A total of 51% (2391 of 4713) of respondents reported receiving statistical literacy training through a journal club, 29% (1359 of 4713) said they had informal training, 15% (711 of 4713) said that they had statistical literacy training as part of a course, and 11% (527 of 4713) said that they had no training.</description></item><item><title>Fisher and post mortem examination</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e361cd8b-796d-4edd-8b8a-1f5325c9801c/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e361cd8b-796d-4edd-8b8a-1f5325c9801c/</guid><description>To consult the statistician after an experiment is fnished is often merely to ask him to conduct a post mortem examination. He can perhaps say what the experiment died of.</description></item><item><title>Fisher on p=0.05</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9306030d-dc0f-42cd-ae4f-8c77d9dbd656/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9306030d-dc0f-42cd-ae4f-8c77d9dbd656/</guid><description>The value for which P = 0.05, or 1 in 20, is 1'96 or nearly 2; it is convenient to take this point as a limit in judging whether a deviation is to be considered significant or not. Deviations exceeding twice the standard deviation are thus formally regarded as significant.</description></item><item><title>Five percieved probability values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/68b00b34-b893-406a-963c-6775b11a9147/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/68b00b34-b893-406a-963c-6775b11a9147/</guid><description>There are only five probabilities the average human can handle: 99 percent, one percent, 100 percent, zero, and 50-50. That’s it.
Source: https://twitter.com/ProbFact/status/1559569468979908608</description></item><item><title>Freud on normality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca964333-044c-4fec-8d89-145921696525/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca964333-044c-4fec-8d89-145921696525/</guid><description>Normal or approximately normal subjects are less useful objects of research than their pathological counterparts.</description></item><item><title>Horton on the statistical accessibility of medical papers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/cca63eb6-34c7-451e-baaf-1c35e7c1d7d8/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/cca63eb6-34c7-451e-baaf-1c35e7c1d7d8/</guid><description>Similarly, if a reader had knowledge of t-tests, contingency tables, nonparametric tests, epidemiologic statistics, Pearson’s correlation, simple linear regression, analysis of variance, transformations, and nonparametric correlation (topics typically included in introductory statistics courses), then 21 percent of the articles would be accessible.</description></item><item><title>Ioannidis on the null field</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/f05e3cd0-fb35-4654-b121-421c58c5f5e4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/f05e3cd0-fb35-4654-b121-421c58c5f5e4/</guid><description>Let us suppose that in a research field there are no true findings at all to be discovered. History of science teaches us that scientific endeavor has often in the past wasted effort in fields with absolutely no yield of true scientific information, at least based on our current understanding. In such a “null field,” one would ideally expect all observed effect sizes to vary by chance around the null in the absence of bias. The extent that observed findings deviate from what is expected by chance alone would be simply a pure measure of the prevailing bias.</description></item><item><title>Meehl on eager-beaver researchers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/5a3b8f36-edc5-4e56-bd51-d6fe8c1e0fee/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/5a3b8f36-edc5-4e56-bd51-d6fe8c1e0fee/</guid><description>Meanwhile our eager-beaver researcher, undismayed by logic-of-science considerations and relying blissfully on the “exactitude” of modem statistical hypothesis-testing, has produced a long publication list and been promoted to a full professorship. In terms of his contribution to the enduring body of psychological knowledge, he has done hardly anything. His true position is that of a potent-but-sterile intellectual rake, who leaves in his merry path a long train of ravished maidens but no viable scientific offspring.
Note First, I found this quote in the paper itself, next rediscovered it in Statistics Done Wrong: The Woefully Complete Guide.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on counterintuitiveness of significance testing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/87d5d946-bcbf-4c7d-921f-d7d2f680a5d4/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/87d5d946-bcbf-4c7d-921f-d7d2f680a5d4/</guid><description>This is a counterintuitive feature of significance testing: if you want to prove that your drug works, you do so by showing the data is inconsistent with the drug not working.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on journal’s impact factor and overestimation of effect sizes</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/544f89c6-188a-488a-a13a-585caf62ef81/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/544f89c6-188a-488a-a13a-585caf62ef81/</guid><description>Some evidence suggests a correlation between a journal’s impact factor (a rough measure of its prominence and importance) and the factor by which its studies overestimate effect sizes. Studies that produce less “exciting” results are closer to the truth but less interesting to a major journal editor.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on noise and real effects</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca6fb0ae-cfb4-406b-b47d-603f05d13cd6/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca6fb0ae-cfb4-406b-b47d-603f05d13cd6/</guid><description>A statistically insignificant difference could be nothing but noise, or it could represent a real effect that can be pinned down only with more data.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on sphygmomanometer</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a2525cc5-5f08-47f3-a5af-da84d9e94d9b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a2525cc5-5f08-47f3-a5af-da84d9e94d9b/</guid><description> Or perhaps I’m worried that my sphygmomanometers are not perfectly calibrated, so I measure with a different one each day.
I just wanted an excuse to use the word sphygmomanometer.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on statistical reforms</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/efcae53d-3220-4ef9-9a3d-2d2925a667c2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/efcae53d-3220-4ef9-9a3d-2d2925a667c2/</guid><description>In recent years there have been many advocates for statistical reform, and naturally there is disagreement among them on the best method to address these problems. Some insist that p values, which I will show are frequently misleading and confusing, should be abandoned altogether; others advocate a “new statistics” based on confidence intervals. Still others suggest a switch to new Bayesian methods that give more-interpretable results, while others believe statistics as it’s currently taught is just fine but used poorly.</description></item><item><title>Reinhart on truth inflation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/48424c6e-3e04-4281-87fd-2b2ca1ef057d/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/48424c6e-3e04-4281-87fd-2b2ca1ef057d/</guid><description>This effect, known as truth inflation, type M error (M for magnitude), or the winner’s curse, occurs in fields where many researchers conduct similar experiments and compete to publish the most “exciting” results: pharmacological trials, epidemiological studies, gene association studies (“gene A causes condition B”), and psychological studies often show symptoms, along with some of the most-cited papers in the medical literature.</description></item><item><title>Sokal on Monte Carlo methods</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/cdce4d2e-fb19-44fb-997f-4d1981e471a2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/cdce4d2e-fb19-44fb-997f-4d1981e471a2/</guid><description>Monte Carlo is an extremely bad method; it should only be used when all alternative methods are worse.</description></item><item><title>The first Feynman's principle</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fb1f3887-c6eb-4bbe-9275-6cf0424e276f/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fb1f3887-c6eb-4bbe-9275-6cf0424e276f/</guid><description>The first principle is that you must not fool yourself — and you are the easiest person to fool.</description></item><item><title>Twelve P-Value Misconceptions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac262184-cdb6-46f8-b7ac-5107d66d8314/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac262184-cdb6-46f8-b7ac-5107d66d8314/</guid><description> Twelve P-Value Misconceptions:
If P =.05, the null hypothesis has only a 5% chance of being true. A nonsignificant difference (eg, P &amp;gt; .05) means there is no difference between groups. A statistically significant finding is clinically important. Studies with P values on opposite sides of .05 are conflicting. Studies with the same P value provide the same evidence against the null hypothesis. P = .05 means that we have observed data that would occur only 5% of the time under the null hypothesis. P = .05 and P &amp;lt;= .05 mean the same thing. P values are properly written as inequalities (eg, “P &amp;lt; .02” when P = .015) P = .05 means that if you reject the null hypothesis, the probability of a type I error is only 5%. With a P = .05 threshold for significance, the chance of a type I error will be 5%. You should use a one-sided P value when you don’t care about a result in one direction, or a difference in that direction is impossible. A scientific conclusion or treatment policy should be based on whether or not the P value is significant.</description></item><item><title>Wilcox on normality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8c71defc-488a-4b1e-a360-f0b37f77de12/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8c71defc-488a-4b1e-a360-f0b37f77de12/</guid><description>To begin, distributions are never normal. For some this seems obvious, hardly worth mentioning, but an aphorism given by Cramér (1946) and attributed to the mathematician Poincaré remains relevant: “Everyone believes in the [normal] law of errors, the experimenters because they think it is a mathematical theorem, the mathematicians because they think it is an experimental fact.”</description></item></channel></rss>