<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Mann-Whitney U-test on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/mann-whitney/</link><description>Recent content in Mann-Whitney U-test on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/mann-whitney/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Research] Weighted Mann-Whitney U test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-wmw/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-wmw/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Weighted Mann-Whitney U test, Part 3</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw3/</guid><description>&lt;p>I continue building a weighted version of the Mann–Whitney $U$ test.
While &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw1/">previously suggested approach&lt;/a> feel promising,
I don&amp;rsquo;t like the usage of Bootstrap to obtain the $p$-value.
It is always better to have a deterministic and exact approach where it&amp;rsquo;s possible.
I still don&amp;rsquo;t know how to solve it in general case,
but it seems that I&amp;rsquo;ve obtained a reasonable solution for some specific cases.
The current version of the approach still has issues and
requires additional correction factors in some cases and additional improvements.
However, it passes my minimal requirements, so it is worth trying to continue developing this idea.
In this post, I share the description of the weighted approach and provide numerical examples.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Andreas Löffler's implementation of the exact p-values calculations for the Mann-Whitney U test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-loeffler/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-loeffler/</guid><description>&lt;p>Mann-Whitney is one of the most popular non-parametric statistical tests.
Unfortunately, most test implementations in statistical packages are far from perfect.
The exact p-value calculation is time-consuming and can be impractical for large samples.
Therefore, most implementations automatically switch to the asymptotic approximation, which can be quite inaccurate.
Indeed, the classic normal approximation could produce
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/r-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/">enormous&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/python-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/">errors&lt;/a>.
Thanks to the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth2/">Edgeworth expansion&lt;/a>, the accuracy can be improved,
but it is still not always satisfactory enough.
I prefer using the exact p-value calculation whenever possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The computational complexity of the exact p-value calculation using the classic recurrent equation
suggested by Mann and Whitney is $\mathcal{O}(n^2 m^2)$ in terms of time and memory.
It&amp;rsquo;s not a problem for small samples, but for medium-size samples,
it is slow, and it has an extremely huge memory footprint.
This gives us an unpleasant dilemma:
either we use the exact p-value calculation (which is extremely time and memory-consuming),
or we use the asymptotic approximation (which gives poor accuracy).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last week, I got acquainted with a brilliant algorithm for the exact p-value calculation
suggested by Andreas Löffler in 1982.
It&amp;rsquo;s much faster than the classic approach, and it requires only $\mathcal{O}(n+m)$ memory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mann-Whitney U test and heteroscedasticity</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-heteroscedasticity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-heteroscedasticity/</guid><description>&lt;p>Mann-Whitney U test is a good nonparametric test, which mostly targets changes in locations.
However, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t properly support all types of differences between the two distributions.
Specifically, it poorly handles changes in variance.
In this post, I briefly discuss its behavior in reaction to scaling a distribution without introducing location changes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Weighted Mann-Whitney U test, Part 2</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Previously, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw1/">suggested&lt;/a> a weighted version of the Mann–Whitney $U$ test.
The distribution of the weighted normalized $U_\circ^\star$ can be obtained via bootstrap.
However, it is always nice if we can come up with an exact solution for the statistic distribution or
at least provide reasonable approximations.
In this post, we start exploring this distribution.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Weighted Mann-Whitney U test, Part 1</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/wmw1/</guid><description>&lt;p>Previously, I have discussed how to build weighted versions of various statistical methods.
I have already covered weighted versions of
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-wqe/">various quantile estimators&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/whl/">the Hodges-Lehmann location estimator&lt;/a>.
Such methods can be useful in various tasks like the support of weighted mixture distributions or exponential smoothing.
In this post, I suggest a way to build a weighted version of the Mann-Whitney U test.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Edgeworth expansion for the Mann-Whitney U test, Part 2: increased accuracy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth/">previous post&lt;/a>,
we showed how the Edgeworth expansion can improve the accuracy of obtained p-values in the Mann-Whitney U test.
However, we considered only the Edgeworth expansion to terms of order $1/m$.
In this post, we explore how to improve the accuracyk of this approach using
the Edgeworth expansion to terms of order $1/m^2$.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Edgeworth expansion for the Mann-Whitney U test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-edgeworth/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/r-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/">previous posts&lt;/a>,
I have shown a severe drawback of the classic Normal approximation for the Mann-Whitney U test:
under certain conditions, can lead to quite substantial p-value errors,
distorting the significance level of the test.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we will explore the potential of the Edgeworth expansion
as a more accurate alternative for approximating the distribution of the Mann-Whitney U statistic.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Confusing tie correction in the classic Mann-Whitney U test implementation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-confusing-tie-correction/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mw-confusing-tie-correction/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post, we discuss the classic implementation of the Mann-Whitney U test for cases
in which the considered samples contain tied values.
This approach is used the same way in all the popular statistical packages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, in some situations, this approach produces confusing p-values, which may be surprising for researchers
who do not have a deep understanding of ties correction.
Moreover, some statistical textbooks argue against the validity of the default tie correction.
The controversialness and counterintuitiveness of this approach may become a severe issue which may lead
to incorrect experiment design and flawed result interpretation.
In order to prevent such problems, it is essential to clearly understand
the actual impact of tied observations on the true p-value and
the impact of tie correction on the approximated p-value estimation.
In this post, we discuss the tie correction for the Mann-Whitney U test
and review examples that illustrate potential problems.
We also provide examples of the Mann-Whitney U test implementations from popular statistical packages:
&lt;code>wilcox.test&lt;/code> from &lt;code>stats&lt;/code> (R),
&lt;code>mannwhitneyu&lt;/code> from &lt;code>SciPy&lt;/code> (Python), and
&lt;code>MannWhitneyUTest&lt;/code> from &lt;code>HypothesisTests&lt;/code> (Julia).
At the end of the post, we discuss how to avoid possible problems related to the tie correction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When Python's Mann-Whitney U test returns extremely distorted p-values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/python-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/python-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/r-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/">previous post&lt;/a>,
I have discussed a huge difference between p-values evaluated via the R implementation of
the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mann%E2%80%93Whitney_U_test">Mann-Whitney U test&lt;/a>
between the exact and asymptotic implementations.
This issue is not unique only to R, it is relevant for other statistical packages in other languages as well.
In this post, we review this problem in the Python package &lt;a href="https://scipy.org/">SciPy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When R's Mann-Whitney U test returns extremely distorted p-values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/r-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/r-mann-whitney-incorrect-p-value/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mann%E2%80%93Whitney_U_test">Mann–Whitney U test&lt;/a>
(also known as the Wilcoxon rank-sum test)
is one of the most popular nonparametric statistical tests.
In R, it can be accessed using
the &lt;a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/stats/html/wilcox.test.html">wilcox.test&lt;/a> function,
which has been &lt;a href="https://github.com/wch/r-source/blob/tags/R-1-0/src/library/ctest/R/wilcox.test.R">available&lt;/a>
since R 1.0.0 (February 2000).
With its extensive adoption and long-standing presence in R,
the &lt;code>wilcox.test&lt;/code> function has become a trusted tool for many researchers.
But is it truly reliable, and to what extent can we rely on its accuracy by default?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my work,
I often encounter the task of comparing a large sample (e.g., of size 50+) with a small sample (e.g., of size 5).
In some cases, the ranges of these samples do not overlap with each other,
which is the extreme case of the Mann–Whitney U test: it gives the minimum possible p-value.
In &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-min-stat-level/">one of the previous posts&lt;/a>,
I presented the exact equation for such a p-value.
If we compare two samples of sizes $n$ and $m$,
the minimum p-value we can observe with the one-tailed Mann–Whitney U test is $1/C_{n+m}^n$.
For example, if $n=50$ and $m=5$, we get $1/C_{55}^5 \approx 0.0000002874587$.
Let&amp;rsquo;s check these calculations using R:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-r" data-lang="r">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="o">&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">wilcox.test&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">101&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">105&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">1&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">50&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">alternative&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;greater&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">$&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">p.value&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">[1]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">0.0001337028&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The obtained p-value is $\approx 0.0001337028$, which is $\approx 465$ times larger than we expected!
Have we discovered a critical bug in &lt;code>wilcox.test&lt;/code>?
Can we now trust this function?
Let&amp;rsquo;s find out!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Comparing statistical power of the Mann-Whitney U test and the Brunner-Munzel test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/power-mw-bm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/power-mw-bm/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post, we perform a short numerical simulation to compare the statistical power
of the Mann-Whitney U test and the Brunner-Munzel test under normality
for various sample sizes and significance levels.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>p-value distribution of the Mann–Whitney U test in the finite case</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-pvalue-distribution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-pvalue-distribution/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we work with null hypothesis significance testing and the null hypothesis is true,
the distribution of observed p-value is asymptotically uniform.
However, the distribution shape is not always uniform in the finite case.
For example, when we work with rank-based tests like the Mann–Whitney U test,
the distribution of the p-values is discrete with a limited set of possible values.
This should be taken into account when we design a testing procedure for small samples
and choose the significance level.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Previously, we already discussed the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-min-stat-level/">minimum reasonable significance level&lt;/a>
of the Mann-Whitney U test for small samples.
In this post, we explore the full distribution of the p-values for this case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Examples of the Mann–Whitney U test misuse cases</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-misuse/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-misuse/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Mann–Whitney U test is one of the most popular nonparametric statistical tests.
Its alternative hypothesis claims that one distribution is stochastically greater than the other.
However, people often misuse this test and try to apply it to check
if two nonparametric distributions are not identical
or that there is a difference in distribution medians
(while there are no additional assumptions on the shapes of the distributions).
In this post, I show several cases in which the Mann–Whitney U test is not applicable
for comparing two distributions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Minimum meaningful statistical level for the Mann–Whitney U test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-min-stat-level/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mann-whitney-min-stat-level/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mann%E2%80%93Whitney_U_test">Mann–Whitney U test&lt;/a> is one of the most popular
nonparametric null hypothesis significance tests.
However, like any statistical test, it has limitations.
We should always carefully match them with our business requirements.
In this post, we discuss how to properly choose the statistical level for the Mann–Whitney U test on small samples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say we want to compare two samples $x = \{ x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n \}$ and $y = \{ y_1, y_2, \ldots, y_m \}$
using the one-sided Mann–Whitney U test.
Sometimes, we don&amp;rsquo;t have an opportunity to gather enough data and we have to work with small samples.
Imagine that the size of both samples is six: $n=m=6$.
We want to set the statistical level $\alpha$ to $0.001$ (because we really don&amp;rsquo;t want to get false-positive results).
Is it a valid requirement?
In fact, the minimum p-value we can observe with $n=m=6$ is $\approx 0.001082$.
Thus, with $\alpha = 0.001$, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to get a positive result.
Meanwhile, everything is correct from the technical point of view:
since we can&amp;rsquo;t get any positive results, the false positive rate is exactly zero which is less than $0.001$.
However, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely not something that we want: with this setup the test becomes useless because
it always provides negative results regardless of the input data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This brings an important question: what is the minimum meaningful statistical level
that we can require for the one-sided Mann–Whitney U test knowing the sample sizes?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Uniform Saddlepoint Expansion for the Null-Distribution of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Statistic</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/froda2000/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/froda2000/</guid><description>Reference Sorana Froda, Constance Van Eeden “A Uniform Saddlepoint Expansion for the Null-Distribution of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Statistic” (2000) // The Canadian Journal of Statistics / La Revue Canadienne de Statistique. Vol. 28. No 1. Pp. 137. DOI: 10.2307/3315887
Bib @Article{froda2000, title = {A Uniform Saddlepoint Expansion for the Null-Distribution of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Statistic}, volume = {28}, issn = {03195724}, url = {https://www.jstor.org/stable/3315887?origin=crossref}, doi = {10.2307/3315887}, number = {1}, urldate = {2023-05-31}, journal = {The Canadian Journal of Statistics / La Revue Canadienne de Statistique}, author = {Froda, Sorana and Van Eeden, Constance}, month = {mar}, year = {2000}, pages = {137} }</description></item><item><title>Case for Omitting Tied Observations in the two-sample t-test and the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mcgee2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mcgee2018/</guid><description>Reference Monnie McGee, David Fardo “Case for omitting tied observations in the two-sample t-test and the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test” (2018) // PLOS ONE. Vol. 13. No 7. Pp. e0200837. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0200837
Bib @Article{mcgee2018, title = {Case for omitting tied observations in the two-sample t-test and the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test}, volume = {13}, issn = {1932-6203}, url = {https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0200837}, doi = {10.1371/journal.pone.0200837}, language = {en}, number = {7}, urldate = {2023-05-04}, journal = {PLOS ONE}, author = {McGee, Monnie}, editor = {Fardo, David}, month = {jul}, year = {2018}, pages = {e0200837} }</description></item><item><title>Different Outcomes of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test from Different Statistics Packages</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bergmann2000/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bergmann2000/</guid><description>Reference Reinhard Bergmann, John Ludbrook, Will P J M Spooren “Different Outcomes of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test from Different Statistics Packages” (2000) // The American Statistician. Vol. 54. No 1. Pp. 72. DOI: 10.2307/2685616
Bib @Article{bergmann2000, title = {Different Outcomes of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test from Different Statistics Packages}, volume = {54}, issn = {00031305}, url = {https://www.jstor.org/stable/2685616?origin=crossref}, doi = {10.2307/2685616}, number = {1}, urldate = {2023-05-03}, journal = {The American Statistician}, author = {Bergmann, Reinhard and Ludbrook, John and Spooren, Will P J M}, month = {feb}, year = {2000}, pages = {72} }</description></item><item><title>Mann-Whitney Test is Not Just a Test of medians: Differences in Spread Can Be Important</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hart2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hart2001/</guid><description>Reference A Hart “Mann-Whitney test is not just a test of medians: differences in spread can be important” (2001) // BMJ. Vol. 323. No 7309. Pp. 391–393. DOI: 10.1136/bmj.323.7309.391
Bib @Article{hart2001, title = {Mann-Whitney test is not just a test of medians: differences in spread can be important}, volume = {323}, issn = {09598138}, shorttitle = {Mann-Whitney test is not just a test of medians}, url = {https://www.bmj.com/lookup/doi/10.1136/bmj.323.7309.391}, doi = {10.1136/bmj.323.7309.391}, number = {7309}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {BMJ}, author = {Hart, A}, month = {aug}, year = {2001}, pages = {391--393} }</description></item><item><title>Mann–Whitney U Test When Variances Are Unequal</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/kasuya2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/kasuya2001/</guid><description>Reference Eiiti Kasuya “Mann–Whitney U test when variances are unequal” (2001) // Animal Behaviour. Vol. 61. No 6. Pp. 1247–1249. DOI: 10.1006/anbe.2001.1691
Bib @Article{kasuya2001, title = {Mann–Whitney U test when variances are unequal}, volume = {61}, issn = {00033472}, url = {https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0003347201916914}, doi = {10.1006/anbe.2001.1691}, language = {en}, number = {6}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {Animal Behaviour}, author = {Kasuya, Eiiti}, month = {jun}, year = {2001}, pages = {1247--1249} }</description></item><item><title>On a Test of Whether One of Two Random Variables is Stochastically Larger Than the Other</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mann1947/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mann1947/</guid><description>Reference H B Mann, D R Whitney “On a Test of Whether one of Two Random Variables is Stochastically Larger than the Other” (1947) // The Annals of Mathematical Statistics. Vol. 18. No 1. Pp. 50–60. DOI: 10.1214/aoms/1177730491
Bib @Article{mann1947, title = {On a Test of Whether one of Two Random Variables is Stochastically Larger than the Other}, volume = {18}, issn = {0003-4851}, url = {http://projecteuclid.org/euclid.aoms/1177730491}, doi = {10.1214/aoms/1177730491}, language = {en}, number = {1}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {The Annals of Mathematical Statistics}, author = {Mann, H B and Whitney, D R}, month = {mar}, year = {1947}, pages = {50--60} }</description></item><item><title>The normal, Edgeworth, Saddlepoint and Uniform Approximations to the Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney null-distribution: A Numerical Comparison</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bean2004/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bean2004/</guid><description>Reference Raphaël Bean, Sorana Froda, Constance Van Eeden “The normal, Edgeworth, saddlepoint and uniform approximations to the Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney null-distribution: a numerical comparison” (2004) // Journal of Nonparametric Statistics. Vol. 16. No 1-2. Pp. 279–288. DOI: 10.1080/10485250310001622677
Bib @Article{bean2004, title = {The normal, Edgeworth, saddlepoint and uniform approximations to the Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney null-distribution: a numerical comparison}, volume = {16}, issn = {1048-5252, 1029-0311}, shorttitle = {The normal, Edgeworth, saddlepoint and uniform approximations to the Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney null-distribution}, url = {http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10485250310001622677}, doi = {10.1080/10485250310001622677}, language = {en}, number = {1-2}, urldate = {2023-05-04}, journal = {Journal of Nonparametric Statistics}, author = {Bean, Raphaël and Froda, Sorana and Van Eeden, Constance}, month = {feb}, year = {2004}, pages = {279--288} }</description></item><item><title>The Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney Procedure Fails as a Test of Medians</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/divine2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/divine2018/</guid><description>Reference George W Divine, H James Norton, Anna E Barón, Elizabeth Juarez-Colunga “The Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney Procedure Fails as a Test of Medians” (2018) // The American Statistician. Vol. 72. No 3. Pp. 278–286. DOI: 10.1080/00031305.2017.1305291
Bib @Article{divine2018, title = {The Wilcoxon–Mann–Whitney Procedure Fails as a Test of Medians}, volume = {72}, issn = {0003-1305, 1537-2731}, url = {https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2017.1305291}, doi = {10.1080/00031305.2017.1305291}, language = {en}, number = {3}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {The American Statistician}, author = {Divine, George W and Norton, H James and Barón, Anna E and Juarez-Colunga, Elizabeth}, month = {jul}, year = {2018}, pages = {278--286} }</description></item><item><title>Über Eine Partition Der nat. Zahlen Und Ihre Anwendung Beim U-Test</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/loeffler1982/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/loeffler1982/</guid><description>Original | English Version
Reference Andreas Löffler “Über eine Partition der nat. Zahlen und ihre Anwendung beim U-Test” (1982)
Bib @Article{loeffler1982, title = {Über eine Partition der nat. Zahlen und ihre Anwendung beim U-Test}, year = {1982}, url = {https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/de/1/19/MannWhitney_151102.pdf}, language = {german}, author = {Löffler, Andreas} }</description></item><item><title>What Hypotheses Do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/conroy2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/conroy2012/</guid><description>Reference Ronán M Conroy “What Hypotheses do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?” (2012) // The Stata Journal: Promoting communications on statistics and Stata. Vol. 12. No 2. Pp. 182–190. DOI: 10.1177/1536867X1201200202
Abstract In this article, I discuss measures of effect size for two-group comparisons where data are not appropriately analyzed by least-squares methods. The Mann–Whitney test calculates a statistic that is a very useful measure of effect size, particularly suited to situations in which differences are measured on scales that either are ordinal or use arbitrary scale units. Both the difference in medians and the median difference between groups are also useful measures of effect size.
Bib @Article{conroy2012, title = {What Hypotheses do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?}, volume = {12}, issn = {1536-867X, 1536-8734}, url = {http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1536867X1201200202}, doi = {10.1177/1536867X1201200202}, abstract = {In this article, I discuss measures of effect size for two-group comparisons where data are not appropriately analyzed by least-squares methods. The Mann–Whitney test calculates a statistic that is a very useful measure of effect size, particularly suited to situations in which differences are measured on scales that either are ordinal or use arbitrary scale units. Both the difference in medians and the median difference between groups are also useful measures of effect size.}, language = {en}, number = {2}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {The Stata Journal: Promoting communications on statistics and Stata}, author = {Conroy, Ronán M}, month = {jun}, year = {2012}, pages = {182--190} }</description></item></channel></rss>