<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>V. P. Golubyatnikov on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/v.-p.-golubyatnikov/</link><description>Recent content in V. P. Golubyatnikov on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/v.-p.-golubyatnikov/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mathematical and Numerical Models of the Central Regulatory Circuit of the Morphogenesis System of Drosophila</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2020sjim/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2020sjim/</guid><description>Reference A. A. Akinshin, T. A. Bukharina, V. P. Golubyatnikov, D. P. Furman “Mathematical and Numerical Models of the Central Regulatory Circuit of the Morphogenesis System of Drosophila” (2020) // Journal of Applied and Industrial Mathematics. Vol. 14. No 2. Pp. 249-255. DOI: 10.1134/S1990478920020040
Abstract The results are presented of mathematical and computer simulation of the functioning of the central regulatory circuit (CRC) which is the system integrator of the gene networks ofmorphogenesis of Drosophila mechanoreceptors. The main element of the CRC is represented bythe complex of Achaete-Scute (AS-C) genes, the main genes of the mechanoreceptor morphogenesis.The content level of the proteins encoded by the AS-Cgenes is a determining factor for initiating the development of a mechanoreceptor. We carried outa comparative study of the CRC behavior under normal conditions and in the presence ofmutational changes in the Achaete-Scute complex. Theresults of simulation are in good accord with the available biological data.
Bib @Article{akinshin2020sjim, author = {Akinshin, A. A. and Bukharina, T. A. and Golubyatnikov, V. P. and Furman, D. P.}, title = {Mathematical and Numerical Models of the Central Regulatory Circuit of the Morphogenesis System of Drosophila}, journal = {Journal of Applied and Industrial Mathematics}, year = {2020}, month = {May}, day = {01}, volume = {14}, number = {2}, pages = {249-255}, abstract = {The results are presented of mathematical and computer simulation of the functioning of the central regulatory circuit (CRC) which is the system integrator of the gene networks ofmorphogenesis of Drosophila mechanoreceptors. The main element of the CRC is represented bythe complex of Achaete-Scute (AS-C) genes, the main genes of the mechanoreceptor morphogenesis.The content level of the proteins encoded by the AS-Cgenes is a determining factor for initiating the development of a mechanoreceptor. We carried outa comparative study of the CRC behavior under normal conditions and in the presence ofmutational changes in the Achaete-Scute complex.</description></item><item><title>On a Numerical Model of a Circadian Oscillator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2022circadian/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2022circadian/</guid><description>Reference A. A. Akinshin, N. B. Ayupova, V. P. Golubyatnikov, N. E. Kirillova, O. A. Podkolodnaya, N. L. Podkolodnyy “On a Numerical Model of a Circadian Oscillator” (2022) // Numerical Analysis and Applications. Vol. 15. No 3. Pp. 187-196. DOI: 10.1134/S1995423922030016
Abstract For a model of a circadian oscillator presented in the form of a 6-dimensional nonlinear dynamical system, conditions of uniqueness of an equilibrium point and conditions of existence of a periodic trajectory (cycle) are established. A client-server application is developed to perform numerical experiments with this model on a cloud server and to visualize the results of these experiments.
Bib @Article{akinshin2022circadian, author = {Akinshin, A. A. and Ayupova, N. B. and Golubyatnikov, V. P. and Kirillova, N. E. and Podkolodnaya, O. A. and Podkolodnyy, N. L.}, title = {On a Numerical Model of a Circadian Oscillator}, journal = {Numerical Analysis and Applications}, year = {2022}, month = {Sep}, day = {01}, volume = {15}, number = {3}, pages = {187-196}, abstract = {For a model of a circadian oscillator presented in the form of a 6-dimensional nonlinear dynamical system, conditions of uniqueness of an equilibrium point and conditions of existence of a periodic trajectory (cycle) are established. A client-server application is developed to perform numerical experiments with this model on a cloud server and to visualize the results of these experiments.}, issn = {1995-4247}, doi = {10.1134/S1995423922030016}, url = {https://rdcu.be/cUri9}, custom-project = {gene-networks}, custom-tags = {Scopus,WoS,Springer} }</description></item><item><title>Stratifications and Foliations in Phase Portraits of Gene Network Models</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2023strat/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/akinshin2023strat/</guid><description>Reference A. A. Akinshin, V. P. Golubyatnikov, N. B. Ayupova, L. S. Minushkina “Stratifications and foliations in phase portraits of gene network models” (2023) // Vavilov Journal of Genetics and Breeding. Publisher: Institute of Cytology and Genetics, SB RAS. Vol. 26. No 8. Pp. 758–764. DOI: 10.18699/vjgb-22-91
Bib @Article{akinshin2023strat, doi = {10.18699/vjgb-22-91}, year = {2023}, month = {jan}, publisher = {Institute of Cytology and Genetics, SB RAS}, volume = {26}, number = {8}, pages = {758--764}, author = {A. A. Akinshin and V. P. Golubyatnikov and N. B. Ayupova and L. S. Minushkina}, title = {Stratifications and foliations in phase portraits of gene network models}, journal = {Vavilov Journal of Genetics and Breeding}, custom-project = {gene-networks} }</description></item></channel></rss>