<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Christina M. Bird on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/christina-m.-bird/</link><description>Recent content in Christina M. Bird on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/christina-m.-bird/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Detecting Bimodality in Astronomical Datasets</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ashman1994/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ashman1994/</guid><description>Reference Keith A. Ashman, Christina M. Bird, Stephen E. Zepf “Detecting bimodality in astronomical datasets” (1994) // The Astronomical Journal. Publisher: American Astronomical Society. Vol. 108. Pp. 2348. DOI: 10.1086/117248
Abstract We discuss statistical techniques for detecting and quantifying bimodality in astronomical datasets. We concentrate on the KMM algorithm, which estimates the statistical significance of bimodality in such datasets and objectively partitions data into sub-populations. By simulating bimodal distributions with a range of properties we investigate the sensitivity of KMM to datasets with varying characteristics. Our results facilitate the planning of optimal observing strategies for systems where bimodality is suspected. Mixture-modeling algorithms similar to the KMM algorithm have been used in previous studies to partition the stellar population of the Milky Way into subsystems. We illustrate the broad applicability of KMM by analysing published data on globular cluster metallicity distributions, velocity distributions of galaxies in clusters, and burst durations of gamma-ray sources. PostScript versions of the tables and figures, as well as FORTRAN code for KMM and instructions for its use, are available by anonymous ftp from kula.phsx.ukans.edu.
Bib @Article{ashman1994, title = {Detecting bimodality in astronomical datasets}, abstract = {We discuss statistical techniques for detecting and quantifying bimodality in astronomical datasets. We concentrate on the KMM algorithm, which estimates the statistical significance of bimodality in such datasets and objectively partitions data into sub-populations. By simulating bimodal distributions with a range of properties we investigate the sensitivity of KMM to datasets with varying characteristics. Our results facilitate the planning of optimal observing strategies for systems where bimodality is suspected. Mixture-modeling algorithms similar to the KMM algorithm have been used in previous studies to partition the stellar population of the Milky Way into subsystems. We illustrate the broad applicability of KMM by analysing published data on globular cluster metallicity distributions, velocity distributions of galaxies in clusters, and burst durations of gamma-ray sources.</description></item></channel></rss>