<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Multimodality Detection on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/multimodality-detection/</link><description>Recent content in Multimodality Detection on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/multimodality-detection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Multimodal distributions and effect size</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/multimodal-es/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/multimodal-es/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we want to express the difference between two samples or distributions,
a popular measure family is the effect sizes based on differences between means (difference family).
When the normality assumption is satisfied, this approach works well thanks to classic measures of effect size
like Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d, Glass&amp;rsquo; Δ, or Hedges&amp;rsquo; g.
With slight deviations from normality, &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size2/">robust alternatives&lt;/a> may be considered.
To build such a measure, it&amp;rsquo;s enough to upgrade classic measures by
replacing the sample mean with a robust measure of central tendency and
replacing the standard deviation with a robust measure of dispersion.
However, it might not be enough in the case of large deviations from normality.
In this post, I briefly discuss the problem of effect size evaluation in the context of multimodal distributions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Joining modes of multimodal distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/joining-modes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/joining-modes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Multimodality of distributions is a severe issue in statistical analysis.
Comparing two multimodal distributions is a tricky challenge.
The degree of this challenge depends on the number of existing modes.
Switching from unimodal models to multimodal ones
can be a controversial decision, potentially causing more problems than solutions.
Hence, if we dare to increase the complexity of the considering models,
we should be sure that this is an essential necessity.
Even when we confidently detect a truly multimodal distribution,
a unimodal model could be an acceptable approximation if it is sufficiently close to the true distribution.
The simplicity of a unimodal model may make it preferable, even if it is less accurate.
Of course, the research goals should always be taken into account when the particular model choice is being made.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Plain-text summary notation for multimodal distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you collected a lot of data and want to explore the underlying distributions of collected samples.
If you have only a few distributions, the best way to do that is to look at the density plots
(expressed via histograms, kernel density estimations, or &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimations&lt;/a>).
However, it&amp;rsquo;s not always possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suppose you have to process dozens, hundreds, or even thousands of distributions.
In that case,
it may be extremely time-consuming to manually check visualizations of each distribution.
If you analyze distributions from the command line or send notifications about suspicious samples,
it may be impossible to embed images in the reports.
In these cases, there is a need to present a distribution using plain text.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One way to do that is plain text histograms.
Unfortunately, this kind of visualization may occupy o lot of space.
In complicated cases, you may need 20 or 30 lines per a single distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another way is to present classic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summary_statistics">summary statistics&lt;/a>
like mean or median, standard deviation or median absolute deviation, quantiles, skewness, and kurtosis.
There is another problem here:
without experience, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to reconstruct the true distribution shape based on these values.
Even if you are an experienced researcher, the statistical metrics may become misleading in the case of multimodal distributions.
Multimodality is one of the most severe challenges in distribution analysis because it distorts basic summary statistics.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to not only find such distribution but also have a way to present brief information about multimodality effects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, how can we condense the underlying distribution shape of a given sample to a short text line?
I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to find an approach that works fine in my cases, so I came up with my own notation.
Most of the interpretation problems in my experiments arise from multimodality and outliers,
so I decided to focus on these two things and specifically highlight them.
Let&amp;rsquo;s consider this plot:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="thumbnail">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="thumbnail">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>I suggest describing it like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>1.00, 2.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span> + &lt;span class="o">[&lt;/span>7.16&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> 13.12&lt;span class="o">]&lt;/span>_100 + &lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>19.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span> + &lt;span class="o">[&lt;/span>27.69&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> 32.34&lt;span class="o">]&lt;/span>_100 + &lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>37.00..39.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span>_3
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Let me explain the suggested notation in detail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Intermodal outliers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outlier">Outlier&lt;/a> analysis is a typical step in distribution exploration.
Usually, we work with the &amp;ldquo;lower outliers&amp;rdquo; (extremely low values) and the &amp;ldquo;upper outliers&amp;rdquo; (extremely high values).
However, outliers are not always extreme values.
In the general case, an outlier is a value that significantly differs from other values in the same sample.
In the case of multimodal distribution, we can also consider outliers in the middle of the distribution.
Let&amp;rsquo;s call such outliers that we found between modes the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>intermodal outliers&lt;/em>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="step4">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="step4">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Look at the above density plot.
It&amp;rsquo;s a bimodal distribution that is formed as a combination of two unimodal distributions.
Each of the unimodal distributions may have its own lower and upper outliers.
When we merge them, the upper outliers of the first distribution and the lower outliers of the second distribution
stop being lower or upper outliers.
However, if these values don&amp;rsquo;t belong to the modes, they still are a subject of interest.
In this post, I will show you how to detect such intermodal outliers
and how they can be used to form a better distribution description.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lowland multimodality detection</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/</guid><description>&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="data5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="data5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Multimodality is an essential feature of a distribution, which may create many troubles during automatic analysis.
One of the best ways to work with such distributions is to detect all the modes in advance based on the given samples.
Unfortunately, this problem is much harder than it looks like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tried many different approaches for multimodality detection, but none of them was good enough.
During the past several years, my approach of choice was the &lt;a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/FrequencyTrails/modes.html">mvalue-based modal test&lt;/a> by Brendan Gregg.
It works nicely in simple cases, but I was constantly stumbling over noisy samples where this algorithm doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce reliable results.
Also, it has some limitations that make it inapplicable to some corner cases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, I needed a better approach.
Here are my main requirements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It should detect the exact mode locations and ranges&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should provide reliable results even on noisy samples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should be able to detect multimodality even when some modes are extremely close to each other&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should work out of the box without tricky parameter tuning for each specific distribution&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I failed to find such an algorithm anywhere, so I came up with my own!
The current working title is &amp;ldquo;the lowland multimodality detector.&amp;rdquo;
It takes an estimation of the probability density function (PDF) and tries to find &amp;ldquo;lowlands&amp;rdquo; (areas that are much lower than neighboring peaks).
Next, it splits the plot by these lowlands and detects modes between them.
For the PDF estimation, it uses the
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a> (QRDE-HD)
(see also &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/harrell1982/">&lt;svg class="rating-icon">&lt;use xlink:href="https://aakinshin.net/img/fa/all.svg#paper">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>harrell1982&lt;/a>)
Let me explain how it works in detail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Misleading histograms</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/</guid><description>&lt;p>Below you see two histograms.
What could you say about them?&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/img/hist-riddle-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="hist-riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/img/hist-riddle-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/img/hist-riddle-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="hist-riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-histograms/img/hist-riddle-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Most likely, you say that the first histogram is based on a uniform distribution,
and the second one is based on a multimodal distribution with four modes.
Although this is not obvious from the plots,
both histograms are based on the same sample:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-cs" data-lang="cs">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="m">20.13&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.94&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.03&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.06&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.04&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.98&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.15&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.99&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.20&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.99&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.13&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.22&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.86&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.97&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">19.98&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">20.06&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="m">29.97&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.73&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.75&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.13&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.96&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.82&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.98&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.12&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.18&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.95&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.97&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.82&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.04&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">29.93&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.04&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">30.07&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="m">40.10&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.93&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.05&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.82&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.92&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.91&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.75&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.00&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.02&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.96&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.07&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.92&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.86&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.04&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">39.91&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">40.14&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="m">49.95&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.06&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.03&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">49.92&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.15&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.06&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.00&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.02&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.06&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.00&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">49.70&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.02&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">49.96&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.01&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.05&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">50.13&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Thus, the only difference between histograms is the offset!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Visualization is a simple way to understand the shape of your data.
Unfortunately, this way may easily become a slippery slope.
In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kde-bw/">previous post&lt;/a>, I have shown how density plots may deceive you when the bandwidth is poorly chosen.
Today, we talk about histograms and why you can&amp;rsquo;t trust them in the general case.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Likelihood Ratio Test for Bimodality in two-component Mixtures with Application to Regional Income Distribution in the EU</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/holzmann2008/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/holzmann2008/</guid><description>A parametric test for bimodality based on the likelihood principle by using two-component mixtures. For the given two normal distributions, the test checks if their mixture is bimodal or unimodal.
Reference Hajo Holzmann, Sebastian Vollmer “A likelihood ratio test for bimodality in two-component mixtures with application to regional income distribution in the EU” (2008) // AStA Advances in Statistical Analysis. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 92. No 1. Pp. 57–69. DOI: 10.1007/s10182-008-0057-2
Abstract We propose a parametric test for bimodality based on the likelihood principle by using two-component mixtures. The test uses explicit characterizations of the modal structure of such mixtures in terms of their parameters. Examples include the univariate and multivariate normal distributions and the von Mises distribution. We present the asymptotic distribution of the proposed test and analyze its finite sample performance in a simulation study. To illustrate our method, we use mixtures to investigate the modal structure of the cross-sectional distribution of per capita log GDP across EU regions from 1977 to 1993. Although these mixtures clearly have two components over the whole time period, the resulting distributions evolve from bimodality toward unimodality at the end of the 1970s.
Bib @Article{holzmann2008, title = {A likelihood ratio test for bimodality in two-component mixtures with application to regional income distribution in the EU}, abstract = {We propose a parametric test for bimodality based on the likelihood principle by using two-component mixtures. The test uses explicit characterizations of the modal structure of such mixtures in terms of their parameters. Examples include the univariate and multivariate normal distributions and the von Mises distribution. We present the asymptotic distribution of the proposed test and analyze its finite sample performance in a simulation study. To illustrate our method, we use mixtures to investigate the modal structure of the cross-sectional distribution of per capita log GDP across EU regions from 1977 to 1993.</description></item><item><title>A Typing Error in Tokeshi’s Test of Bimodality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/barreto2003/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/barreto2003/</guid><description>Reference S. Barreto, P.A.V. Borges, Q. Guo “A typing error in Tokeshi’s test of bimodality” (2003) // Global Ecology and Biogeography. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 12. No 2. Pp. 173–174. DOI: 10.1046/j.1466-822x.2003.00018.x
Bib @Article{barreto2003, title = {A typing error in Tokeshi’s test of bimodality}, volume = {12}, issn = {1466-8238}, doi = {10.1046/j.1466-822x.2003.00018.x}, number = {2}, journal = {Global Ecology and Biogeography}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Barreto, S. and Borges, P.A.V. and Guo, Q.}, year = {2003}, month = {mar}, pages = {173–174} }</description></item><item><title>An Algorithm for Assessing Bimodality vs. Unimodality in a Univariate Distribution</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/larkin1979/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/larkin1979/</guid><description>Reference Ronald P. Larkin “An algorithm for assessing bimodality vs. unimodality in a univariate distribution” (1979) // Behavior Research Methods &amp;amp; Instrumentation. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 11. No 4. Pp. 467–468. DOI: 10.3758/bf03205709
Bib @Article{larkin1979, title = {An algorithm for assessing bimodality vs. unimodality in a univariate distribution}, volume = {11}, issn = {1554-3528}, doi = {10.3758/bf03205709}, number = {4}, journal = {Behavior Research Methods &amp;amp;amp; Instrumentation}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Larkin, Ronald P.}, year = {1979}, month = {jul}, pages = {467–468} }</description></item><item><title>Analysis of Bimodality in Histograms Formed from GALLEX and GNO Solar Neutrino Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/sturrock2008/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/sturrock2008/</guid><description>Reference P. A. Sturrock “Analysis of Bimodality in Histograms Formed from GALLEX and GNO Solar Neutrino Data” (2008) // Solar Physics. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 249. No 1. Pp. 1–10. DOI: 10.1007/s11207-008-9170-3
Bib @Article{sturrock2008, title = {Analysis of Bimodality in Histograms Formed from GALLEX and GNO Solar Neutrino Data}, volume = {249}, issn = {1573-093X}, doi = {10.1007/s11207-008-9170-3}, number = {1}, journal = {Solar Physics}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Sturrock, P. A.}, year = {2008}, month = {apr}, pages = {1–10} }</description></item><item><title>Assessing Bimodality to Detect the Presence of a Dual Cognitive Process</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/freeman2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/freeman2012/</guid><description>Reference Jonathan B. Freeman, Rick Dale “Assessing bimodality to detect the presence of a dual cognitive process” (2012) // Behavior Research Methods. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 45. No 1. Pp. 83–97. DOI: 10.3758/s13428-012-0225-x
Bib @Article{freeman2012, title = {Assessing bimodality to detect the presence of a dual cognitive process}, volume = {45}, issn = {1554-3528}, doi = {10.3758/s13428-012-0225-x}, number = {1}, journal = {Behavior Research Methods}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Freeman, Jonathan B. and Dale, Rick}, year = {2012}, month = {jul}, pages = {83–97} }</description></item><item><title>Bimodality in Tropical Water Vapour</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zhang2003/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zhang2003/</guid><description>Reference Chidong Zhang, Brian E. Mapes, Brian J. Soden “Bimodality in tropical water vapour” (2003) // Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 129. No 594. Pp. 2847–2866. DOI: 10.1256/qj.02.166
Bib @Article{zhang2003, title = {Bimodality in tropical water vapour}, volume = {129}, issn = {1477-870X}, doi = {10.1256/qj.02.166}, number = {594}, journal = {Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Zhang, Chidong and Mapes, Brian E. and Soden, Brian J.}, year = {2003}, month = {oct}, pages = {2847–2866} }</description></item><item><title>Brazos River Bar [Texas]; A Study in the Significance of Grain Size Parameters</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/folk1957/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/folk1957/</guid><description>Reference R. L. Folk, W. C. Ward “Brazos River bar [Texas]; a study in the significance of grain size parameters” (1957) // Journal of Sedimentary Research. Publisher: Society for Sedimentary Geology. Vol. 27. No 1. Pp. 3–26. DOI: 10.1306/74d70646-2b21-11d7-8648000102c1865d
Bib @Article{folk1957, title = {Brazos River bar [Texas]; a study in the significance of grain size parameters}, volume = {27}, issn = {1527-1404}, doi = {10.1306/74d70646-2b21-11d7-8648000102c1865d}, number = {1}, journal = {Journal of Sedimentary Research}, publisher = {Society for Sedimentary Geology}, author = {Folk, R. L. and Ward, W. C.}, year = {1957}, month = {mar}, pages = {3–26} }</description></item><item><title>Critical Shear Stress of Natural Sediments</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wilcock1993/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wilcock1993/</guid><description>Reference Peter R. Wilcock “Critical Shear Stress of Natural Sediments” (1993) // Journal of Hydraulic Engineering. Publisher: American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE). Vol. 119. No 4. Pp. 491–505. DOI: 10.1061/(asce)0733-9429(1993)119:4(491)
Bib @Article{wilcock1993, title = {Critical Shear Stress of Natural Sediments}, volume = {119}, issn = {1943-7900}, doi = {10.1061/(asce)0733-9429(1993)119:4(491)}, number = {4}, journal = {Journal of Hydraulic Engineering}, publisher = {American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE)}, author = {Wilcock, Peter R.}, year = {1993}, month = {apr}, pages = {491–505} }</description></item><item><title>Density Estimation and Bump-Hunting by the Penalized Likelihood Method Exemplified by Scattering and Meteorite Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/good1980/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/good1980/</guid><description>Reference I. J. Good, R. A. Gaskins “Density Estimation and Bump-Hunting by the Penalized Likelihood Method Exemplified by Scattering and Meteorite Data” (1980) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Publisher: JSTOR. Vol. 75. No 369. Pp. 42. DOI: 10.2307/2287377
Bib @Article{good1980, title = {Density Estimation and Bump-Hunting by the Penalized Likelihood Method Exemplified by Scattering and Meteorite Data}, volume = {75}, issn = {0162-1459}, doi = {10.2307/2287377}, number = {369}, journal = {Journal of the American Statistical Association}, publisher = {JSTOR}, author = {Good, I. J. and Gaskins, R. A.}, year = {1980}, month = {mar}, pages = {42} }</description></item><item><title>Detecting Bimodality in Astronomical Datasets</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ashman1994/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ashman1994/</guid><description>Reference Keith A. Ashman, Christina M. Bird, Stephen E. Zepf “Detecting bimodality in astronomical datasets” (1994) // The Astronomical Journal. Publisher: American Astronomical Society. Vol. 108. Pp. 2348. DOI: 10.1086/117248
Abstract We discuss statistical techniques for detecting and quantifying bimodality in astronomical datasets. We concentrate on the KMM algorithm, which estimates the statistical significance of bimodality in such datasets and objectively partitions data into sub-populations. By simulating bimodal distributions with a range of properties we investigate the sensitivity of KMM to datasets with varying characteristics. Our results facilitate the planning of optimal observing strategies for systems where bimodality is suspected. Mixture-modeling algorithms similar to the KMM algorithm have been used in previous studies to partition the stellar population of the Milky Way into subsystems. We illustrate the broad applicability of KMM by analysing published data on globular cluster metallicity distributions, velocity distributions of galaxies in clusters, and burst durations of gamma-ray sources. PostScript versions of the tables and figures, as well as FORTRAN code for KMM and instructions for its use, are available by anonymous ftp from kula.phsx.ukans.edu.
Bib @Article{ashman1994, title = {Detecting bimodality in astronomical datasets}, abstract = {We discuss statistical techniques for detecting and quantifying bimodality in astronomical datasets. We concentrate on the KMM algorithm, which estimates the statistical significance of bimodality in such datasets and objectively partitions data into sub-populations. By simulating bimodal distributions with a range of properties we investigate the sensitivity of KMM to datasets with varying characteristics. Our results facilitate the planning of optimal observing strategies for systems where bimodality is suspected. Mixture-modeling algorithms similar to the KMM algorithm have been used in previous studies to partition the stellar population of the Milky Way into subsystems. We illustrate the broad applicability of KMM by analysing published data on globular cluster metallicity distributions, velocity distributions of galaxies in clusters, and burst durations of gamma-ray sources.</description></item><item><title>Dynamics of Distribution in Animal communities: Theory and Analysis</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/tokeshi1992/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/tokeshi1992/</guid><description>Reference Mutsunori Tokeshi “Dynamics of distribution in animal communities: Theory and analysis” (1992) // Population Ecology. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 34. No 2. Pp. 249–273. DOI: 10.1007/bf02514796
Bib @Article{tokeshi1992, title = {Dynamics of distribution in animal communities: Theory and analysis}, volume = {34}, issn = {1438-390X}, doi = {10.1007/bf02514796}, number = {2}, journal = {Population Ecology}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Tokeshi, Mutsunori}, year = {1992}, month = {dec}, pages = {249–273} }</description></item><item><title>Effect of Seed Dimorphism on the density‐dependent Dynamics of Experimental Populations of Atriplex Triangularis (chenopodiaceae)</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ellison1987/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ellison1987/</guid><description>Reference Aaron M. Ellison “Effect of seed dimorphism on the density‐dependent dynamics of experimental populations of atriplex triangularis (chenopodiaceae)” (1987) // American Journal of Botany. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 74. No 8. Pp. 1280–1288. DOI: 10.1002/j.1537-2197.1987.tb08741.x
Bib @Article{ellison1987, title = {Effect of seed dimorphism on the density‐dependent dynamics of experimental populations of atriplex triangularis (chenopodiaceae)}, volume = {74}, issn = {1537-2197}, doi = {10.1002/j.1537-2197.1987.tb08741.x}, number = {8}, journal = {American Journal of Botany}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Ellison, Aaron M.}, year = {1987}, month = {aug}, pages = {1280–1288} }</description></item><item><title>Estimation in Mixtures of Two Normal Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cohen1967/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cohen1967/</guid><description>Reference A. Clifford Cohen “Estimation in Mixtures of Two Normal Distributions” (1967) // Technometrics. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 9. No 1. Pp. 15–28. DOI: 10.1080/00401706.1967.10490438
Bib @Article{cohen1967, title = {Estimation in Mixtures of Two Normal Distributions}, volume = {9}, issn = {1537-2723}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00401706.1967.10490438}, doi = {10.1080/00401706.1967.10490438}, number = {1}, journal = {Technometrics}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Cohen, A. Clifford}, year = {1967}, month = {feb}, pages = {15–28} }</description></item><item><title>Estimation of Parameters for a Mixture of Normal Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hasselblad1966/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hasselblad1966/</guid><description>Reference Victor Hasselblad “Estimation of Parameters for a Mixture of Normal Distributions” (1966) // Technometrics. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 8. No 3. Pp. 431–444. DOI: 10.1080/00401706.1966.10490375
Bib @Article{hasselblad1966, title = {Estimation of Parameters for a Mixture of Normal Distributions}, volume = {8}, issn = {1537-2723}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00401706.1966.10490375}, doi = {10.1080/00401706.1966.10490375}, number = {3}, journal = {Technometrics}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Hasselblad, Victor}, year = {1966}, month = {aug}, pages = {431–444} }</description></item><item><title>Excess Mass Estimates and Tests for Multimodality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/muller1991/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/muller1991/</guid><description>Reference D. W. Müller, G. Sawitzki “Excess Mass Estimates and Tests for Multimodality” (1991) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 86. No 415. Pp. 738–746. DOI: 10.1080/01621459.1991.10475103
Bib @Article{muller1991, title = {Excess Mass Estimates and Tests for Multimodality}, volume = {86}, issn = {1537-274X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01621459.1991.10475103}, doi = {10.1080/01621459.1991.10475103}, number = {415}, journal = {Journal of the American Statistical Association}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Müller, D. W. and Sawitzki, G.}, year = {1991}, month = {sep}, pages = {738–746} }</description></item><item><title>Frequency Trails: Modes and Modality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/cb5645f7ac4f6f375a7a2cd38b58c4e1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/cb5645f7ac4f6f375a7a2cd38b58c4e1/</guid><description>The mvalue approach.</description></item><item><title>Genesis of Bimodal Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/eisenberger1964/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/eisenberger1964/</guid><description>Reference Isidore Eisenberger “Genesis of Bimodal Distributions” (1964) // Technometrics. Publisher: JSTOR. Vol. 6. No 4. Pp. 357. DOI: 10.2307/1266090
Bib @Article{eisenberger1964, title = {Genesis of Bimodal Distributions}, volume = {6}, issn = {0040-1706}, doi = {10.2307/1266090}, number = {4}, journal = {Technometrics}, publisher = {JSTOR}, author = {Eisenberger, Isidore}, year = {1964}, month = {nov}, pages = {357} }</description></item><item><title>Good Things Peak in pairs: A Note on the Bimodality Coefficient</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/pfister2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/pfister2013/</guid><description>Reference Roland Pfister, Katharina A. Schwarz, Markus Janczyk, Rick Dale, Johnathan B. Freeman “Good things peak in pairs: a note on the bimodality coefficient” (2013) // Frontiers in Psychology. Publisher: Frontiers Media SA. Vol. 4. DOI: 10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00700
Bib @Article{pfister2013, title = {Good things peak in pairs: a note on the bimodality coefficient}, volume = {4}, issn = {1664-1078}, doi = {10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00700}, journal = {Frontiers in Psychology}, publisher = {Frontiers Media SA}, author = {Pfister, Roland and Schwarz, Katharina A. and Janczyk, Markus and Dale, Rick and Freeman, Johnathan B.}, year = {2013} }</description></item><item><title>Grain Size and Sorting of Sediments</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c8f7700c-3dae-4b39-ab68-71fd0df31b80/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c8f7700c-3dae-4b39-ab68-71fd0df31b80/</guid><description>Two of the most discussed yet most poorly understood topics in this day of quantitative geology are the concepts of grain size and sorting of sediments. Countless values have veen published by research workers, recorded in innumerable theses, and secreted in oil company files: yet the meaning of all these figures and their ultimate geological significance (if any) are still quite obscure. One can hardly read a month&amp;rsquo;s publications without enountering plots of sorting versus size or distance; countour maps showing values of grain size parameters; or statemenets of the alleged increase of sorting with sediment transport. Despite all this effort, few of these papers attempt to explain why or how the parameters are varying. If this vagueness is true of fairly simple ideas such as mean size or sorting, the situation with regard to more complex parameters like skewness or kurtosis is even worse. Little attempt has been made to relate these measures to the mode of deposition or to environmental characteristcs and most published papers simply tabulate these values without any evident attempt to understand or interpret them. One begins to wonder if all these length computations are not wasted effort — do they show us anything of real value, or are they merely a deceptively impressive shell of figures surrounding a vacumm of geologic meaning?</description></item><item><title>Information for Estimating the Proportions in Mixtures of Exponential and Normal Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hill1963/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/hill1963/</guid><description>Reference Bruce M. Hill “Information for Estimating the Proportions in Mixtures of Exponential and Normal Distributions” (1963) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 58. No 304. Pp. 918–932. DOI: 10.1080/01621459.1963.10480678
Bib @Article{hill1963, title = {Information for Estimating the Proportions in Mixtures of Exponential and Normal Distributions}, volume = {58}, issn = {1537-274X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01621459.1963.10480678}, doi = {10.1080/01621459.1963.10480678}, number = {304}, journal = {Journal of the American Statistical Association}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Hill, Bruce M.}, year = {1963}, month = {dec}, pages = {918–932} }</description></item><item><title>Is Human Height Bimodal?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/schilling2002/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/schilling2002/</guid><description>Reference Mark F Schilling, Ann E Watkins, William Watkins “Is Human Height Bimodal?” (2002) // The American Statistician. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 56. No 3. Pp. 223–229. DOI: 10.1198/00031300265
Abstract The combined distribution of heights of men and women has become the canonical illustration of bimodality when teaching introductory statistics. But is this example appropriate? This article investigates the conditions under which a mixture of two normal distributions is bimodal. A simple justification is presented that a mixture of equally weighted normal distributions with common standard deviation σ is bimodal if and only if the difference between the means of the distributions is greater than 2σ. More generally, a mixture of two normal distributions with similar variability cannot be bimodal unless their means differ by more than approximately the sum oftheirstandard deviations. Examination of national survey data on young adults shows that the separation between the distributions of men&amp;rsquo;s and women&amp;rsquo;s heights is not wide enough to produce bimodality. We suggest reasons why histograms of height nevertheless often appear bimodal.
Bib @Article{schilling2002, title = {Is Human Height Bimodal?}, abstract = {The combined distribution of heights of men and women has become the canonical illustration of bimodality when teaching introductory statistics. But is this example appropriate? This article investigates the conditions under which a mixture of two normal distributions is bimodal. A simple justification is presented that a mixture of equally weighted normal distributions with common standard deviation σ is bimodal if and only if the difference between the means of the distributions is greater than 2σ. More generally, a mixture of two normal distributions with similar variability cannot be bimodal unless their means differ by more than approximately the sum oftheirstandard deviations. Examination of national survey data on young adults shows that the separation between the distributions of men&amp;#39;s and women&amp;#39;s heights is not wide enough to produce bimodality.</description></item><item><title>Measuring Agreement in Ordered Rating Scales</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/van2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/van2001/</guid><description>Reference Cees Van Der Eijk “Measuring Agreement in Ordered Rating Scales” (2001) // Quality and Quantity. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 35. No 3. Pp. 325–341. DOI: 10.1023/a:1010374114305
Abstract Ordered rating scales are one of the most frequently used question formats in large-scale surveys. Analysts of the responses to such questions often find themselves in need of describing the degree of agreement (concentration, consensus) of the answers to such questions. For that purpose they commonly use standard deviations of the response distributions, or measures based on these (such as the coefficient of consensus defined by Granberg and Holmberg, 1988), or the coefficient of variability, etc. This paper demonstrates that such measures are inappropriate for this purpose because they misrepresent what they are supposed to measure: the `peakedness&amp;rsquo; of a distribution. As an alternative a measure of agreement A is proposed. This measure is a weighted average of the degree of agreement that exists in the simple component parts – layers – into which any frequency distribution can be disaggregated, and for which agreement can be expressed in a straightforward and unequivocal way.
Bib @Article{van2001, title = {Measuring Agreement in Ordered Rating Scales}, abstract = {Ordered rating scales are one of the most frequently used question formats in large-scale surveys. Analysts of the responses to such questions often find themselves in need of describing the degree of agreement (concentration, consensus) of the answers to such questions. For that purpose they commonly use standard deviations of the response distributions, or measures based on these (such as the coefficient of consensus defined by Granberg and Holmberg, 1988), or the coefficient of variability, etc. This paper demonstrates that such measures are inappropriate for this purpose because they misrepresent what they are supposed to measure: the `peakedness&amp;#39; of a distribution. As an alternative a measure of agreement A is proposed.</description></item><item><title>Measuring and Defining Bimodal sediments: Problems and Implications</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/smith1997/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/smith1997/</guid><description>Reference G. H. Sambrook Smith, A. P. Nicholas, R. I. Ferguson “Measuring and defining bimodal sediments: Problems and implications” (1997) // Water Resources Research. Publisher: American Geophysical Union (AGU). Vol. 33. No 5. Pp. 1179–1185. DOI: 10.1029/97wr00365
Bib @Article{smith1997, title = {Measuring and defining bimodal sediments: Problems and implications}, volume = {33}, issn = {1944-7973}, doi = {10.1029/97wr00365}, number = {5}, journal = {Water Resources Research}, publisher = {American Geophysical Union (AGU)}, author = {Smith, G. H. Sambrook and Nicholas, A. P. and Ferguson, R. I.}, year = {1997}, month = {may}, pages = {1179–1185} }</description></item><item><title>Nonparametric Testing of the Existence of Modes</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/minnotte1997/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/minnotte1997/</guid><description>Reference Michael C. Minnotte “Nonparametric testing of the existence of modes” (1997) // The Annals of Statistics. Publisher: Institute of Mathematical Statistics. Vol. 25. No 4. DOI: 10.1214/aos/1031594735
Bib @Article{minnotte1997, title = {Nonparametric testing of the existence of modes}, volume = {25}, issn = {0090-5364}, doi = {10.1214/aos/1031594735}, number = {4}, journal = {The Annals of Statistics}, publisher = {Institute of Mathematical Statistics}, author = {Minnotte, Michael C.}, year = {1997}, month = {aug} }</description></item><item><title>Notes on the Analysis of Mixed frequency1 Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cox1966/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cox1966/</guid><description>Reference D. R. Cox “Notes on the analysis of mixed frequency1 distributions” (1966) // British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 19. No 1. Pp. 39–47. DOI: 10.1111/j.2044-8317.1966.tb00353.x
Bib @Article{cox1966, title = {Notes on the analysis of mixed frequency1 distributions}, volume = {19}, issn = {2044-8317}, doi = {10.1111/j.2044-8317.1966.tb00353.x}, number = {1}, journal = {British Journal of Mathematical and Statistical Psychology}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Cox, D. R.}, year = {1966}, month = {may}, pages = {39–47} }</description></item><item><title>On the Modes of a Mixture of Two Normal Distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/behboodian1970/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/behboodian1970/</guid><description>Reference Javad Behboodian “On the Modes of a Mixture of Two Normal Distributions” (1970) // Technometrics. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 12. No 1. Pp. 131–139. DOI: 10.1080/00401706.1970.10488640
Bib @Article{behboodian1970, title = {On the Modes of a Mixture of Two Normal Distributions}, volume = {12}, issn = {1537-2723}, doi = {10.1080/00401706.1970.10488640}, number = {1}, journal = {Technometrics}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Behboodian, Javad}, year = {1970}, month = {feb}, pages = {131–139} }</description></item><item><title>One Sample Tests for the Location of Modes of Nonnormal Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/carolan2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/carolan2001/</guid><description>Reference Anthony M. Carolan, J. C. W. Rayner “One sample tests for the location of modes of nonnormal data” (2001) // Journal of Applied Mathematics and Decision Sciences. Publisher: Hindawi Limited. Vol. 5. No 1. Pp. 1–19. DOI: 10.1155/s1173912601000013
Bib @Article{carolan2001, title = {One sample tests for the location of modes of nonnormal data}, volume = {5}, issn = {1173-9126}, doi = {10.1155/s1173912601000013}, number = {1}, journal = {Journal of Applied Mathematics and Decision Sciences}, publisher = {Hindawi Limited}, author = {Carolan, Anthony M. and Rayner, J. C. W.}, year = {2001}, month = {jan}, pages = {1–19} }</description></item><item><title>Simple Tests for Bimodality and Bitangentiality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/haldane1951/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/haldane1951/</guid><description>Reference J. B. S. Haldane “Simple tests for bimodality and bitangentiality” (1951) // Annals of Eugenics. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 16. No 1. Pp. 359–364. DOI: 10.1111/j.1469-1809.1951.tb02488.x
Bib @Article{haldane1951, title = {Simple tests for bimodality and bitangentiality}, volume = {16}, issn = {2050-1439}, doi = {10.1111/j.1469-1809.1951.tb02488.x}, number = {1}, journal = {Annals of Eugenics}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Haldane, J. B. S.}, year = {1951}, month = {jan}, pages = {359–364} }</description></item><item><title>Split-And-Merge Procedure for Image Segmentation Using Bimodality Detection Approach</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/chaudhuri2010/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/chaudhuri2010/</guid><description>Reference D. Chaudhuri, A. Agrawal “Split-and-merge Procedure for Image Segmentation using Bimodality Detection Approach” (2010) // Defence Science Journal. Publisher: Defence Scientific Information and Documentation Centre. Vol. 60. No 3. Pp. 290–301. DOI: 10.14429/dsj.60.356
Bib @Article{chaudhuri2010, title = {Split-and-merge Procedure for Image Segmentation using Bimodality Detection Approach}, volume = {60}, issn = {0976-464X}, doi = {10.14429/dsj.60.356}, number = {3}, journal = {Defence Science Journal}, publisher = {Defence Scientific Information and Documentation Centre}, author = {Chaudhuri, D. and Agrawal, A.}, year = {2010}, month = {mar}, pages = {290–301} }</description></item><item><title>The Bimodality Index: A Criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wang2009/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wang2009/</guid><description>Reference Jing Wang, Sijin Wen, W. Fraser Symmans, Lajos Pusztai, Kevin R. Coombes “The Bimodality Index: A criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data” (2009) // Cancer Informatics. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 7. Pp. CIN.S2846. DOI: 10.4137/cin.s2846
Bib @Article{wang2009, title = {The Bimodality Index: A criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data}, volume = {7}, issn = {1176-9351}, doi = {10.4137/cin.s2846}, journal = {Cancer Informatics}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Wang, Jing and Wen, Sijin and Symmans, W. Fraser and Pusztai, Lajos and Coombes, Kevin R.}, year = {2009}, month = {jan}, pages = {CIN.S2846} }</description></item><item><title>The MAP Test for Multimodality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/rozal1994/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/rozal1994/</guid><description>Reference Gregory Paul M. Rozal, J. A. Hartigan “The MAP test for multimodality” (1994) // Journal of Classification. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 11. No 1. Pp. 5–36. DOI: 10.1007/bf01201021
Bib @Article{rozal1994, title = {The MAP test for multimodality}, volume = {11}, issn = {1432-1343}, doi = {10.1007/bf01201021}, number = {1}, journal = {Journal of Classification}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Rozal, Gregory Paul M. and Hartigan, J. A.}, year = {1994}, month = {mar}, pages = {5–36} }</description></item><item><title>Transformations of Bimodal Distriburtions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/baker1930/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/baker1930/</guid><description>Reference G. A. Baker “Transformations of Bimodal Distriburtions” (1930) // The Annals of Mathematical Statistics. Publisher: Institute of Mathematical Statistics. Vol. 1. No 4. Pp. 334–344. DOI: 10.1214/aoms/1177733063
Bib @Article{baker1930, title = {Transformations of Bimodal Distriburtions}, volume = {1}, issn = {0003-4851}, doi = {10.1214/aoms/1177733063}, number = {4}, journal = {The Annals of Mathematical Statistics}, publisher = {Institute of Mathematical Statistics}, author = {Baker, G. A.}, year = {1930}, month = {nov}, pages = {334–344} }</description></item><item><title>Tree Cover Bimodality in Savannas and Forests Emerging from the Switching Between Two Fire Dynamics</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/de2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/de2014/</guid><description>Reference Carlo De Michele, Francesco Accatino, Gennady Cymbalyuk “Tree Cover Bimodality in Savannas and Forests Emerging from the Switching between Two Fire Dynamics” (2014) // PLoS ONE. Publisher: Public Library of Science (PLoS). Vol. 9. No 3. Pp. e91195. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0091195
Abstract Moist savannas and tropical forests share the same climatic conditions and occur side by side. Experimental evidences show that the tree cover of these ecosystems exhibits a bimodal frequency distribution. This is considered as a proof of savanna–forest bistability, predicted by dynamic vegetation models based on non-linear differential equations. Here, we propose a change of perspective about the bimodality of tree cover distribution. We show, using a simple matrix model of tree dynamics, how the bimodality of tree cover can emerge from the switching between two linear dynamics of trees, one in presence and one in absence of fire, with a feedback between fire and trees. As consequence, we find that the transitions between moist savannas and tropical forests, if sharp, are not necessarily catastrophic.
Bib @Article{de2014, title = {Tree Cover Bimodality in Savannas and Forests Emerging from the Switching between Two Fire Dynamics}, abstract = {Moist savannas and tropical forests share the same climatic conditions and occur side by side. Experimental evidences show that the tree cover of these ecosystems exhibits a bimodal frequency distribution. This is considered as a proof of savanna–forest bistability, predicted by dynamic vegetation models based on non-linear differential equations. Here, we propose a change of perspective about the bimodality of tree cover distribution. We show, using a simple matrix model of tree dynamics, how the bimodality of tree cover can emerge from the switching between two linear dynamics of trees, one in presence and one in absence of fire, with a feedback between fire and trees. As consequence, we find that the transitions between moist savannas and tropical forests, if sharp, are not necessarily catastrophic.</description></item><item><title>Using Kernel Density Estimates to Investigate Multimodality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/silverman1981/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/silverman1981/</guid><description>Reference B. W. Silverman “Using Kernel Density Estimates to Investigate Multimodality” (1981) // Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Methodological). Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 43. No 1. Pp. 97–99. DOI: 10.1111/j.2517-6161.1981.tb01155.x
Bib @Article{silverman1981, title = {Using Kernel Density Estimates to Investigate Multimodality}, volume = {43}, issn = {2517-6161}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.2517-6161.1981.tb01155.x}, doi = {10.1111/j.2517-6161.1981.tb01155.x}, number = {1}, journal = {Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Methodological)}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Silverman, B. W.}, year = {1981}, month = {sep}, pages = {97–99} }</description></item></channel></rss>