<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PDF on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/pdf/</link><description>Recent content in PDF on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/pdf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The idea of this post was born when I was working on a presentation for my recent &lt;a href="https://dotnext.ru/en/">DotNext&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gc3yVybPuaY&amp;list=PL21xssNXOJNGUROqzSTOC8uZL4W2QZpvK&amp;index=1">talk&lt;/a>.
It had a &lt;a href="https://slides.aakinshin.net/dotnext-piter2020/#193">slide&lt;/a> with a density plot like this:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-light.png" target="_blank" alt="riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Here we can see a density plot based on a sample with highlighted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decile">decile&lt;/a> locations that split the plot into 10 equal parts.
Before the conference, I have been reviewed by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/VladimirSitnikv">@VladimirSitnikv&lt;/a>.
He raised a reasonable concern: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like all the density plot segments are equal and contain exactly 10% of the whole plot.
And he was right!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t make any miscalculations.
I generated a real sample with 61 elements.
Next, I build a density plot with the kernel density estimation (KDE) using the Sheather &amp;amp; Jones method and the normal kernel.
Next, I calculated decile values using the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
Although both the density plot and the decile values are calculated correctly and consistent with the sample,
they are not consistent with each other!
Indeed, such a density plot is just an estimation of the underlying distribution.
It has its own decile values, which are not equal to the sample decile values regardless of the used quantile estimator.
This problem is common for different kinds of visualization that presents density and quantiles at the same time (e.g., &lt;a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/violin-plots-explained-fb1d115e023d">violin plots&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It leads us to a question: how should we present the shape of our data together with quantile values without confusing inconsistency in the final image?
Today I will present a good solution: we should use the quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator!
I know the title is a bit long, but it&amp;rsquo;s not so complicated as it sounds.
In this post, I will show how to build such plots.
Also I will compare them to the classic histograms and kernel density estimations.
As a bonus, I will demonstrate how awesome these plots are for multimodality detection.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>