<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Monika K Krzyzanowska on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/monika-k-krzyzanowska/</link><description>Recent content in Monika K Krzyzanowska on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/monika-k-krzyzanowska/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bedard2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bedard2007/</guid><description>Reference Philippe L Bedard, Monika K Krzyzanowska, Melania Pintilie, Ian F Tannock “Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings” (2007) // Journal of Clinical Oncology. Publisher: American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO). Vol. 25. No 23. Pp. 3482–3487. DOI: 10.1200/jco.2007.11.3670
Bib @Article{bedard2007, title = {Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings}, volume = {25}, issn = {1527-7755}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2007.11.3670}, doi = {10.1200/jco.2007.11.3670}, number = {23}, journal = {Journal of Clinical Oncology}, publisher = {American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO)}, author = {Bedard, Philippe L and Krzyzanowska, Monika K and Pintilie, Melania and Tannock, Ian F}, year = {2007}, month = {aug}, pages = {3482–3487} }</description></item><item><title>Underpowered Negative Clinical Trials</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/10189519-eb48-41f5-a1ca-adac8092bf8e/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/10189519-eb48-41f5-a1ca-adac8092bf8e/</guid><description>Our survey of 423 negative clinical trials indicates that 55% of trials had too few participants to detect a medium effect size in favor of the experimental over the standard treatment arm for their primary end point with at least 80% statistical power. Although underpowered negative clinical trials have been widely reported in the general medical and subspecialty literature, there are few reports relating to trials evaluating treatment of cancer. A review of 22 negative randomized oncology trials published in major general medical or oncology journals during a 1-year period found that 16 trials (73%) lacked adequate statistical power to detect a 50% improvement in median survival in favor of the experimental arm.</description></item></channel></rss>