<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dinis Pestana on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/dinis-pestana/</link><description>Recent content in Dinis Pestana on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/dinis-pestana/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Simple Generalisation of the Hill Estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fatima2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fatima2013/</guid><description>Reference M Fátima Brilhante, M Ivette Gomes, Dinis Pestana “A simple generalisation of the Hill estimator” (2013) // Computational Statistics &amp;amp; Data Analysis. Vol. 57. No 1. Pp. 518–535. DOI: 10.1016/j.csda.2012.07.019
Abstract The classical Hill estimator of a positive extreme value index (EVI) can be regarded as the logarithm of the geometric mean, or equivalently the logarithm of the mean of order p=0, of a set of adequate statistics. A simple generalisation of the Hill estimator is now proposed, considering a more general mean of order p≥0 of the same statistics. Apart from the derivation of the asymptotic behaviour of this new class of EVI-estimators, an asymptotic comparison, at optimal levels, of the members of such class and other known EVI-estimators is undertaken. An algorithm for an adaptive estimation of the tuning parameters under play is also provided. A large-scale simulation study and an application to simulated and real data are developed.
Bib @Article{fatima2013, title = {A simple generalisation of the Hill estimator}, volume = {57}, issn = {0167-9473}, url = {http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167947312002939}, doi = {10.1016/j.csda.2012.07.019}, abstract = {The classical Hill estimator of a positive extreme value index (EVI) can be regarded as the logarithm of the geometric mean, or equivalently the logarithm of the mean of order p=0, of a set of adequate statistics. A simple generalisation of the Hill estimator is now proposed, considering a more general mean of order p≥0 of the same statistics. Apart from the derivation of the asymptotic behaviour of this new class of EVI-estimators, an asymptotic comparison, at optimal levels, of the members of such class and other known EVI-estimators is undertaken. An algorithm for an adaptive estimation of the tuning parameters under play is also provided. A large-scale simulation study and an application to simulated and real data are developed.}, language = {en}, number = {1}, urldate = {2020-06-27}, journal = {Computational Statistics \&amp;amp; Data Analysis}, author = {Fátima Brilhante, M and Ivette Gomes, M and Pestana, Dinis}, month = {jan}, year = {2013}, keywords = {Bias estimation, Bootstrap methodology, Heavy tails, Optimal levels, Semi-parametric estimation, Statistics of extremes}, pages = {518--535} }</description></item></channel></rss>