<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cal Newport on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/cal-newport/</link><description>Recent content in Cal Newport on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/cal-newport/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-deep-work/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-deep-work/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s a fine book, but some parts are a little dry and boring. Main insights are quite basic and common for GTD books, examples are lengthy.
The book consists of two parts: &amp;ldquo;The Idea&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;The Rules&amp;rdquo;.
The first part covers the general philosophy behind the concept of deep work. Deep work is a state of mind, in which one is extremely focused and productive and is capable of achieving a lot within a short period. True deep work is a rare mental state, and one should train their skills to develop an ability to enter it.
The second part is mostly a set of practical recommendations, most of which are classic:
Quit social media, disable notifications and messengers Schedule a day in advance, and allocate time for deep work (max: 4-5 hours) Set up rituals for deep work (start, end); shutdown ritual at the end of the day Artifical deadlines Boredom - a useful exercise for training life without distractions Review all activities and remove everything that doesn&amp;rsquo;t justify time spent Setting a cutoff point (Don&amp;rsquo;t do any work after xx:yy pm) Productive meditation: think about a dedicated problem during a walk/run/cleaning and don&amp;rsquo;t get distracted The author introduces the following classification of various regimes of deep work:
Bimodal philosophy: live as usual, but sometimes go to the woods for a month of deep work Rhythmic philosophy: live by the schedule, allocate n hours for deep work daily Journalist philosophy: be ready to switch to deep work at any moment once there is an opportunity for that The introduced deep work and shallow work are similar concepts to hyperfocus and scatterfocus from Hyperfocus.
Most references are to online resources, not so much to scientific papers.
In Chapter 1, there is a shallow discussion of leroy2009, but no notes about the effect size.</description></item><item><title>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-digital-minimalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-digital-minimalism/</guid><description/></item><item><title>So Good They Can't Ignore You: Why Skills Trump Passion in the Quest for Work You Love</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-so-good-they-cant-ignore-you/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-so-good-they-cant-ignore-you/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>