<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research: Resistance to the low-density regions on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-rldr/</link><description>Recent content in Research: Resistance to the low-density regions on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-rldr/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Resistance to the low-density regions: the Hodges-Lehmann location estimator based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hlhd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hlhd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Previously, I have discussed the topic of the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-rldr/">resistance to the low-density regions&lt;/a>
of various estimators including &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hl/">the Hodges-Lehmann location estimator&lt;/a> ($\operatorname{HL}$).
In general, $\operatorname{HL}$ is a great estimator with great statistical efficiency and a decent breakdown point.
Unfortunately, it has low resistance to the low-density regions around
$29^\textrm{th}$ and $71^\textrm{th}$ percentiles, which may cause troubles in the case of multimodal distributions.
I am trying to find a modification of $\operatorname{HL}$
that performs almost the same as the original $\operatorname{HL}$, but has increased resistance.
One of the ideas I had was using the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
instead of the sample median to evaluate $\operatorname{HL}$.
Regrettably, this idea did not turn out to be successful:
such an estimator has a resistance function similar to the original $\operatorname{HL}$.
I believe that it is important to share negative results, and therefore this post contains a bunch of plots,
which illustrate results of relevant numerical simulations.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resistance to the low-density regions: the Hodges-Lehmann location estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hl/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous posts, I discussed the concept of a resistance function
that shows the sensitivity of the given estimator to the low-density regions.
I already showed how this function behaves for &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-mean-median/">the mean, the sample median&lt;/a>,
and &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hdmedian/">the Harrell-Davis median&lt;/a>.
In this post, I explore this function for the Hodges-Lehmann location estimator.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resistance to the low-density regions: the Harrell-Davis median</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hdmedian/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-hdmedian/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-mean-median/">previous post&lt;/a>,
we defined the resistance function that show sensitivity of the given estimator
to the low-density regions.
We also showed the resistance function plots for the mean and the sample median.
In this post, we explore corresponding plots for the Harrell-Davis median.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Resistance to the low-density regions: the mean and the median</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-mean-median/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/rldr-mean-median/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we discuss resistant statistics, we typically assume resistance to extreme values.
However, extreme values are not the only problem source
that can violate usual assumptions about expected metric distribution.
The low-density regions which often arise in multimodal distributions
can also corrupt the results of the statistical analysis.
In this post, I discuss this problem and introduce a measure of resistance to low-density regions.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>