<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Robert G Staudte on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/robert-g-staudte/</link><description>Recent content in Robert G Staudte on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/robert-g-staudte/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Robust analogs to the Coefficient of Variation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/arachchige2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/arachchige2020/</guid><description>Reference Chandima N P G Arachchige, Luke A Prendergast, Robert G Staudte “Robust analogs to the Coefficient of Variation” (2020) // Journal of Applied Statistics. Vol. 49. No 2. Pp. 268–290. DOI: 10.1080/02664763.2020.1808599
Abstract The coefficient of variation (CV) is commonly used to measure relative dispersion. However, since it is based on the sample mean and standard deviation, outliers can adversely affect the CV. Additionally, for skewed distributions the mean and standard deviation do not have natural interpretations and, consequently, neither does the CV. Here we investigate the extent to which quantile-based measures of relative dispersion can provide appropriate summary information as an alternative to the CV. In particular, we investigate two measures, the first being the interquartile range (in lieu of the standard deviation), divided by the median (in lieu of the mean), and the second being the median absolute deviation (MAD), divided by the median, as robust estimators of relative dispersion. In addition to comparing the influence functions of the competing estimators and their asymptotic biases and variances, we compare interval estimators using simulation studies to assess coverage.
Bib @Article{arachchige2020, title = {Robust analogs to the Coefficient of Variation}, volume = {49}, issn = {0266-4763, 1360-0532}, url = {http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01110}, doi = {10.1080/02664763.2020.1808599}, abstract = {The coefficient of variation (CV) is commonly used to measure relative dispersion. However, since it is based on the sample mean and standard deviation, outliers can adversely affect the CV. Additionally, for skewed distributions the mean and standard deviation do not have natural interpretations and, consequently, neither does the CV. Here we investigate the extent to which quantile-based measures of relative dispersion can provide appropriate summary information as an alternative to the CV. In particular, we investigate two measures, the first being the interquartile range (in lieu of the standard deviation), divided by the median (in lieu of the mean), and the second being the median absolute deviation (MAD), divided by the median, as robust estimators of relative dispersion.</description></item></channel></rss>