<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Performance Telemetry on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/performance-telemetry/</link><description>Recent content in Performance Telemetry on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/performance-telemetry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>P² quantile estimator: estimating the median without storing values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/p2-quantile-estimator-intro/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/p2-quantile-estimator-intro/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update: the estimator accuracy could be improved using a bunch of &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/p2-quantile-estimator/">patches&lt;/a>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine that you are implementing performance telemetry in your application.
There is an operation that is executed millions of times, and you want to get its &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; duration.
It&amp;rsquo;s not a good idea to use the arithmetic mean because the obtained value can be easily spoiled by outliers.
It&amp;rsquo;s much better to use the median which is one of the most robust ways to describe the average.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The straightforward median estimation approach requires storing all the values.
In our case, it&amp;rsquo;s a bad idea to keep all the values because it will significantly increase the memory footprint.
Such telemetry is harmful because it may become a new bottleneck instead of monitoring the actual performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another way to get the median value is to use a sequential quantile estimator
(also known as an online quantile estimator or a streaming quantile estimator).
This is an algorithm that allows calculating the median value (or any other quantile value)
using a fixed amount of memory.
Of course, it provides only an approximation of the real median value,
but it&amp;rsquo;s usually enough for typical telemetry use cases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I will show one of the simplest sequential quantile estimators that is called the P² quantile estimator
(or the Piecewise-Parabolic quantile estimator).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>