<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Holger J Schünemann on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/holger-j-sch%C3%BCnemann/</link><description>Recent content in Holger J Schünemann on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/holger-j-sch%C3%BCnemann/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Early stopping of RCTs</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7c744647-3299-4d41-b73f-85556e2d6e91/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7c744647-3299-4d41-b73f-85556e2d6e91/</guid><description>RCTs stopped early for benefit are becoming more common, often fail to adequately report relevant information about the decision to stop early, and show implausibly large treatment effects, particularly when the number of events is small. These findings suggest clinicians should view the results of such trials with skepticism.</description></item><item><title>Randomized Trials Stopped Early for Benefit: A Systematic Review</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/montori2005/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/montori2005/</guid><description>Reference Victor M Montori, P J Devereaux, Neill K J Adhikari, Karen E A Burns, Christoph H Eggert, Matthias Briel, Christina Lacchetti, Teresa W Leung, Elizabeth Darling, Dianne M Bryant, Heiner C Bucher, Holger J Schünemann, Maureen O Meade, Deborah J Cook, Patricia J Erwin, Amit Sood, Richa Sood, Benjamin Lo, Carly A Thompson, Qi Zhou, Edward Mills, Gordon H Guyatt “Randomized Trials Stopped Early for Benefit: A Systematic Review” (2005) // JAMA. Publisher: American Medical Association (AMA). Vol. 294. No 17. Pp. 2203. DOI: 10.1001/jama.294.17.2203
Bib @Article{montori2005, title = {Randomized Trials Stopped Early for Benefit: A Systematic Review}, volume = {294}, issn = {0098-7484}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1001/jama.294.17.2203}, doi = {10.1001/jama.294.17.2203}, number = {17}, journal = {JAMA}, publisher = {American Medical Association (AMA)}, author = {Montori, Victor M and Devereaux, P J and Adhikari, Neill K J and Burns, Karen E A and Eggert, Christoph H and Briel, Matthias and Lacchetti, Christina and Leung, Teresa W and Darling, Elizabeth and Bryant, Dianne M and Bucher, Heiner C and Schünemann, Holger J and Meade, Maureen O and Cook, Deborah J and Erwin, Patricia J and Sood, Amit and Sood, Richa and Lo, Benjamin and Thompson, Carly A and Zhou, Qi and Mills, Edward and Guyatt, Gordon H}, year = {2005}, month = {nov}, pages = {2203} }</description></item></channel></rss>