<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Quantile-Respectful Density Estimation on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/qrde/</link><description>Recent content in Quantile-Respectful Density Estimation on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/qrde/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Improving quantile-respectful density estimation for discrete distributions using jittering</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-discrete/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-discrete/</guid><description>&lt;p>In my previous posts, I already discussed the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kde-discrete/">problem&lt;/a> that arise
when we try to build the kernel density estimation (KDE) for samples with ties.
We may get such samples in real life from discrete or mixed discrete/continuous distributions.
Even if the original distribution is continuous,
we may observe artificial sample discretization due to a limited resolution of the measuring tool.
Such discretization may lead to inaccurate density plots due to undersmoothing.
The problem can be resolved using a nice technique called &lt;em>jittering&lt;/em>.
I also discussed &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/">how to apply&lt;/a> jittering to get a smoother version of KDE.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I&amp;rsquo;m not a huge fan of KDE because of two reasons.
The first one is the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/kde-bw/">problem of choosing a proper bandwidth value&lt;/a>.
With poorly chosen bandwidth, we can easily get oversmoothing or undersmoothing even without the discretization problem.
The second one is an inconsistency between the KDE-based probability density function and evaluated sample quantiles.
It could lead to inconsistent visualizations (e.g., KDE-based violin plots with non-KDE-based quantile values)
or it could introduce problems for algorithms that require density function and quantile values at the same time.
The inconsistency could be resolved using &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimation&lt;/a> (QRDE).
This kind of estimation builds the density function which matches the evaluated sample quantiles.
To get a smooth QRDE, we also need a smooth quantile estimator like the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
The robustness and componential efficiency of this approach can be improved using
the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/winsorized-hdqe/">winsorized&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed&lt;/a>
modifications of the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator
(which also have a &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/wthdqe-efficiency/">decent statistical efficiency level&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, the straightforward QRDE calculation is not always applicable for samples with ties
because it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to build an &amp;ldquo;honest&amp;rdquo; density function for discrete distributions
without using the Dirac delta function.
This is a severe problem for QRDE-based algorithms like the
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/">lowland multimodality detection algorithm&lt;/a>.
In this post, I will show how jittering could help to solve this problem and get a smooth QRDE on samples with ties.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Plain-text summary notation for multimodal distributions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you collected a lot of data and want to explore the underlying distributions of collected samples.
If you have only a few distributions, the best way to do that is to look at the density plots
(expressed via histograms, kernel density estimations, or &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimations&lt;/a>).
However, it&amp;rsquo;s not always possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suppose you have to process dozens, hundreds, or even thousands of distributions.
In that case,
it may be extremely time-consuming to manually check visualizations of each distribution.
If you analyze distributions from the command line or send notifications about suspicious samples,
it may be impossible to embed images in the reports.
In these cases, there is a need to present a distribution using plain text.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One way to do that is plain text histograms.
Unfortunately, this kind of visualization may occupy o lot of space.
In complicated cases, you may need 20 or 30 lines per a single distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another way is to present classic &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summary_statistics">summary statistics&lt;/a>
like mean or median, standard deviation or median absolute deviation, quantiles, skewness, and kurtosis.
There is another problem here:
without experience, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to reconstruct the true distribution shape based on these values.
Even if you are an experienced researcher, the statistical metrics may become misleading in the case of multimodal distributions.
Multimodality is one of the most severe challenges in distribution analysis because it distorts basic summary statistics.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to not only find such distribution but also have a way to present brief information about multimodality effects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, how can we condense the underlying distribution shape of a given sample to a short text line?
I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to find an approach that works fine in my cases, so I came up with my own notation.
Most of the interpretation problems in my experiments arise from multimodality and outliers,
so I decided to focus on these two things and specifically highlight them.
Let&amp;rsquo;s consider this plot:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="thumbnail">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="thumbnail">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/modality-summary-notation/img/thumbnail-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>I suggest describing it like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>1.00, 2.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span> + &lt;span class="o">[&lt;/span>7.16&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> 13.12&lt;span class="o">]&lt;/span>_100 + &lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>19.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span> + &lt;span class="o">[&lt;/span>27.69&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> 32.34&lt;span class="o">]&lt;/span>_100 + &lt;span class="o">{&lt;/span>37.00..39.00&lt;span class="o">}&lt;/span>_3
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Let me explain the suggested notation in detail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Intermodal outliers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outlier">Outlier&lt;/a> analysis is a typical step in distribution exploration.
Usually, we work with the &amp;ldquo;lower outliers&amp;rdquo; (extremely low values) and the &amp;ldquo;upper outliers&amp;rdquo; (extremely high values).
However, outliers are not always extreme values.
In the general case, an outlier is a value that significantly differs from other values in the same sample.
In the case of multimodal distribution, we can also consider outliers in the middle of the distribution.
Let&amp;rsquo;s call such outliers that we found between modes the &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>intermodal outliers&lt;/em>.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="step4">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="step4">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/intermodal-outliers/img/step4-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Look at the above density plot.
It&amp;rsquo;s a bimodal distribution that is formed as a combination of two unimodal distributions.
Each of the unimodal distributions may have its own lower and upper outliers.
When we merge them, the upper outliers of the first distribution and the lower outliers of the second distribution
stop being lower or upper outliers.
However, if these values don&amp;rsquo;t belong to the modes, they still are a subject of interest.
In this post, I will show you how to detect such intermodal outliers
and how they can be used to form a better distribution description.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lowland multimodality detection</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/</guid><description>&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-light.svg" target="_blank" alt="data5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-light.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-dark.svg" target="_blank" alt="data5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/img/data5-dark.svg" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Multimodality is an essential feature of a distribution, which may create many troubles during automatic analysis.
One of the best ways to work with such distributions is to detect all the modes in advance based on the given samples.
Unfortunately, this problem is much harder than it looks like.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I tried many different approaches for multimodality detection, but none of them was good enough.
During the past several years, my approach of choice was the &lt;a href="http://www.brendangregg.com/FrequencyTrails/modes.html">mvalue-based modal test&lt;/a> by Brendan Gregg.
It works nicely in simple cases, but I was constantly stumbling over noisy samples where this algorithm doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce reliable results.
Also, it has some limitations that make it unapplicable to some corner cases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, I needed a better approach.
Here are my main requirements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It should detect the exact mode locations and ranges&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should provide reliable results even on noisy samples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should be able to detect multimodality even when some modes are extremely close to each other&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It should work out of the box without tricky parameter tuning for each specific distribution&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I failed to find such an algorithm anywhere, so I came up with my own!
The current working title is &amp;ldquo;the lowland multimodality detector.&amp;rdquo;
It takes an estimation of the probability density function (PDF) and tries to find &amp;ldquo;lowlands&amp;rdquo; (areas that are much lower than neighboring peaks).
Next, it splits the plot by these lowlands and detects modes between them.
For the PDF estimation, it uses the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/">quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator&lt;/a> (QRDE-HD).
Let me explain how it works in detail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/</guid><description>&lt;p>The idea of this post was born when I was working on a presentation for my recent &lt;a href="https://dotnext.ru/en/">DotNext&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gc3yVybPuaY&amp;list=PL21xssNXOJNGUROqzSTOC8uZL4W2QZpvK&amp;index=1">talk&lt;/a>.
It had a &lt;a href="https://slides.aakinshin.net/dotnext-piter2020/#193">slide&lt;/a> with a density plot like this:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-light.png" target="_blank" alt="riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="riddle">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qrde-hd/img/riddle-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Here we can see a density plot based on a sample with highlighted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decile">decile&lt;/a> locations that split the plot into 10 equal parts.
Before the conference, I have been reviewed by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/VladimirSitnikv">@VladimirSitnikv&lt;/a>.
He raised a reasonable concern: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like all the density plot segments are equal and contain exactly 10% of the whole plot.
And he was right!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t make any miscalculations.
I generated a real sample with 61 elements.
Next, I build a density plot with the kernel density estimation (KDE) using the Sheather &amp;amp; Jones method and the normal kernel.
Next, I calculated decile values using the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
Although both the density plot and the decile values are calculated correctly and consistent with the sample,
they are not consistent with each other!
Indeed, such a density plot is just an estimation of the underlying distribution.
It has its own decile values, which are not equal to the sample decile values regardless of the used quantile estimator.
This problem is common for different kinds of visualization that presents density and quantiles at the same time (e.g., &lt;a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/violin-plots-explained-fb1d115e023d">violin plots&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It leads us to a question: how should we present the shape of our data together with quantile values without confusing inconsistency in the final image?
Today I will present a good solution: we should use the quantile-respectful density estimation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator!
I know the title is a bit long, but it&amp;rsquo;s not so complicated as it sounds.
In this post, I will show how to build such plots.
Also I will compare them to the classic histograms and kernel density estimations.
As a bonus, I will demonstrate how awesome these plots are for multimodality detection.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>