<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Paul E Meehl on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/paul-e-meehl/</link><description>Recent content in Paul E Meehl on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/paul-e-meehl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Eager-beaver researchers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/5a3b8f36-edc5-4e56-bd51-d6fe8c1e0fee/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/5a3b8f36-edc5-4e56-bd51-d6fe8c1e0fee/</guid><description>Meanwhile our eager-beaver researcher, undismayed by logic-of-science considerations and relying blissfully on the “exactitude” of modem statistical hypothesis-testing, has produced a long publication list and been promoted to a full professorship. In terms of his contribution to the enduring body of psychological knowledge, he has done hardly anything. His true position is that of a potent-but-sterile intellectual rake, who leaves in his merry path a long train of ravished maidens but no viable scientific offspring.
First, I found this quote in the paper itself, next rediscovered it in Statistics Done Wrong.</description></item><item><title>My intellectual superiority</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/74f82fe8-c5b2-42c3-ac0b-fb969d32d39e/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/74f82fe8-c5b2-42c3-ac0b-fb969d32d39e/</guid><description>I was aware of my intellectual superiority by age six or earlier.</description></item><item><title>On college professors</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/08bf0dd4-ae92-4925-9a95-4dbcf2079634/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/08bf0dd4-ae92-4925-9a95-4dbcf2079634/</guid><description>While I have mellowed with age and become more tolerant of other people’s frailties (as I hope they are of mine), I must confess that I have never fully recovered from the shock of realizing that one can become a college professor and not be able to think straight.</description></item><item><title>Paul E. Meehl (Autobiography)</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1989/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1989/</guid><description>Reference Paul E Meehl, G Lindzey “Paul E. Meehl (Autobiography)” (1989) // A history of psychology in autobiography. Vol. 8. Pp. 337–389.
Bib @Inbook{meehl1989, author = {Paul E Meehl}, editor = {G Lindzey}, title = {Paul E. Meehl (Autobiography)}, booktitle = {A history of psychology in autobiography}, volume = {8}, language = {en}, year = {1989}, pages = {337--389}, custom-url-pdf = {https://meehl.umn.edu/sites/meehl.umn.edu/files/files/139autobiography.pdf} }</description></item><item><title>People you meet</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/d4fe8282-aebc-4abc-ba8b-e19bb83c98f7/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/d4fe8282-aebc-4abc-ba8b-e19bb83c98f7/</guid><description>Statistically speaking, most of the people you meet will be fair to middling stupid.</description></item><item><title>Recognizing fallacies</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/46d1d9c2-9ed0-46da-848a-eb2685fce777/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/46d1d9c2-9ed0-46da-848a-eb2685fce777/</guid><description>It was excusable to make a mistake, although if you made too many egregious ones you would not be well accepted; but the unpardonable sin was to refuse to recognize that you had committed a fallacy, formal or material, when it was pointed out. A close second major sin would be to keep committing the same fallacy over and over again and having to be reminded of it.</description></item><item><title>Sir. Ronald Fisher</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/01015429-2154-45e1-b36d-9e11757643ca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/01015429-2154-45e1-b36d-9e11757643ca/</guid><description>You may say, “But, Meehl, R. A. Fisher was a genius, and we all know how valuable his stuff has been in agronomy. Why shouldn’t it work for soft psychology?” Well, I am not intimidated by Fisher’s genius, because my complaint is not in the field of mathematical statistics, and as regards inductive logic and philosophy of science, it is well-known that Sir Ronald permitted himself a great deal of dogmatism. I remember my amazement when the late Rudolf Carnap said to me, the first time I met him, “But, of course, on this subject Fisher is just mistaken: surely you must know that.” My statistician friends tell me that it is not clear just how useful the significance test has been in biological science either, but I set that aside as beyond my competence to discuss.</description></item><item><title>The Mother</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/93a73227-bcc9-4a25-9eb7-8a650dfa317e/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/93a73227-bcc9-4a25-9eb7-8a650dfa317e/</guid><description>My mother was affectionate, nurturant, praiseful, but somewhat seductive, which led to sexual problems for me as a young adult.</description></item><item><title>The null hypothesis is always false</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9d1c1cff-0bdb-4fd7-b146-da704a7caa82/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9d1c1cff-0bdb-4fd7-b146-da704a7caa82/</guid><description>I believe is generally recognized by statisticians today and by thoughtful social scientists, the null hypothesis, taken literally, is always false.</description></item><item><title>The parents</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7f1e39a3-06fe-4662-b5d5-96fbb64cf984/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7f1e39a3-06fe-4662-b5d5-96fbb64cf984/</guid><description>In 1931 my father, who had embezzled money to play the stock market, committed suicide. &amp;hellip; My mother began having frightening “heart attacks,” and life seemed precarious indeed. &amp;hellip; My mother isn’t going to die of heart failure, she’s a young widow with anxiety neurosis. I decided overnight to become a psychotherapist. &amp;hellip; At age sixteen I suffered a second object loss when my mother (who had remarried when I was fourteen) died of ether pneumonia after surgery for a brain tumor.</description></item><item><title>Theoretical risks and tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the slow progress of soft psychology</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1978/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1978/</guid><description>Reference Paul E Meehl “Theoretical risks and tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the slow progress of soft psychology” (1978) // Publisher: American Psychological Association. DOI: 10.1037/0022-006X.46.4.806
Bib @Article{meehl1978, title = {Theoretical risks and tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the slow progress of soft psychology}, author = {Meehl, Paul E}, year = {1978}, publisher = {American Psychological Association}, doi = {10.1037/0022-006X.46.4.806} }</description></item><item><title>Theory-testing in psychology and physics: A methodological paradox</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1967/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1967/</guid><description>Reference Paul E Meehl “Theory-testing in psychology and physics: A methodological paradox” (1967) // Philosophy of science. Publisher: Cambridge University Press. Vol. 34. No 2. Pp. 103–115.
Bib @Article{meehl1967, title = {Theory-testing in psychology and physics: A methodological paradox}, author = {Meehl, Paul E}, url = {https://meehl.umn.edu/sites/meehl.umn.edu/files/files/074theorytestingparadox.pdf}, journal = {Philosophy of science}, volume = {34}, number = {2}, pages = {103--115}, year = {1967}, publisher = {Cambridge University Press} }</description></item><item><title>Unimpressive theories in psychology</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a877a820-1fcb-4944-99ad-5f888320ea8d/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a877a820-1fcb-4944-99ad-5f888320ea8d/</guid><description>I consider it unnecessary to persuade you that most so-called “theories” in the soft areas of psychology (clinical, counseling, social, personality, community, and school psychology) are scientifically unimpressive and technologically worthless.</description></item></channel></rss>