<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Confusing Statistics on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/confusing-statistics/</link><description>Recent content in Confusing Statistics on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/confusing-statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Cautionary Note on the Use of Error Bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lanzante2005/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lanzante2005/</guid><description>Reference John R Lanzante “A Cautionary Note on the Use of Error Bars” (2005) // Journal of Climate. Publisher: American Meteorological Society. Vol. 18. No 17. Pp. 3699–3703. DOI: 10.1175/jcli3499.1
Bib @Article{lanzante2005, title = {A Cautionary Note on the Use of Error Bars}, volume = {18}, issn = {0894-8755}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1175/JCLI3499.1}, doi = {10.1175/jcli3499.1}, number = {17}, journal = {Journal of Climate}, publisher = {American Meteorological Society}, author = {Lanzante, John R}, year = {2005}, month = {sep}, pages = {3699–3703} }</description></item><item><title>Misunderstanding of Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/22a80e19-4456-4510-8a14-7415b537a7da/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/22a80e19-4456-4510-8a14-7415b537a7da/</guid><description>Little is known about researchers’ understanding of confidence intervals (CIs) and standard error (SE) bars. Authors of journal articles in psychology, behavioral neuroscience, and medicine were invited to visit a Web site where they adjusted a figure until they judged 2 means, with error bars, to be just statistically significantly different (p &amp;lt; .05). Results from 473 respondents suggest that many leading researchers have severe misconceptions about how error bars relate to statistical significance, do not adequately distinguish CIs and SE bars, and do not appreciate the importance of whether the 2 means are independent or come from a repeated measures design. Better guidelines for researchers and less ambiguous graphical conventions are needed before the advantages of CIs for research communication can be realized.</description></item><item><title>Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/belia2005/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/belia2005/</guid><description>Reference Sarah Belia, Fiona Fidler, Jennifer Williams, Geoff Cumming “Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars” (2005) // Psychological Methods. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 10. No 4. Pp. 389–396. DOI: 10.1037/1082-989x.10.4.389
Bib @Article{belia2005, title = {Researchers Misunderstand Confidence Intervals and Standard Error Bars}, volume = {10}, issn = {1082-989X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/1082-989X.10.4.389}, doi = {10.1037/1082-989x.10.4.389}, number = {4}, journal = {Psychological Methods}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Belia, Sarah and Fidler, Fiona and Williams, Jennifer and Cumming, Geoff}, year = {2005}, pages = {389–396} }</description></item><item><title>Statistical misleadingness of error bars</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e42a2cde-94ae-44f9-b9bf-3f2c1eee39c9/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e42a2cde-94ae-44f9-b9bf-3f2c1eee39c9/</guid><description>Climate studies often involve comparisons between estimates of some parameter derived from different observed and/or model-generated datasets. It is common practice to present estimates of two or more statistical quantities with error bars about each representing a confidence interval. If the error bars do not overlap, it is presumed that there is a statistically significant difference between them. In general, such a procedure is not valid and usually results in declaring statistical significance too infrequently. Simple examples that demonstrate the nature of this pitfall, along with some formulations, are presented. It is recommended that practitioners use standard hypothesis testing techniques that have been derived from statistical theory rather than the ad hoc approach involving error bars.</description></item></channel></rss>