<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Paper announcement on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/paper-announcement/</link><description>Recent content in Paper announcement on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/paper-announcement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Weighted quantile estimators'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-wqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-wqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have just published a preprint of a paper &amp;lsquo;Weighted quantile estimators&amp;rsquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on a series of my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-wqe/">research notes&lt;/a> that I have been writing since September 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07265">arXiv:2304.07265 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-wqe">AndreyAkinshin/paper-wqe&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2023)
&amp;ldquo;Weighted quantile estimators&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07265">arXiv:2304.07265&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In this paper, we consider a generic scheme that allows building weighted versions of various quantile estimators,
such as traditional quantile estimators based on linear interpolation of two order statistics,
the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification.
The obtained weighted quantile estimators are especially useful
in the problem of estimating a distribution at the tail of a time series using quantile exponential smoothing.
The presented approach can also be applied to other problems,
such as quantile estimation of weighted mixture distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Finite-sample Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-frc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-frc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, I published a preprint of a paper &amp;lsquo;Finite-sample Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators&amp;rsquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on a series of my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-frc/">research notes&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12268">arXiv:2209.12268 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-frc">AndreyAkinshin/paper-frc&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&amp;ldquo;Finite-sample Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12268">arXiv:2209.12268&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Rousseeuw-Croux $S_n$, $Q_n$ scale estimators and the median absolute deviation $\operatorname{MAD}_n$
can be used as consistent estimators for the standard deviation under normality.
All of them are highly robust: the breakdown point of all three estimators is $50\%$.
However, $S_n$ and $Q_n$ are much more efficient than $\operatorname{MAD}_n$:
their asymptotic Gaussian efficiency values are $58\%$ and $82\%$ respectively
compared to $37\%$ for $\operatorname{MAD}_n$.
Although these values look impressive, they are only asymptotic values.
The actual Gaussian efficiency of $S_n$ and $Q_n$ for small sample sizes
is noticeably lower than in the asymptotic case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The original work by Rousseeuw and Croux (1993)
provides only rough approximations of the finite-sample bias-correction factors for $S_n,\, Q_n$
and brief notes on their finite-sample efficiency values.
In this paper, we perform extensive Monte-Carlo simulations in order to obtain refined values of the
finite-sample properties of the Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators.
We present accurate values of the bias-correction factors and Gaussian efficiency for small samples ($n \leq 100$)
and prediction equations for samples of larger sizes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Quantile absolute deviation'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-qad/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-qad/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have just published a preprint of a paper &amp;lsquo;Quantile absolute deviation&amp;rsquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on a series of my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-qad/">research notes&lt;/a>
that I have been writing since December 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13459">arXiv:2208.13459 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-qad">AndreyAkinshin/paper-qad&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&amp;ldquo;Quantile absolute deviation&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13459">arXiv:2208.13459&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The median absolute deviation (MAD) is a popular robust measure of statistical dispersion.
However, when it is applied to non-parametric distributions (especially multimodal, discrete, or heavy-tailed),
lots of statistical inference issues arise.
Even when it is applied to distributions with slight deviations from normality and these issues are not actual,
the Gaussian efficiency of the MAD is only 37% which is not always enough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this paper, we introduce the &lt;em>quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em> (QAD) as a generalization of the MAD.
This measure of dispersion provides a flexible approach to analyzing properties of non-parametric distributions.
It also allows controlling the trade-off between robustness and statistical efficiency.
We use the trimmed Harrell-Davis median estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width
as a complimentary median estimator that gives
increased finite-sample Gaussian efficiency compared to the sample median
and a breakdown point matched to the QAD.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a rule of thumb, we suggest using two new measures of dispersion
called the &lt;em>standard QAD&lt;/em> and the &lt;em>optimal QAD&lt;/em>.
They give 54% and 65% of Gaussian efficiency having breakdown points of 32% and 14% respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Finite-sample bias-correction factors for the median absolute deviation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-mad-factors/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-mad-factors/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have just published a preprint of a paper
&amp;lsquo;Finite-sample bias-correction factors for the median absolute deviation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification&amp;rsquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on a series of my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-unbiased-mad/">research notes&lt;/a>
that I have been writing since February 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.12005">arXiv:2207.12005 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-mad-factors">AndreyAkinshin/paper-mad-factors&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&amp;ldquo;Finite-sample bias-correction factors for the median absolute deviation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification,&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.12005">arXiv:2207.12005&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The median absolute deviation is a widely used robust measure of statistical dispersion.
Using a scale constant, we can use it as an asymptotically consistent estimator for the standard deviation under normality.
For finite samples, the scale constant should be corrected in order to obtain an unbiased estimator.
The bias-correction factor depends on the sample size and the median estimator.
When we use the traditional sample median, the factor values are well known,
but this approach does not provide optimal statistical efficiency.
In this paper, we present the bias-correction factors for the median absolute deviation
based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification
which allow us to achieve better statistical efficiency of the standard deviation estimations.
The obtained estimators are especially useful for samples with a small number of elements.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Publication announcement: 'Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Since the beginning of previous year, I have been working on building a quantile estimator
that provides an optimal trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness.
At the end of the year, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/">published&lt;/a> the corresponding preprint
where I presented a description of such an estimator:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe">AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, the paper was published in &lt;em>Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation&lt;/em>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&lt;em>Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width,&lt;/em>
Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation,
DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396">10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-thdqe/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update: the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/pub-thdqe/">final paper&lt;/a> was published in &lt;em>Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation&lt;/em> (DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396">10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396&lt;/a>).&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the beginning of this year, I have been working on building a quantile estimator
that provides an optimal trade-off between statistical efficiency and robustness.
Finally, I have built such an estimator.
A paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe">AndreyAkinshin/paper-thdqe&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2021)
Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width,
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11776">arXiv:2111.11776&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>