<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ronán M Conroy on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/ron%C3%A1n-m-conroy/</link><description>Recent content in Ronán M Conroy on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/ron%C3%A1n-m-conroy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What Hypotheses Do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/conroy2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/conroy2012/</guid><description>Reference Ronán M Conroy “What Hypotheses do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?” (2012) // The Stata Journal: Promoting communications on statistics and Stata. Vol. 12. No 2. Pp. 182–190. DOI: 10.1177/1536867X1201200202
Abstract In this article, I discuss measures of effect size for two-group comparisons where data are not appropriately analyzed by least-squares methods. The Mann–Whitney test calculates a statistic that is a very useful measure of effect size, particularly suited to situations in which differences are measured on scales that either are ordinal or use arbitrary scale units. Both the difference in medians and the median difference between groups are also useful measures of effect size.
Bib @Article{conroy2012, title = {What Hypotheses do “Nonparametric” Two-Group Tests Actually Test?}, volume = {12}, issn = {1536-867X, 1536-8734}, url = {http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1536867X1201200202}, doi = {10.1177/1536867X1201200202}, abstract = {In this article, I discuss measures of effect size for two-group comparisons where data are not appropriately analyzed by least-squares methods. The Mann–Whitney test calculates a statistic that is a very useful measure of effect size, particularly suited to situations in which differences are measured on scales that either are ordinal or use arbitrary scale units. Both the difference in medians and the median difference between groups are also useful measures of effect size.}, language = {en}, number = {2}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {The Stata Journal: Promoting communications on statistics and Stata}, author = {Conroy, Ronán M}, month = {jun}, year = {2012}, pages = {182--190} }</description></item></channel></rss>