<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>GTD on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/gtd/</link><description>Recent content in GTD on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/gtd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/clear-atomic-habits/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/clear-atomic-habits/</guid><description>The only pragmatic book on habits.</description></item><item><title>Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-deep-work/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-deep-work/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s a fine book, but some parts are a little dry and boring. Main insights are quite basic and common for GTD books, examples are lengthy.
The book consists of two parts: &amp;ldquo;The Idea&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;The Rules&amp;rdquo;.
The first part covers the general philosophy behind the concept of deep work. Deep work is a state of mind, in which one is extremely focused and productive and is capable of achieving a lot within a short period. True deep work is a rare mental state, and one should train their skills to develop an ability to enter it.
The second part is mostly a set of practical recommendations, most of which are classic:
Quit social media, disable notifications and messengers Schedule a day in advance, and allocate time for deep work (max: 4-5 hours) Set up rituals for deep work (start, end); shutdown ritual at the end of the day Artifical deadlines Boredom - a useful exercise for training life without distractions Review all activities and remove everything that doesn&amp;rsquo;t justify time spent Setting a cutoff point (Don&amp;rsquo;t do any work after xx:yy pm) Productive meditation: think about a dedicated problem during a walk/run/cleaning and don&amp;rsquo;t get distracted The author introduces the following classification of various regimes of deep work:
Bimodal philosophy: live as usual, but sometimes go to the woods for a month of deep work Rhythmic philosophy: live by the schedule, allocate n hours for deep work daily Journalist philosophy: be ready to switch to deep work at any moment once there is an opportunity for that The introduced deep work and shallow work are similar concepts to hyperfocus and scatterfocus from Hyperfocus.
Most references are to online resources, not so much to scientific papers.
There are shallow discussions of some papers like leroy2009 and masicampo2011.</description></item><item><title>Digital Minimalism: Choosing a Focused Life in a Noisy World</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-digital-minimalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-digital-minimalism/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burkeman-four-thousand-weeks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burkeman-four-thousand-weeks/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/allen-getting-things-done/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/allen-getting-things-done/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hyperfocus: How to Be More Productive in a World of Distraction</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-hyperfocus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-hyperfocus/</guid><description>Boring and lengthy book. The content can be easily five times shorter. Advise like &amp;ldquo;Bad focus - drink coffee, bad creativity - have a little booze.&amp;rdquo; The opposite of hyperfocus is presented as scatterfocus (the brainstorming mode).</description></item><item><title>Jedi Techniques</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/dorofeev-jedi-techniques/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/dorofeev-jedi-techniques/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Pomodoro Technique Illustrated: The Easy Way to Do More in Less Time</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/noteberg-pomodoro-technique-illustrated/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/noteberg-pomodoro-technique-illustrated/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Art of Procrastination: A Guide to Effective Dawdling, Lollygagging and Postponing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/perry-the-art-of-procrastination/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/perry-the-art-of-procrastination/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Path of the Jedi</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/dorofeev-path-of-the-jedi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/dorofeev-path-of-the-jedi/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Productivity Project: Accomplishing More by Managing Your Time, Attention, and Energy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-the-productivity-project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-the-productivity-project/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Way We're Working Isn't Working: The Four Forgotten Needs that Energize Great Performance</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/schwartz-the-way-were-working-isnt-working/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/schwartz-the-way-were-working-isnt-working/</guid><description/></item><item><title>When: The Scientific Secrets of Perfect Timing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-when/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-when/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Why is It so Hard to Do My work? The Challenge of Attention Residue When Switching Between Work Tasks</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</guid><description>One of the main insights from this research: in switching between tasks, the performance on the subsequent tasks increases when the previous task was finished and performed under high time pressure. The statistical analysis was performed unsatisfactorily, but the effect size is decent and the results look believable. However, it is not clear to which extent the results can be generalized to other tasks and other populations (some of the possible concerns are discussed in the &amp;ldquo;Limitations&amp;rdquo; section on page 179).
Introduction There is a nice overview of the problem with a rich set of references.
Study 1 (Attention residue) The author introduces two research propositions:
RP1: People who do not finish Task A before switching to Task B experience more attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A prior to switching to Task B.
RP2: People who finish Task A under high time pressure exhibit less attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A under low time pressure.
Design:
84 undergraduate students (26 men; 58 women) random assignment to the (finished/unfinished) X (high/low time pressure) between-participants design The participants were told that they were going to participate in two separate studies crafted by different researchers. Procedure:
Task A (5 minutes; framing on intelligence): solving 17 clues in a fixed number of one-word answers (Appendix A) Three manipulation check questions (Table 1) If Task A is completed Satisfaction with own performance (7-point Likert scale) Consistency with the experimental conditions Lexical decision task (measures attention residue): quick distinguishing of real words from fake words (Table 2) Debriefing Task B (5 minutes): reviewing 4 CVs Manipulations:
Finished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 13 unique words Unfinished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 5 unique words (non-solvable) High time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work as fast as you can&amp;rdquo;; background timer with announcement of remaining time every minute Low time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work at your own pace&amp;rdquo; The study design feels good and is formed according to well-established recommendations by other research teams.</description></item></channel></rss>