<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Fernando Marmolejo-Ramos on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/fernando-marmolejo-ramos/</link><description>Recent content in Fernando Marmolejo-Ramos on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/fernando-marmolejo-ramos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Performance of Some Estimators of Relative Variability</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ospina2019/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ospina2019/</guid><description>Reference Raydonal Ospina, Fernando Marmolejo-Ramos “Performance of Some Estimators of Relative Variability” (2019) // Frontiers in Applied Mathematics and Statistics. Vol. 5. DOI: 10.3389/fams.2019.00043
Abstract The classic coefficient of variation (CV) is the ratio of the standard deviation to the mean and can be used to compare normally distributed data with respect to their variability, this measure has been widely used in many fields. In the Social Sciences, the CV is used to evaluate demographic heterogeneity and social aggregates such as race, sex, education and others. Data of this nature are usually not normally distributed, and the distributional characteristics can vary widely. In this sense, more accurate and robust estimator variations of the classic CV are needed to give a more realistic picture of the behavior of collected data. In this work, we empirically evaluate five measures of relative variability, including the classic CV, of finite sample sizes via Monte Carlo simulations. Our purpose is to give an insight into the behavior of these estimators, as their performance has not previously been systematically investigated. To represent different behaviors of the data, we considered some statistical distributions—which are frequently used to model data across various research fields. To enable comparisons, we consider parameters of these distributions that lead to a similar range of values for the CV. Our results indicate that CV estimators based on robust statistics of scale and location are more accurate and give the highest measure of efficiency. Finally, we study the stability of a robust CV estimator in psychological and genetic data and compare the results with the traditional CV.
Bib @Article{ospina2019, title = {Performance of Some Estimators of Relative Variability}, volume = {5}, issn = {2297-4687}, url = {https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fams.2019.00043}, abstract = {The classic coefficient of variation (CV) is the ratio of the standard deviation to the mean and can be used to compare normally distributed data with respect to their variability, this measure has been widely used in many fields.</description></item></channel></rss>