<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Medicine on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/medicine/</link><description>Recent content in Medicine on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/medicine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>0.05 Evidence-based Medicine from Magic to the Search for Immortality</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/talantov-005-evidence-based-medicine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/talantov-005-evidence-based-medicine/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A Decade of Reversal: An Analysis of 146 Contradicted Medical Practices</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/prasad2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/prasad2013/</guid><description>Reference Vinay Prasad, Andrae Vandross, Caitlin Toomey, Michael Cheung, Jason Rho, Steven Quinn, Satish Jacob Chacko, Durga Borkar, Victor Gall, Senthil Selvaraj, Nancy Ho, Adam Cifu “A Decade of Reversal: An Analysis of 146 Contradicted Medical Practices” (2013) // Mayo Clinic Proceedings. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 88. No 8. Pp. 790–798. DOI: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.05.012
Bib @Article{prasad2013, title = {A Decade of Reversal: An Analysis of 146 Contradicted Medical Practices}, volume = {88}, issn = {0025-6196}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.05.012}, doi = {10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.05.012}, number = {8}, journal = {Mayo Clinic Proceedings}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Prasad, Vinay and Vandross, Andrae and Toomey, Caitlin and Cheung, Michael and Rho, Jason and Quinn, Steven and Chacko, Satish Jacob and Borkar, Durga and Gall, Victor and Selvaraj, Senthil and Ho, Nancy and Cifu, Adam}, year = {2013}, month = {aug}, pages = {790–798} }</description></item><item><title>A Dirty dozen: Twelve p-value Misconceptions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/goodman2008/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/goodman2008/</guid><description>Reference Steven Goodman “A dirty dozen: twelve p-value misconceptions” (2008) // Seminars in hematology. Elsevier. Vol. 45. No 3. Pp. 135–140. DOI: 10.1053/j.seminhematol.2008.04.003
Abstract The P value is a measure of statistical evidence that appears in virtually all medical research papers. Its interpretation is made extraordinarily difficult because it is not part of any formal system of statistical inference. As a result, the P value&amp;rsquo;s inferential meaning is widely and often wildly misconstrued, a fact that has been pointed out in innumerable papers and books appearing since at least the 1940s. This commentary reviews a dozen of these common misinterpretations and explains why each is wrong. It also reviews the possible consequences of these improper understandings or representations of its meaning. Finally, it contrasts the P value with its Bayesian counterpart, the Bayes&amp;rsquo; factor, which has virtually all of the desirable properties of an evidential measure that the P value lacks, most notably interpretability. The most serious consequence of this array of P-value misconceptions is the false belief that the probability of a conclusion being in error can be calculated from the data in a single experiment without reference to external evidence or the plausibility of the underlying mechanism.
Bib @Inproceedings{goodman2008, title = {A dirty dozen: twelve p-value misconceptions}, author = {Goodman, Steven}, abstract = {The P value is a measure of statistical evidence that appears in virtually all medical research papers. Its interpretation is made extraordinarily difficult because it is not part of any formal system of statistical inference. As a result, the P value&amp;#39;s inferential meaning is widely and often wildly misconstrued, a fact that has been pointed out in innumerable papers and books appearing since at least the 1940s. This commentary reviews a dozen of these common misinterpretations and explains why each is wrong. It also reviews the possible consequences of these improper understandings or representations of its meaning.</description></item><item><title>Confidence Intervals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8a403d69-3240-4581-9710-cde46af21603/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8a403d69-3240-4581-9710-cde46af21603/</guid><description>We have argued that the excessive use of hypothesis testing at the expense of more informative approaches to data interpretation is an unsatisfactory way of assessing and presenting statistical findings from medical studies. We prefer the use of confidence intervals, which present the results directly on the scale of data measurement. We have also suggested a notation for confidence intervals which is intended to force clarity of meaning. Confidence intervals, which also have a link to the outcome of hypothesis tests, should become the standard method for presenting the statistical results of major findings.</description></item><item><title>Confidence Intervals Rather Than P values: Estimation Rather Than Hypothesis Testing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/gardner1986/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/gardner1986/</guid><description>Reference M J Gardner, D G Altman “Confidence intervals rather than P values: estimation rather than hypothesis testing” (1986) // BMJ. Publisher: BMJ. Vol. 292. No 6522. Pp. 746–750. DOI: 10.1136/bmj.292.6522.746
Bib @Article{gardner1986, title = {Confidence intervals rather than P values: estimation rather than hypothesis testing}, volume = {292}, issn = {1468-5833}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.292.6522.746}, doi = {10.1136/bmj.292.6522.746}, number = {6522}, journal = {BMJ}, publisher = {BMJ}, author = {Gardner, M J and Altman, D G}, year = {1986}, month = {mar}, pages = {746–750} }</description></item><item><title>Confounding and Simpson’s Paradox</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/julious1994/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/julious1994/</guid><description>Reference SA Julious, MA Mullee “Confounding and Simpson’s paradox” (1994) // BMJ. Publisher: BMJ. Vol. 309. No 6967. Pp. 1480–1481. DOI: 10.1136/bmj.309.6967.1480
Abstract A common problem when analysing clinical data is that of confounding. This occurs when the association between an exposure and an outcome is investigated but the exposure and outcome are strongly associated with a third variable. An extreme example of this is Simpson&amp;rsquo;s paradox, in which this third factor reverses the effect first observed.1 This phenomenon has long been recognised as a theoretical possibility but few real examples have been presented.
Bib @Article{julious1994, title = {Confounding and Simpson’s paradox}, abstract = {A common problem when analysing clinical data is that of confounding. This occurs when the association between an exposure and an outcome is investigated but the exposure and outcome are strongly associated with a third variable. An extreme example of this is Simpson&amp;#39;s paradox, in which this third factor reverses the effect first observed.1 This phenomenon has long been recognised as a theoretical possibility but few real examples have been presented.}, volume = {309}, issn = {1468-5833}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.309.6967.1480}, doi = {10.1136/bmj.309.6967.1480}, number = {6967}, journal = {BMJ}, publisher = {BMJ}, author = {Julious, SA and Mullee, MA}, year = {1994}, month = {dec}, pages = {1480–1481}, custom-url-pdf = {https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2541623/pdf/bmj00468-0032.pdf} }</description></item><item><title>Correspondence Between Confidence Intervals and Hypothesis Tests</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/426c7b3f-1b39-443c-9f6f-25dfaa973005/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/426c7b3f-1b39-443c-9f6f-25dfaa973005/</guid><description>Although for quantitative data and means there is a direct correspondence between the confidence interval approach and a t test ofthe null hypothesis at the associated level of statistical significance, this is not exactly so for qualitative data and proportions. The reason is related to the use of different estimates of the standard error for the usual tests of the null hypothesis from those given here for constructing confidence intervals. The lack of direct correspondence is small and should not result in changes of interpretation. In addition, more accurate confidence intervals can sometimes be obtained by using estimates of the standard error of the sample statistic at the confidence limits themselves-such as derived by Cornfield for relative risks.</description></item><item><title>Efficacy of n-3 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids and Feasibility of Optimizing Preventive Strategies in Patients at High Cardiovascular risk: Rationale, Design and Baseline Characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a Large Randomised Trial in General Practice</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101186174562151168_2010/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101186174562151168_2010/</guid><description>The authors claim that treatment with n−3 polyunsaturated fatty acid reduces the risk of heart attacks. The claim has been made using observational research without accounting for multiple confounding factors. Correlation does not imply causation.
In d101056nejmoa1205409_2013 (double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial), a similar study shows that there is no effect.
Discussed in Statistics Done Wrong (page 84).
Reference “Efficacy of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and feasibility of optimizing preventive strategies in patients at high cardiovascular risk: rationale, design and baseline characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a large randomised trial in general practice” (2010) // Trials. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 11. No 1. DOI: 10.1186/1745-6215-11-68
Bib @Article{d101186174562151168_2010, title = {Efficacy of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and feasibility of optimizing preventive strategies in patients at high cardiovascular risk: rationale, design and baseline characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a large randomised trial in general practice}, volume = {11}, issn = {1745-6215}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-11-68}, doi = {10.1186/1745-6215-11-68}, number = {1}, journal = {Trials}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, year = {2010}, month = {may} }</description></item><item><title>Gene Expression Profiling Predicts Clinical Outcome of Breast Cancer</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/van2002/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/van2002/</guid><description>Pioneer work, 11K+ citations.
Sample size: 117 young patients Initial research: 98 34 from patients who developed distant metastases within 5 years 44 from patients who continued to be disease-free after a period of at least 5 years 18 from patients with BRCA1 germline mutations 2 from BRCA2 carriers Additional conformational research: 19 Reference Laura J. van ’t Veer, Hongyue Dai, Marc J. van de Vijver, Yudong D. He, Augustinus A. M. Hart, Mao Mao, Hans L. Peterse, Karin van der Kooy, Matthew J. Marton, Anke T. Witteveen, George J. Schreiber, Ron M. Kerkhoven, Chris Roberts, Peter S. Linsley, René Bernards, Stephen H. Friend “Gene expression profiling predicts clinical outcome of breast cancer” (2002) // Nature. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 415. No 6871. Pp. 530–536. DOI: 10.1038/415530a
Abstract Breast cancer patients with the same stage of disease can have markedly different treatment responses and overall outcome. The strongest predictors for metastases (for example, lymph node status and histological grade) fail to classify accurately breast tumours according to their clinical behaviour. Chemotherapy or hormonal therapy reduces the risk of distant metastases by approximately one-third; however, 70-80% of patients receiving this treatment would have survived without it. None of the signatures of breast cancer gene expression reported to date allow for patient-tailored therapy strategies. Here we used DNA microarray analysis on primary breast tumours of 117 young patients, and applied supervised classification to identify a gene expression signature strongly predictive of a short interval to distant metastases (&amp;lsquo;poor prognosis&amp;rsquo; signature) in patients without tumour cells in local lymph nodes at diagnosis (lymph node negative). In addition, we established a signature that identifies tumours of BRCA1 carriers. The poor prognosis signature consists of genes regulating cell cycle, invasion, metastasis and angiogenesis. This gene expression profile will outperform all currently used clinical parameters in predicting disease outcome.</description></item><item><title>Incongruence Between Test Statistics and P Values in Medical Papers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/garc%C3%ADa-berthou2004/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/garc%C3%ADa-berthou2004/</guid><description>Reference Emili García-Berthou, Carles Alcaraz “Incongruence between test statistics and P values in medical papers” (2004) // BMC Medical Research Methodology. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 4. No 1. DOI: 10.1186/1471-2288-4-13
Bib @Article{garcía-berthou2004, title = {Incongruence between test statistics and P values in medical papers}, volume = {4}, issn = {1471-2288}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2288-4-13}, doi = {10.1186/1471-2288-4-13}, number = {1}, journal = {BMC Medical Research Methodology}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {García-Berthou, Emili and Alcaraz, Carles}, year = {2004}, month = {may} }</description></item><item><title>Interim Analyses and Sequential Designs in Phase III Studies</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/todd2001/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/todd2001/</guid><description>Reference Susan Todd, Anne Whitehead, Nigel Stallard, John Whitehead “Interim analyses and sequential designs in phase III studies” (2001) // British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology. Publisher: Wiley. Vol. 51. No 5. Pp. 394–399. DOI: 10.1046/j.1365-2125.2001.01382.x
Bib @Article{todd2001, title = {Interim analyses and sequential designs in phase III studies}, volume = {51}, issn = {1365-2125}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2125.2001.01382.x}, doi = {10.1046/j.1365-2125.2001.01382.x}, number = {5}, journal = {British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology}, publisher = {Wiley}, author = {Todd, Susan and Whitehead, Anne and Stallard, Nigel and Whitehead, John}, year = {2001}, month = {may}, pages = {394–399} }</description></item><item><title>Is Molecular Profiling Ready for Use in Clinical Decision Making?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2007a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2007a/</guid><description>Reference John PA Ioannidis “Is Molecular Profiling Ready for Use in Clinical Decision Making?” (2007) // The Oncologist. Publisher: Oxford University Press (OUP). Vol. 12. No 3. Pp. 301–311. DOI: 10.1634/theoncologist.12-3-301
Abstract Molecular profiling, the classification of tissue or other specimens for diagnostic, prognostic, and predictive purposes based on multiple gene expression, is a technology that holds major promise for optimizing the management of patients with cancer. However, the use of these tests for clinical decision making presents many challenges to overcome. Assay development and data analysis in this field have been largely exploratory, and leave numerous possibilities for the introduction of bias. Standardization of profiles remains the exception. Classifier performance is usually overinterpreted by presenting the results as p-values or multiplicative effects (e.g., relative risks), while the absolute sensitivity and specificity of classification remain modest at best, especially when tested in large validation samples. Validation has often been done with suboptimal attention to methodology and protection from bias. The postulated classifier performance may be inflated compared to what these profiles can achieve. With the exception of breast cancer, we have little evidence about the incremental discrimination that molecular profiles can provide versus classic risk factors alone. Clinical trials have started to evaluate the utility of using molecular profiles for breast cancer management. Until we obtain data from these trials, the impact of these tests and the net benefit under real-life settings remain unknown. Optimal incorporation into clinical practice is not straightforward. Finally, cost-effectiveness is difficult to appreciate until these other challenges are addressed. Overall, molecular profiling is a fascinating and promising technology, but its incorporation into clinical decision making requires careful planning and robust evidence.
Bib @Article{ioannidis2007a, title = {Is Molecular Profiling Ready for Use in Clinical Decision Making?}, abstract = {Molecular profiling, the classification of tissue or other specimens for diagnostic, prognostic, and predictive purposes based on multiple gene expression, is a technology that holds major promise for optimizing the management of patients with cancer.</description></item><item><title>Making the Study Positive</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/613be7e4-c3fd-405a-be24-1874a4c93a26/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/613be7e4-c3fd-405a-be24-1874a4c93a26/</guid><description>Believing there is a difference between groups, a well-intentioned clinician researcher addresses unexpected values. We tested how much removal, remeasurement, or reclassification of patients would be needed in most cases to turn an otherwise-neutral study positive. Remeasurement of 19 patients out of 200 per group was required to make most studies positive. Removal was more powerful: just 9 out of 200 was enough. Reclassification was most powerful, with 5 out of 200 enough. The larger the study, the smaller the proportion of patients needing to be manipulated to make the study positive: the percentages needed to be remeasured, removed, or reclassified fell from 45%, 20%, and 10% respectively for a 20 patient-per-group study, to 4%, 2%, and 1% for an 800 patient-per-group study. Dot-plots, but not bar-charts, make the perhaps-inadvertent manipulations visible.</description></item><item><title>Medicine residents' Understanding of the Biostatistics and Results in the Medical Literature</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/windish2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/windish2007/</guid><description>Reference Donna M Windish, Stephen J Huot, Michael L Green “Medicine residents&amp;rsquo; understanding of the biostatistics and results in the medical literature” (2007) // Jama. Publisher: American Medical Association. Vol. 298. No 9. Pp. 1010–1022. DOI: 10.1001/jama.298.9.1010
Bib @Article{windish2007, title = {Medicine residents&amp;#39; understanding of the biostatistics and results in the medical literature}, author = {Windish, Donna M and Huot, Stephen J and Green, Michael L}, journal = {Jama}, volume = {298}, number = {9}, pages = {1010--1022}, year = {2007}, publisher = {American Medical Association}, doi = {10.1001/jama.298.9.1010} }</description></item><item><title>Menstrual Synchrony and Suppression</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mcclintock1971/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/mcclintock1971/</guid><description>Critisism:
Critique of McClintock&amp;#39;s Study of Human Menstrual Cycles wilson1992 yang2006 Reference Martha K McClintock “Menstrual Synchrony and Suppression” (1971) // Nature. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 229. No 5282. Pp. 244–245. DOI: 10.1038/229244a0
Bib @Article{mcclintock1971, title = {Menstrual Synchrony and Suppression}, volume = {229}, issn = {1476-4687}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/229244a0}, doi = {10.1038/229244a0}, number = {5282}, journal = {Nature}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Martha K McClintock}, year = {1971}, month = {jan}, pages = {244–245} }</description></item><item><title>N–3 Fatty Acids in Patients with Multiple Cardiovascular Risk Factors</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101056nejmoa1205409_2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101056nejmoa1205409_2013/</guid><description>The authors claim that treatment with n−3 polyunsaturated fatty acid does not reduce the risk of heart attacks.
Double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial Decent sample size: 1383 events; 11200 patients Claimed power: 90% Detailed results, confidence intervals are provided I found protocol here, but it&amp;rsquo;s in Italian. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the raw data Discussed in Statistics Done Wrong (page 84).
Reference “n–3 Fatty Acids in Patients with Multiple Cardiovascular Risk Factors” (2013) // New England Journal of Medicine. Publisher: Massachusetts Medical Society. Vol. 368. No 19. Pp. 1800–1808. DOI: 10.1056/nejmoa1205409
Bib @Article{d101056nejmoa1205409_2013, title = {n–3 Fatty Acids in Patients with Multiple Cardiovascular Risk Factors}, volume = {368}, issn = {1533-4406}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1205409}, doi = {10.1056/nejmoa1205409}, number = {19}, journal = {New England Journal of Medicine}, publisher = {Massachusetts Medical Society}, year = {2013}, month = {may}, pages = {1800–1808} }</description></item><item><title>Statistical Literacy of obstetrics-gynecology Residents</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/anderson2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/anderson2013/</guid><description>Reference Britta L Anderson, Sterling Williams, Jay Schulkin “Statistical literacy of obstetrics-gynecology residents” (2013) // Journal of graduate medical education. Publisher: The Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education Suite 2000, 515~…. Vol. 5. No 2. Pp. 272–275. DOI: 10.4300/jgme-d-12-00161.1
Bib @Article{anderson2013, title = {Statistical literacy of obstetrics-gynecology residents}, author = {Anderson, Britta L and Williams, Sterling and Schulkin, Jay}, journal = {Journal of graduate medical education}, volume = {5}, number = {2}, pages = {272--275}, year = {2013}, publisher = {The Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education Suite 2000, 515~…}, doi = {10.4300/jgme-d-12-00161.1} }</description></item><item><title>Statistical Literacy Training for obstetrics-gynecology Residents</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/58d4e333-4344-4fef-be8a-61e319433780/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/58d4e333-4344-4fef-be8a-61e319433780/</guid><description>Methods In 2011 we surveyed US obstetrics-gynecology residents participating in the Council for Resident Education in Obstetrics and Gynecology In-Training Examination about their statistical literacy and statistical literacy training.
Results Our response rate was 95% (4713 of 4961). About two-thirds (2980 of 4713) of the residents rated their statistical literacy training as adequate. Female respondents were more likely to rate their statistical literacy training poorly, with 25% (897 of 3575) indicating inadequate literacy compared with 17% (141 of 806) of the male respondents (P &amp;lt; .001). Respondents performed poorly on 2 statistical literacy questions, with only 26% (1222 of 4713) correctly answering a positive predictive value question and 42% (1989 of 4173) correctly defining a P value. A total of 51% (2391 of 4713) of respondents reported receiving statistical literacy training through a journal club, 29% (1359 of 4713) said they had informal training, 15% (711 of 4713) said that they had statistical literacy training as part of a course, and 11% (527 of 4713) said that they had no training.</description></item><item><title>Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bedard2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bedard2007/</guid><description>Reference Philippe L Bedard, Monika K Krzyzanowska, Melania Pintilie, Ian F Tannock “Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings” (2007) // Journal of Clinical Oncology. Publisher: American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO). Vol. 25. No 23. Pp. 3482–3487. DOI: 10.1200/jco.2007.11.3670
Bib @Article{bedard2007, title = {Statistical Power of Negative Randomized Controlled Trials Presented at American Society for Clinical Oncology Annual Meetings}, volume = {25}, issn = {1527-7755}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2007.11.3670}, doi = {10.1200/jco.2007.11.3670}, number = {23}, journal = {Journal of Clinical Oncology}, publisher = {American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO)}, author = {Bedard, Philippe L and Krzyzanowska, Monika K and Pintilie, Melania and Tannock, Ian F}, year = {2007}, month = {aug}, pages = {3482–3487} }</description></item><item><title>Statistics and Death from Meningococcal Disease in Children</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/perera2006/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/perera2006/</guid><description>Reference Rafael Perera “Statistics and death from meningococcal disease in children” (2006) // BMJ. Publisher: BMJ. Vol. 332. No 7553. Pp. 1297–1298. DOI: 10.1136/bmj.332.7553.1297
Bib @Article{perera2006, title = {Statistics and death from meningococcal disease in children}, volume = {332}, issn = {1468-5833}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.332.7553.1297}, doi = {10.1136/bmj.332.7553.1297}, number = {7553}, journal = {BMJ}, publisher = {BMJ}, author = {Perera, Rafael}, year = {2006}, month = {jun}, pages = {1297–1298} }</description></item><item><title>Summa Biotechnologiae</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/panchin-summa-biotechnologiae/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/panchin-summa-biotechnologiae/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Swaying an Entire Study</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c81a5510-8273-4df8-aaef-aeadc928b20f/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c81a5510-8273-4df8-aaef-aeadc928b20f/</guid><description>In medical practice, clinically unexpected measurements might be quite properly handled by the remeasurement, removal, or reclassification of patients. If these habits are not prevented during clinical research, how much of each is needed to sway an entire study?</description></item><item><title>The Beta Error and Sample Size Determination in Clinical Trials in Emergency Medicine</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brown1987/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brown1987/</guid><description>Reference Charles G Brown, Gabor D Kelen, James J Ashton, Howard A Werman “The beta error and sample size determination in clinical trials in emergency medicine” (1987) // Annals of Emergency Medicine. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 16. No 2. Pp. 183–187. DOI: 10.1016/s0196-0644(87)80013-6
Bib @Article{brown1987, title = {The beta error and sample size determination in clinical trials in emergency medicine}, volume = {16}, issn = {0196-0644}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0196-0644(87)80013-6}, doi = {10.1016/s0196-0644(87)80013-6}, number = {2}, journal = {Annals of Emergency Medicine}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Brown, Charles G and Kelen, Gabor D and Ashton, James J and Werman, Howard A}, year = {1987}, month = {feb}, pages = {183–187} }</description></item><item><title>The Bimodality Index: A Criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wang2009/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/wang2009/</guid><description>Reference Jing Wang, Sijin Wen, W. Fraser Symmans, Lajos Pusztai, Kevin R. Coombes “The Bimodality Index: A criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data” (2009) // Cancer Informatics. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 7. Pp. CIN.S2846. DOI: 10.4137/cin.s2846
Bib @Article{wang2009, title = {The Bimodality Index: A criterion for Discovering and Ranking Bimodal Signatures from Cancer Gene Expression Profiling Data}, volume = {7}, issn = {1176-9351}, doi = {10.4137/cin.s2846}, journal = {Cancer Informatics}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Wang, Jing and Wen, Sijin and Symmans, W. Fraser and Pusztai, Lajos and Coombes, Kevin R.}, year = {2009}, month = {jan}, pages = {CIN.S2846} }</description></item><item><title>The Virus that Broke the Planet</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yakutenko-the-virus-that-broke-the-planet/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yakutenko-the-virus-that-broke-the-planet/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Three Doctors</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7cc6c419-8556-40a5-b642-4c7ae9c6a3d9/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/7cc6c419-8556-40a5-b642-4c7ae9c6a3d9/</guid><description>Imagine three researchers in separate laboratories around the world who believe that patients in two groups differ in their values of a variable. Each researcher proclaims high clinical and research standards. Dr A is particularly fastidious, taking care to remeasure any initial measurements where they are inconsistent with the clinical picture. Dr B is especially scrupulous about bias in research and tries to prevent even a few patients who have other intercurrent diseases from distorting results. Dr C realises that unaided clinical judgement may be poor at classifying patients and that test results may be better guidance.</description></item><item><title>Twelve P-Value Misconceptions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac262184-cdb6-46f8-b7ac-5107d66d8314/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac262184-cdb6-46f8-b7ac-5107d66d8314/</guid><description> Twelve P-Value Misconceptions:
If P =.05, the null hypothesis has only a 5% chance of being true. A nonsignificant difference (eg, P &amp;gt; .05) means there is no difference between groups. A statistically significant finding is clinically important. Studies with P values on opposite sides of .05 are conflicting. Studies with the same P value provide the same evidence against the null hypothesis. P = .05 means that we have observed data that would occur only 5% of the time under the null hypothesis. P = .05 and P &amp;lt;= .05 mean the same thing. P values are properly written as inequalities (eg, “P &amp;lt; .02” when P = .015) P = .05 means that if you reject the null hypothesis, the probability of a type I error is only 5%. With a P = .05 threshold for significance, the chance of a type I error will be 5%. You should use a one-sided P value when you don’t care about a result in one direction, or a difference in that direction is impossible. A scientific conclusion or treatment policy should be based on whether or not the P value is significant.</description></item><item><title>Type II Error Should Be as Essential a Requirement for Publication</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c7ba1497-c183-41ab-9d9e-a4cffb4d2c84/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c7ba1497-c183-41ab-9d9e-a4cffb4d2c84/</guid><description>Failure to achieve statistical significance between interventions does not prove the absence of any difference. Proper planning of a clinical trial with attention to beta error and sample size determination allows the critical investigator to acknowledge the probability of a type II error and therefore the probability of detecting a clinically meaningful difference if one exists. The reader and clinician must be aware that negative trials may in fact be falsely negative, and should look for specific reporting of alpha, beta, and $\Delta_c$ error to provide the details of the reliability of such conclusions. Type II error should be as essential a requirement for publication, and as rigorously analyzed, as the traditional and far more common type I (alpha) error.</description></item><item><title>Underpowered Negative Clinical Trials</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/10189519-eb48-41f5-a1ca-adac8092bf8e/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/10189519-eb48-41f5-a1ca-adac8092bf8e/</guid><description>Our survey of 423 negative clinical trials indicates that 55% of trials had too few participants to detect a medium effect size in favor of the experimental over the standard treatment arm for their primary end point with at least 80% statistical power. Although underpowered negative clinical trials have been widely reported in the general medical and subspecialty literature, there are few reports relating to trials evaluating treatment of cancer. A review of 22 negative randomized oncology trials published in major general medical or oncology journals during a 1-year period found that 16 trials (73%) lacked adequate statistical power to detect a 50% improvement in median survival in favor of the experimental arm.</description></item><item><title>When We Do Harm: A Doctor Confronts Medical Error</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/ofri-when-we-do-harm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/ofri-when-we-do-harm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Why Even More Clinical Research Studies May Be False: Effect of Asymmetrical Handling of Clinically Unexpected Values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/shun-shin2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/shun-shin2013/</guid><description>Sequel for ioannidis2005. At the beginning, there is a wonderful questionnaire for clinical readers with subsequent sarcastic discussion of the state of the art.
Reference Matthew James Shun-Shin, Darrel P. Francis, Andrew R. Dalby “Why Even More Clinical Research Studies May Be False: Effect of Asymmetrical Handling of Clinically Unexpected Values” (2013) // PLoS ONE. Publisher: Public Library of Science (PLoS). Vol. 8. No 6. Pp. e65323. DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0065323
Bib @Article{shun-shin2013, title = {Why Even More Clinical Research Studies May Be False: Effect of Asymmetrical Handling of Clinically Unexpected Values}, volume = {8}, issn = {1932-6203}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0065323}, doi = {10.1371/journal.pone.0065323}, number = {6}, journal = {PLoS ONE}, publisher = {Public Library of Science (PLoS)}, author = {Shun-Shin, Matthew James and Francis, Darrel P.}, editor = {Dalby, Andrew R.}, year = {2013}, month = {jun}, pages = {e65323} }</description></item></channel></rss>