<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harold D Delaney on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/harold-d-delaney/</link><description>Recent content in Harold D Delaney on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/harold-d-delaney/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Critique and Improvement of the "CL" Common Language Effect Size Statistics of McGraw and Wong</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/vargha2000/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/vargha2000/</guid><description>Reference András Vargha, Harold D Delaney, Andras Vargha “A Critique and Improvement of the &amp;ldquo;CL&amp;rdquo; Common Language Effect Size Statistics of McGraw and Wong” (2000) // Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics. Vol. 25. No 2. Pp. 101. DOI: 10.2307/1165329
Bib @Article{vargha2000, title = {A Critique and Improvement of the &amp;#34;CL&amp;#34; Common Language Effect Size Statistics of McGraw and Wong}, volume = {25}, issn = {10769986}, url = {http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=1076-9986%28200022%2925%3A2%3C101%3AACAIOT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-O&amp;amp;origin=crossref}, doi = {10.2307/1165329}, number = {2}, urldate = {2023-10-22}, journal = {Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics}, author = {Vargha, András and Delaney, Harold D and Vargha, Andras}, year = {2000}, pages = {101} }</description></item><item><title>Bivariate median splits and spurious statistical significance</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/maxwell1993/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/maxwell1993/</guid><description>Reference Scott E Maxwell, Harold D Delaney “Bivariate median splits and spurious statistical significance” (1993) // Psychological Bulletin. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 113. No 1. Pp. 181–190. DOI: 10.1037/0033-2909.113.1.181
Bib @Article{maxwell1993, title = {Bivariate median splits and spurious statistical significance}, volume = {113}, issn = {0033-2909}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.113.1.181}, doi = {10.1037/0033-2909.113.1.181}, number = {1}, journal = {Psychological Bulletin}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Maxwell, Scott E and Delaney, Harold D}, year = {1993}, month = {jan}, pages = {181–190} }</description></item><item><title>Dichotomization of 2 continuous independent variables</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac013725-23bd-4d83-b98c-4b791a382e70/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ac013725-23bd-4d83-b98c-4b791a382e70/</guid><description>Despite pleas from methodologists, researchers often continue to dichotomize continuous predictor variables. The primary argument against this practice has been that it underestimates the strength of relationships and reduces statistical power. Although this argument is correct for relationships involving a single predictor, a different problem can arise when multiple predictors are involved. Specifically, dichotomizing 2 continuous independent variables can lead to false statistical significance. As a result, the typical justification for using a median split as long as results continue to be statistically significant is invalid, because such results may in fact be spurious. Thus, researchers who dichotomize multiple continuous predictor variables not only may lose power to detect true predictor-criterion relationships in some situations but also may dramatically increase the probability of Type I errors in other situations.</description></item></channel></rss>