<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Manojkumar Selvaraju on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/manojkumar-selvaraju/</link><description>Recent content in Manojkumar Selvaraju on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/manojkumar-selvaraju/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Justify your alpha</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lakens2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/lakens2018/</guid><description>Reference Daniel Lakens, Federico G Adolfi, Casper J Albers, Farid Anvari, Matthew A J Apps, Shlomo E Argamon, Thom Baguley, Raymond B Becker, Stephen D Benning, Daniel E Bradford, Erin M Buchanan, Aaron R Caldwell, Ben Van Calster, Rickard Carlsson, Sau-Chin Chen, Bryan Chung, Lincoln J Colling, Gary S Collins, Zander Crook, Emily S Cross, Sameera Daniels, Henrik Danielsson, Lisa DeBruine, Daniel J Dunleavy, Brian D Earp, Michele I Feist, Jason D Ferrell, James G Field, Nicholas W Fox, Amanda Friesen, Caio Gomes, Monica Gonzalez-Marquez, James A Grange, Andrew P Grieve, Robert Guggenberger, James Grist, Anne-Laura van Harmelen, Fred Hasselman, Kevin D Hochard, Mark R Hoffarth, Nicholas P Holmes, Michael Ingre, Peder M Isager, Hanna K Isotalus, Christer Johansson, Konrad Juszczyk, David A Kenny, Ahmed A Khalil, Barbara Konat, Junpeng Lao, Erik Gahner Larsen, Gerine M A Lodder, Jiří Lukavský, Christopher R Madan, David Manheim, Stephen R Martin, Andrea E Martin, Deborah G Mayo, Randy J McCarthy, Kevin McConway, Colin McFarland, Amanda Q X Nio, Gustav Nilsonne, Cilene Lino de Oliveira, Jean-Jacques Orban de Xivry, Sam Parsons, Gerit Pfuhl, Kimberly A Quinn, John J Sakon, S Adil Saribay, Iris K Schneider, Manojkumar Selvaraju, Zsuzsika Sjoerds, Samuel G Smith, Tim Smits, Jeffrey R Spies, Vishnu Sreekumar, Crystal N Steltenpohl, Neil Stenhouse, Wojciech Świątkowski, Miguel A Vadillo, Marcel A L M Van Assen, Matt N Williams, Samantha E Williams, Donald R Williams, Tal Yarkoni, Ignazio Ziano, Rolf A Zwaan “Justify your alpha” (2018) // Nature Human Behaviour. Vol. 2. No 3. Pp. 168–171. DOI: 10.1038/s41562-018-0311-x
Abstract In response to recommendations to redefine statistical significance to P ≤ 0.005, we propose that researchers should transparently report and justify all choices they make when designing a study, including the alpha level.
Bib @Article{lakens2018, title = {Justify your alpha}, volume = {2}, copyright = {2018 The Publisher}, issn = {2397-3374}, url = {https://www.</description></item></channel></rss>