<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Impact Factor on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/impact-factor/</link><description>Recent content in Impact Factor on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/impact-factor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Conclusions on Journal Impact Factor</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2526af27-e9d4-4a82-a5d3-e95b8af58146/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2526af27-e9d4-4a82-a5d3-e95b8af58146/</guid><description> While at this point it seems impossible to quantify the relative contributions of the different factors influencing the reliability of scientific publications, the current empirical literature on the effects of journal rank provides evidence supporting the following four conclusions:
Journal rank is a weak to moderate predictor of utility and perceived importance; Journal rank is a moderate to strong predictor of both intentional and unintentional scientific unreliability Journal rank is expensive, delays science and frustrates researchers; Journal rank as established by IF violates even the most basic scientific standards, but predicts subjective judgments of journal quality.</description></item><item><title>Deep impact: Unintended Consequences of Journal Rank</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brembs2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/brembs2013/</guid><description>Reference Björn Brembs, Katherine Button, Marcus Munafò “Deep impact: unintended consequences of journal rank” (2013) // Frontiers in Human Neuroscience. Publisher: Frontiers Media SA. Vol. 7. DOI: 10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291
Bib @Article{brembs2013, title = {Deep impact: unintended consequences of journal rank}, volume = {7}, issn = {1662-5161}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291}, doi = {10.3389/fnhum.2013.00291}, journal = {Frontiers in Human Neuroscience}, publisher = {Frontiers Media SA}, author = {Brembs, Björn and Button, Katherine and Munafò, Marcus}, year = {2013} }</description></item><item><title>Magnitude of Effects in Clinical Trials Published in high-impact General Medical Journals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/siontis2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/siontis2011/</guid><description>Reference Konstantinos CM Siontis, Evangelos Evangelou, John PA Ioannidis “Magnitude of effects in clinical trials published in high-impact general medical journals” (2011) // International Journal of Epidemiology. Publisher: Oxford University Press (OUP). Vol. 40. No 5. Pp. 1280–1291. DOI: 10.1093/ije/dyr095
Bib @Article{siontis2011, title = {Magnitude of effects in clinical trials published in high-impact general medical journals}, volume = {40}, issn = {0300-5771}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyr095}, doi = {10.1093/ije/dyr095}, number = {5}, journal = {International Journal of Epidemiology}, publisher = {Oxford University Press (OUP)}, author = {Siontis, Konstantinos CM and Evangelou, Evangelos and Ioannidis, John PA}, year = {2011}, month = {sep}, pages = {1280–1291} }</description></item><item><title>The Influence of Journal Prestige on the Inflation of Effect Sizes in Small Trials</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/79991435-cde7-4963-8f62-2bf812a39fda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/79991435-cde7-4963-8f62-2bf812a39fda/</guid><description>We found that small trials published in NEJM, JAMA and Lancet were more likely to display more favourable results for experimental interventions compared with trials in other publication venues. Inflated effect sizes were seen primarily for early small trials in these prominent journals. Therefore, the results of small trials with spectacular early promises for large treatment effects should be seen with great caution. Conversely, for large trials, effect estimates are likely to be more reliable. Small-study effects have been previously documented in the randomized trials literature. However, the results of our study provide further insight suggesting the possibility of a specific interaction with further exaggerated effects when the limited evidence from small trials appears in the most prestigious journals. Also, the inflation of effects in early randomized trials on particular interventions appears to be quite specific to these most prestigious journals. Some modest heterogeneity was seen in the two tertiles with higher events, but heterogeneity is difficult to determine in the tertile with lower events, because of the wide uncertainty in the ROR for single topics, when there is limited evidence.</description></item></channel></rss>