<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thomas A Trikalinos on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/thomas-a-trikalinos/</link><description>Recent content in Thomas A Trikalinos on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/thomas-a-trikalinos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Exploratory Test for an Excess of Significant Findings</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2007/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2007/</guid><description>Reference John PA Ioannidis, Thomas A Trikalinos “An exploratory test for an excess of significant findings” (2007) // Clinical Trials. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 4. No 3. Pp. 245–253. DOI: 10.1177/1740774507079441
Bib @Article{ioannidis2007, title = {An exploratory test for an excess of significant findings}, volume = {4}, issn = {1740-7753}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1740774507079441}, doi = {10.1177/1740774507079441}, number = {3}, journal = {Clinical Trials}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Ioannidis, John PA and Trikalinos, Thomas A}, year = {2007}, month = {jun}, pages = {245–253} }</description></item><item><title>Analysis of Variance in Genetic Associations and Health Care Interventions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c84cec6e-c9dd-4ea2-b87f-516d09824fbf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/c84cec6e-c9dd-4ea2-b87f-516d09824fbf/</guid><description>The maximal between-study variance was more likely to be recorded early in the 44 eligible meta-analyses of genetic associations than in the 37 meta-analyses of health care interventions (P = .013). At the time of the first heterogeneity assessment, the most favorable-ever result in support of a specific association was more likely to appear than the least favorable-ever result (22 vs. 10, P = .017); the opposite was seen at the second heterogeneity assessment (15 vs. 5, P = .031). Such a sequence of extreme opposite results was not seen in the clinical trials meta-analyses. The estimated between-study variance decreased over time in genetic association studies (P = .010), but not in clinical trials (P = .30).</description></item><item><title>Early Extreme Contradictory Estimates May Appear in Published research: The Proteus Phenomenon in Molecular Genetics Research and Randomized Trials</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2005b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ioannidis2005b/</guid><description>Reference John PA Ioannidis, Thomas A Trikalinos “Early extreme contradictory estimates may appear in published research: The Proteus phenomenon in molecular genetics research and randomized trials” (2005) // Journal of Clinical Epidemiology. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 58. No 6. Pp. 543–549. DOI: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2004.10.019
Bib @Article{ioannidis2005b, title = {Early extreme contradictory estimates may appear in published research: The Proteus phenomenon in molecular genetics research and randomized trials}, volume = {58}, issn = {0895-4356}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2004.10.019}, doi = {10.1016/j.jclinepi.2004.10.019}, number = {6}, journal = {Journal of Clinical Epidemiology}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Ioannidis, John PA and Trikalinos, Thomas A}, year = {2005}, month = {jun}, pages = {543–549} }</description></item></channel></rss>