<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pragmatic Statistics on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/pragmatic-statistics/</link><description>Recent content in Pragmatic Statistics on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/pragmatic-statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pragmatic Statistics Manifesto</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pragmatic-statistics-manifesto/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/pragmatic-statistics-manifesto/</guid><description>&lt;p>Statistics is one of the most confusing, controversial, and depressing disciplines I know.
So many different approaches, so many different opinions, so many arguments, so many person-years of wasted time,
and so many flawed peer-reviewed papers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What we want from statistics is an easy-to-use tool that would nudge us toward asking the right questions
and then straightforwardly guide us on how to design proper and relevant statistical procedures.
What we have is a bunch of vaguely described sets of strange equations,
a few arbitrarily chosen magical numbers as thresholds,
and no clear understanding of what to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the scientific community, there are a lot of adherents of
&lt;em>Frequentist&lt;/em> statistics (both Neyman-Pearson and Fisherian),
&lt;em>Bayesian&lt;/em> statistics,
&lt;em>Likelihood&lt;/em> statistics,
&lt;em>Nonparametric&lt;/em> statistics,
&lt;em>Robust&lt;/em> statistics,
and many other statistics.
And almost no one discusses &lt;em>Pragmatic&lt;/em> statistics.
I feel like we really need something which is called &lt;em>Pragmatic&lt;/em> statistics.
However, it should not be just a set of &amp;ldquo;blessed&amp;rdquo; approaches but rather a mindset.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let me make an attempt to speculate on the principles
that should form the foundation of the &lt;em>Pragmatic&lt;/em> statistics approach.
In future posts, I will show how to apply these principles to solve real-world problems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ill-Defined and well-defined Problems</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fdecbf50-a5d0-4999-87bf-8e7357542223/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fdecbf50-a5d0-4999-87bf-8e7357542223/</guid><description>At the one extreme are &amp;ldquo;well-defined&amp;rdquo; problems, at the other are &amp;ldquo;ill-defined&amp;quot;problems. Well-defined problems (like the chemical composition of the lunar samples) are amenableto solution in that they can be clearly posed and hence solved by relatively clear-cut, standard, analytic tech- niques; they are &amp;ldquo;consensible&amp;rdquo;(Ziman, 1968) ifnthat a relatively wide degree of consensus can be obtained regardingthe &amp;ldquo;natureof the problem;&amp;rdquo; in short, they are easily formulated. Ill-defined problems (like the origin of the moon) are almost defiantly elusive; they seem to defy a common &amp;ldquo;consensible&amp;rdquo; formulation (Mitroff and Betz, 1972). Beause of their widespreadconsensiblenature, well-defined problems seem independent of the personality of their formulators; they appearto be impersonal. Ill-defined problems, on the other hand, appearto be the intensely personal creations of their creators. Whereas the conventional norms of science are dominant for well-structured problems, the counter-norms proposed here appear to be dominant for ill-structured problems.</description></item></channel></rss>