<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pages on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/pages/</link><description>Recent content in Pages on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/about/</guid><description>Andrey Akinshin is a software developer and a mathematician, an author of blog posts and papers about statistics and programming, a conference speaker. He is a PhD, a performance engineer at JetBrains, the project lead of BenchmarkDotNet, the author of Pro .NET Benchmarking. Previously, he was a postdoc at the Weizmann Institute of Science, a Microsoft .NET MVP, an ACM ICPC medalist.</description></item><item><title>Blog posts BibTeX references</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts-bib/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts-bib/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Library</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/</guid><description>Library I enjoy the concept of having a personal library, but keeping a physical one is challenging. So, I’ve created a virtual library. This page contains a list of some books and papers I’ve read with occasional notes and reviews. Currently, the list is quite incomplete, but I’m slowly and steadily expanding it using my old archive notes. Ratings usually reflect my perception at the moment of reading and can be changed later. Sorted first by rating, then by title.
Highlighted bookshelves Philosophy Psychology Biography Mathematics Fiction
Books Rating: 6 &amp;#34;Surely You&amp;#39;re Joking, Mr. Feynman!&amp;#34;: Adventures of a Curious Character (1985) by Richard P. Feynman Rating: 6 0.05 Evidence-based medicine from magic to the search for immortality (2019, In Russian) by Petr Talantov Rating: 6 Animal Farm (1945) by George Orwell Rating: 6 Gödel, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid (1999) by Douglas R. Hofstadter Rating: 6 Meditations (2006) by Marcus Aurelius Rating: 6 Mistakes Were Made, but Not by Me: Why We Justify Foolish Beliefs, Bad Decisions, and Hurtful Acts (2007) by Carol Tavris, Elliot Aronson Rating: 6 Never Split the Difference: Negotiating as if Your Life Depended on It (2023) by Chris Voss Rating: 6 One palm clap (2020, In Russian) by Nikolay Kukushkin Rating: 6 Slaughterhouse-Five (1969) by Kurt Vonnegut Jr. Rating: 6 Statistics Done Wrong: The Woefully Complete Guide (2015) by Alex Reinhart Rating: 6 Uncle Petros and Goldbach&amp;#39;s Conjecture (1992) by Apostolos Doxiadis Rating: 6 Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance: An Inquiry Into Values (1974) by Robert M. Pirsig Rating: 5 21 Lessons for the 21st Century (2018) by Yuval Noah Harari Rating: 5 A Country Doctor&amp;#39;s Notebook (1925) by Mikhail Bulgakov Rating: 5 A Genetic Switch: Gene Control and Phage Lambda (1986) by Mark Ptashne Rating: 5 A History of the Jews (1987) by Paul Johnson Rating: 5 A Man Called Ove (2012) by Fredrik Backman Rating: 5 Adventures of a Mathematician (1991) by Stanislaw M.</description></item><item><title>Pro .NET Benchmarking</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/prodotnetbenchmarking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/prodotnetbenchmarking/</guid><description>Learn how to measure application performance and analyze the results! Use this in-depth guide to correctly design benchmarks, measure key performance metrics of .NET applications, and analyze results. This book presents dozens of case studies to help you understand complicated benchmarking topics. You will avoid common pitfalls, control the accuracy of your measurements, and improve performance of your software. Author Andrey Akinshin has maintained BenchmarkDotNet (the most popular .NET library for benchmarking) for five years and covers common mistakes that developers usually make in their benchmarks. This book includes not only .NET-specific content but also essential knowledge about performance measurements which can be applied to any language or platform (common benchmarking methodology, statistics, and low-level features of modern hardware). With this book, you will learn: Be aware of the best practices for writing benchmarks and performance tests Avoid the common benchmarking pitfalls Know the hardware and software factors that affect application performance Analyze performance measurements Apress Amazon US Amazon CA Amazon UK Amazon DE Amazon FR Amazon ES Amazon JP Springer Google Books O’Reilly GoodReads ResearchGate Examples (GitHub) Errata (GitHub) Content The book contains nine chapters:
Chapter 1 “Introducing Benchmarking”
This chapter contains some basic information about benchmarking and other performance investigations, including benchmarking goals and requirements. We will also discuss performance spaces and why it’s so important to analyze benchmark results. Chapter 2 “Common Benchmarking Pitfalls”
This chapter contains 15 examples of common mistakes that developers usually make during benchmarking. Each example is pretty small (so, you can easily understand what’s going on), but all of them demonstrate important problems and explain how to resolve them. Chapter 3 “How Environment Affects Performance”
This chapter explains why the environment is so important and introduces a lot of terms that will be used in subsequent chapters. You will find 12 case studies that demonstrate how minor changes in the environment may significantly affect application performance.</description></item><item><title>Research projects</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/research/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/research/</guid><description>Research projects Google Scholar ORCID ResearchGate arXiv Web of Science Scopus This page aggregates results from some of my research projects:
Statistical performance analysis Software benchmarking Mathematical models of gene networks Digital signal processing Statistical performance analysis This project aims to develop advanced statistical procedures for the automatic analysis of software performance measurements. This included various location estimators, dispersion estimators, quantile estimators, effect size estimators, density estimators, change point detectors, outlier detectors, and multimodality detectors. The goal is to provide a set of non-parametric, robust, and efficient approaches that are applicable to software performance distributions.
I regularly share my preliminary research notes in the form of blog posts (192).
Publications:
Andrey Akinshin “Weighted quantile estimators” (2023) // arXiv. DOI:&amp;nbsp;10.48550/arXiv.2304.07265 EN Article Preprint DOI arXiv PDF GitHub Andrey Akinshin “Finite-sample Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators” (2022) // arXiv. DOI:&amp;nbsp;10.48550/arXiv.2209.12268 EN Article Preprint DOI arXiv PDF GitHub Andrey Akinshin “Quantile absolute deviation” (2022) // arXiv. DOI:&amp;nbsp;10.48550/ARXIV.2208.13459 EN Article Preprint DOI arXiv PDF GitHub Andrey Akinshin “Finite-sample bias-correction factors for the median absolute deviation based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator and its trimmed modification” (2022) // arXiv. DOI:&amp;nbsp;10.48550/ARXIV.2207.12005 EN Article Preprint DOI arXiv PDF GitHub Andrey Akinshin “Trimmed Harrell-Davis quantile estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width” (2022) // Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation. Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis. Pp.&amp;nbsp;1-11. DOI:&amp;nbsp;10.1080/03610918.2022.2050396 EN Article Web of Science Scopus DOI Link arXiv PDF GitHub Software benchmarking This project aims to provide a set of reliable tools and approaches for software benchmarking.
Since 2013, I have been working on developing BenchmarkDotNet (9K+ GitHub stars, 19K+ dependent GitHub projects, 24M+ NuGet downloads). This .NET library helps to transform methods into benchmarks, track their performance, and share reproducible measurement experiments. In the context of the statistical performance analysis project, I&amp;rsquo;m working on the next-generation statistical engine for performance measurement analysis.</description></item></channel></rss>