<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Incorrect on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/incorrect/</link><description>Recent content in Incorrect on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/incorrect/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Efficacy of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and feasibility of optimizing preventive strategies in patients at high cardiovascular risk: rationale, design and baseline characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a large randomised trial in general practice</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101186174562151168_2010/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/d101186174562151168_2010/</guid><description>The authors claim that treatment with n−3 polyunsaturated fatty acid reduces the risk of heart attacks. The claim has been made using observational research without accounting for multiple confounding factors. Correlation does not imply causation.
In d101056nejmoa1205409_2013 (double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial), a similar study shows that there is no effect.
Discussed in Statistics Done Wrong (page 84).
Reference “Efficacy of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and feasibility of optimizing preventive strategies in patients at high cardiovascular risk: rationale, design and baseline characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a large randomised trial in general practice” (2010) // Trials. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 11. No 1. DOI: 10.1186/1745-6215-11-68
Bib @Article{d101186174562151168_2010, title = {Efficacy of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids and feasibility of optimizing preventive strategies in patients at high cardiovascular risk: rationale, design and baseline characteristics of the Rischio and Prevenzione study, a large randomised trial in general practice}, volume = {11}, issn = {1745-6215}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-11-68}, doi = {10.1186/1745-6215-11-68}, number = {1}, journal = {Trials}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, year = {2010}, month = {may} }</description></item><item><title>Evaluation of watermelons texture using their vibration responses</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/abbaszadeh2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/abbaszadeh2013/</guid><description>Fabulous research! Four scientists took 43 watermelons (Crimson sweet), measured their vibration response, rated them using a five-point ripeness scale, built a regression model to predict ripeness from vibration response, checked the model on the same 43 watermelons, got R² = 0.9998, published the results in a peer-reviewed journal.
Debunked in Statistics Done Wrong.
Reference Rouzbeh Abbaszadeh, Ali Rajabipour, Mohammad Mahjoob, Mojtaba Delshad, Hojjat Ahmadi “Evaluation of watermelons texture using their vibration responses” (2013) // Biosystems Engineering. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 115. No 1. Pp. 102–105. DOI: 10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2013.01.001
Bib @Article{abbaszadeh2013, title = {Evaluation of watermelons texture using their vibration responses}, volume = {115}, issn = {1537-5110}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2013.01.001}, doi = {10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2013.01.001}, number = {1}, journal = {Biosystems Engineering}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Abbaszadeh, Rouzbeh and Rajabipour, Ali and Mahjoob, Mohammad and Delshad, Mojtaba and Ahmadi, Hojjat}, year = {2013}, month = {may}, pages = {102–105} }</description></item></channel></rss>