<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Scott Aaronson on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/scott-aaronson/</link><description>Recent content in Scott Aaronson on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/scott-aaronson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Busy Beaver Frontier</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/aaronson2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/aaronson2020/</guid><description>Scott Aaronson “The Busy Beaver Frontier” (2020) // ACM SIGACT News. Vol. 51. No 3. Pp. 32–54. DOI: 10.1145/3427361.3427369
Abstract The Busy Beaver function, with its incomprehensibly rapid growth, has captivated generations of computer scientists, mathematicians, and hobbyists. In this survey, I o er a personal view of the BB function 58 years after its introduction, emphasizing lesser-known insights, recent progress, and especially favorite open problems. Examples of such problems include: when does the BB function rst exceed the Ackermann function? Is the value of BB(20) independent of set theory? Can we prove that BB(n + 1) \textgreater 2BB(n) for large enough n? Given BB(n), how many advice bits are needed to compute BB(n + 1)? Do all Busy Beavers halt on all inputs, not just the 0 input? Is it decidable, given n, whether BB(n) is even or odd?
Bib @Article{aaronson2020, title = {The Busy Beaver Frontier}, volume = {51}, issn = {0163-5700}, url = {https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3427361.3427369}, doi = {10.1145/3427361.3427369}, abstract = {The Busy Beaver function, with its incomprehensibly rapid growth, has captivated generations of computer scientists, mathematicians, and hobbyists. In this survey, I o er a personal view of the BB function 58 years after its introduction, emphasizing lesser-known insights, recent progress, and especially favorite open problems. Examples of such problems include: when does the BB function rst exceed the Ackermann function? Is the value of BB(20) independent of set theory? Can we prove that BB(n + 1) \textgreater 2BB(n) for large enough n? Given BB(n), how many advice bits are needed to compute BB(n + 1)? Do all Busy Beavers halt on all inputs, not just the 0 input? Is it decidable, given n, whether BB(n) is even or odd?}, language = {en}, number = {3}, urldate = {2022-05-29}, journal = {ACM SIGACT News}, author = {Aaronson, Scott}, month = {sep}, year = {2020}, pages = {32--54} }</description></item></channel></rss>