<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Change Point Detection on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/change-point-detection/</link><description>Recent content in Change Point Detection on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/change-point-detection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Change Point Detection and Recent Changes</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cpd-recent-changes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cpd-recent-changes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Change point detection (CPD) in time series analysis
is an essential tool for identifying significant shifts in data patterns.
These shifts, or &amp;ldquo;change points,&amp;rdquo; can signal critical transitions in various contexts.
While most CPD algorithms are adept at discovering historical change points,
their sensitivity in detecting recent changes can be limited,
often due to a key parameter: the minimum distance between sequential change points.
In this post, I share some speculations on how we can improve cpd analysis by combining two change point detectors.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Two-pass change point detection for temporary interval condensation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/two-pass-cpd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/two-pass-cpd/</guid><description>&lt;p>When we choose a change point detection algorithm, the most important thing is to clearly understand
why we want to detect the change points.
The knowledge of the final business goals is essential.
In this post, I show a simple example of how a business requirement can be translated into algorithm adjustments.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sporadic noise problem in change point detection</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sporadic-noise-problem/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sporadic-noise-problem/</guid><description>&lt;p>We consider a problem of change point detection at the end of a time series.
Let us say that we systematically monitor readings of an indicator,
and we want to react to noticeable changes in the measured values as fast as possible.
When there are no changes in the underlying distribution,
any alerts about detected change points should be considered false positives.
Typically, in such problems,
we consider the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_and_identically_distributed_random_variables">i.i.d.&lt;/a>
assumption that claims that in the absence of change points,
all the measurements are independent and identically distributed.
Such an assumption significantly simplifies the mathematical model,
but unfortunately, it is rarely fully satisfied in real life.
If we want to build a reliable change point detection system,
it is important to be aware of possible real-life artifacts that introduce deviations from the declared model.
In this problem, I discuss the problem of the sporadic noise.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Challenges of change point detection in CI performance data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cpd-perf-challenges/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cpd-perf-challenges/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Change_detection">Change point detection&lt;/a> is a popular task in various disciplines.
There are many algorithms that solve this problem.
For example, in &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/truong2020/">&lt;svg class="rating-icon">&lt;use xlink:href="https://aakinshin.net/img/fa/all.svg#paper">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>truong2020&lt;/a>,
the authors presented a classification of different approaches and discussed 35 algorithms.
However, not all the algorithms fit all the situations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we consider the problem of change point detection in time series based on
software performance measurements obtained from a continuous integration (CI) server.
Examples of data sources are CI builds, unit tests, benchmarks, performance tests, and so on.
We would like to automatically find performance degradations in such time series.
Unfortunately, most of the available algorithms do not provide decent solutions for this problem.
In this post, I discuss some challenges that arise when we are looking for change points in CI performance data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fixing Performance Regressions Before They Happen</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/ea46c08b5c421602297910c7fc8380fd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/ea46c08b5c421602297910c7fc8380fd/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Implementation of an efficient algorithm for changepoint detection: ED-PELT</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Change_detection">Changepoint detection&lt;/a> is an important task that has a lot of applications.
For example, I use it to detect changes in the &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/rider/">Rider&lt;/a> performance test suite.
It&amp;rsquo;s very important to detect not only performance degradations, but any kinds of performance changes
(e.g., the variance may increase, or an unimodal distribution may be split into several modes).
You can see examples of such changes in the following picture (we change the color when a changepoint is detected):&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/img/edpelt-light.png" target="_blank" alt="edpelt">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/img/edpelt-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/img/edpelt-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="edpelt">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/edpelt/img/edpelt-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty hard to write a reliable and fast algorithm for changepoint detection.
Recently, I found a cool paper &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/haynes2016/">&lt;svg class="rating-icon">&lt;use xlink:href="https://aakinshin.net/img/fa/all.svg#paper">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>haynes2016&lt;/a> that describes the ED-PELT algorithm.
It has &lt;code>O(N*log(N))&lt;/code> complexity and pretty good detection accuracy.
The reference implementation can be used via the &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/changepoint.np/index.html">changepoint.np&lt;/a> R package.
However, I can&amp;rsquo;t use &lt;a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R&lt;/a> on our build server, so I decided to write my own C# implementation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Computationally Efficient Nonparametric Approach for Changepoint Detection</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/haynes2016/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/haynes2016/</guid><description>ED-PELT — one of my favorite change point detection algorithms.
Reference Kaylea Haynes, Paul Fearnhead, Idris A. Eckley “A computationally efficient nonparametric approach for changepoint detection” (2016) // Statistics and Computing. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 27. No 5. Pp. 1293–1305. DOI: 10.1007/s11222-016-9687-5
Bib @Article{haynes2016, title = {A computationally efficient nonparametric approach for changepoint detection}, volume = {27}, issn = {1573-1375}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11222-016-9687-5}, doi = {10.1007/s11222-016-9687-5}, number = {5}, journal = {Statistics and Computing}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Haynes, Kaylea and Fearnhead, Paul and Eckley, Idris A.}, year = {2016}, month = {jul}, pages = {1293–1305} }</description></item><item><title>Automated System Performance Testing at Mongodb</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ingo2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/ingo2020/</guid><description>Open sourced solution: github/signal-processing-algorithms.
Reference Henrik Ingo, David Daly “Automated system performance testing at MongoDB” (2020) // Proceedings of the workshop on Testing Database Systems. Publisher: ACM. DOI: 10.1145/3395032.3395323
Bib @Inproceedings{ingo2020, series = {SIGMOD/PODS ’20}, title = {Automated system performance testing at MongoDB}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/3395032.3395323}, doi = {10.1145/3395032.3395323}, booktitle = {Proceedings of the workshop on Testing Database Systems}, publisher = {ACM}, author = {Ingo, Henrik and Daly, David}, year = {2020}, month = {jun}, collection = {SIGMOD/PODS ’20}, arxiv = {2004.08425} }</description></item><item><title>github/hunter</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/github-hunter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/github-hunter/</guid><description>Hunter performs statistical analysis of performance test results stored in CSV files or Graphite database. It finds change-points and notifies about possible performance regressions.</description></item><item><title>github/signal-processing-algorithms</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/github-signal-processing-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/github-signal-processing-algorithms/</guid><description>A suite of algorithms implementing Energy Statistics, E-Divisive with Means and Generalized ESD Test for Outliers in python. See The Use of Change Point Detection to Identify Software Performance Regressions in a Continuous Integration System and Creating a Virtuous Cycle in Performance Testing at MongoDB for background on the development and use of this library.</description></item><item><title>github/signal-processing-algorithms</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/signal-processing-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/signal-processing-algorithms/</guid><description>A suite of algorithms implementing Energy Statistics, E-Divisive with Means and Generalized ESD Test for Outliers in python. See The Use of Change Point Detection to Identify Software Performance Regressions in a Continuous Integration System and Creating a Virtuous Cycle in Performance Testing at MongoDB for background on the development and use of this library.</description></item><item><title>Hunter: Using Change Point Detection to Hunt for Performance Regressions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fleming2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/fleming2023/</guid><description>The authors present an open-source framework github/hunter for automatic change point detection.
Notes:
Assumes normality + Student’s t-test Haven&amp;rsquo;t performed own experiments yet, but expect poor accuracy and alpha in multimodal cases Presented data samples in Figure 2 do not have any unpleasant deviations In Hunter is Affected by Strong Noise, the authors admit issues on untuned hardware Comparison only with PELT and DYNP, no mentions of ED-PELT (see haynes2016) Reference Matt Fleming, Piotr Kolaczkowski, Ishita Kumar, Shaunak Das, Sean McCarthy, Pushkala Pattabhiraman, Henrik Ingo “Hunter: Using Change Point Detection to Hunt for Performance Regressions” (2023) // Proceedings of the 2023 ACM/SPEC International Conference on Performance Engineering. Publisher: ACM. DOI: 10.1145/3578244.3583719
Abstract Change point detection has recently gained popularity as a method of detecting performance changes in software due to its ability to cope with noisy data. In this paper we present Hunter, an open source tool that automatically detects performance regressions and improvements in time-series data. Hunter uses a modified E-divisive means algorithm to identify statistically significant changes in normally-distributed performance metrics. We describe the changes we made to the E-divisive means algorithm along with their motivation. The main change we adopted was to replace the significance test using randomized permutations with a Student&amp;rsquo;s t-test, as we discovered that the randomized approach did not produce deterministic results, at least not with a reasonable number of iterations. In addition we&amp;rsquo;ve made tweaks that allow us to find change points the original algorithm would not, such as two nearby changes. For evaluation, we developed a method to generate real timeseries, but with artificially injected changes in latency. We used these data sets to compare Hunter against two other well known algorithms, PELT and DYNP. Finally, we conclude with lessons we&amp;rsquo;ve learned supporting Hunter across teams with individual responsibility for the performance of their project.</description></item><item><title>Nonparametric Maximum Likelihood Approach to Multiple change-point Problems</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zou2014/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zou2014/</guid><description>Reference Changliang Zou, Guosheng Yin, Long Feng, Zhaojun Wang “Nonparametric maximum likelihood approach to multiple change-point problems” (2014) // The Annals of Statistics. Publisher: Institute of Mathematical Statistics. Vol. 42. No 3. DOI: 10.1214/14-aos1210
Bib @Article{zou2014, title = {Nonparametric maximum likelihood approach to multiple change-point problems}, volume = {42}, issn = {0090-5364}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1214/14-AOS1210}, doi = {10.1214/14-aos1210}, number = {3}, journal = {The Annals of Statistics}, publisher = {Institute of Mathematical Statistics}, author = {Zou, Changliang and Yin, Guosheng and Feng, Long and Wang, Zhaojun}, year = {2014}, month = {jun} }</description></item><item><title>Nyrkiö: Harness the Power of Change Point Detection</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/nyrkio/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/web/nyrkio/</guid><description>Change point detection as a service. Benchmarking as a service is on the way.
Based on github/hunter and github/signal-processing-algorithms.
API example:
curl -s -X POST -H &amp;#34;Content-type: application/json&amp;#34; -H &amp;#34;Authorization: Bearer $TOKEN&amp;#34; https://nyrkio.com/api/v0/result/benchmark1 \ -d &amp;#39;[{&amp;#34;timestamp&amp;#34;: 1706220908, &amp;#34;metrics&amp;#34;: [ {&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;p50&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;unit&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;us&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;value&amp;#34;: 56 }, {&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;p90&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;unit&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;us&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;value&amp;#34;: 125 }, {&amp;#34;name&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;p99&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;unit&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;us&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;value&amp;#34;: 280 } ], &amp;#34;attributes&amp;#34;: { &amp;#34;git_repo&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;https://github.com/nyrkio/nyrkio&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;branch&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;main&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;git_commit&amp;#34;: &amp;#34;6995e2de6891c724bfeb2db33d7b87775f913ad1&amp;#34;, } }]&amp;#39;</description></item><item><title>Optimal Detection of Changepoints with a Linear Computational Cost</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/killick2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/killick2012/</guid><description>Reference R. Killick, P. Fearnhead, I. A. Eckley “Optimal Detection of Changepoints With a Linear Computational Cost” (2012) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Publisher: Informa UK Limited. Vol. 107. No 500. Pp. 1590–1598. DOI: 10.1080/01621459.2012.737745
Bib @Article{killick2012, title = {Optimal Detection of Changepoints With a Linear Computational Cost}, volume = {107}, issn = {1537-274X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01621459.2012.737745}, doi = {10.1080/01621459.2012.737745}, number = {500}, journal = {Journal of the American Statistical Association}, publisher = {Informa UK Limited}, author = {Killick, R. and Fearnhead, P. and Eckley, I. A.}, year = {2012}, month = {oct}, pages = {1590–1598}, arxiv = {1101.1438} }</description></item><item><title>Selective Review of Offline Change Point Detection Methods</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/truong2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/truong2020/</guid><description>As of 2020, the best change point detection overview I found.
Reference Charles Truong, Laurent Oudre, Nicolas Vayatis “Selective review of offline change point detection methods” (2020) // Signal Processing. Vol. 167. Pp. 107299. DOI: 10.1016/j.sigpro.2019.107299
Abstract This article presents a selective survey of algorithms for the offline detection of multiple change points in multivariate time series. A general yet structuring methodological strategy is adopted to organize this vast body of work. More precisely, detection algorithms considered in this review are characterized by three elements: a cost function, a search method and a constraint on the number of changes. Each of those elements is described, reviewed and discussed separately. Implementations of the main algorithms described in this article are provided within a Python package called ruptures.
Bib @Article{truong2020, title = {Selective review of offline change point detection methods}, volume = {167}, issn = {01651684}, url = {http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.00718}, doi = {10.1016/j.sigpro.2019.107299}, abstract = {This article presents a selective survey of algorithms for the offline detection of multiple change points in multivariate time series. A general yet structuring methodological strategy is adopted to organize this vast body of work. More precisely, detection algorithms considered in this review are characterized by three elements: a cost function, a search method and a constraint on the number of changes. Each of those elements is described, reviewed and discussed separately. Implementations of the main algorithms described in this article are provided within a Python package called ruptures.}, urldate = {2020-06-30}, journal = {Signal Processing}, author = {Truong, Charles and Oudre, Laurent and Vayatis, Nicolas}, month = {feb}, year = {2020}, note = {arXiv: 1801.00718}, arxiv = {1801.00718}, keywords = {overview}, pages = {107299} }</description></item><item><title>The Use of Change Point Detection to Identify Software Performance Regressions in a Continuous Integration System</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/daly2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/daly2020/</guid><description>Reference David Daly, William Brown, Henrik Ingo, Jim O’Leary, David Bradford “The Use of Change Point Detection to Identify Software Performance Regressions in a Continuous Integration System” (2020) // Proceedings of the ACM/SPEC International Conference on Performance Engineering. Publisher: ACM. DOI: 10.1145/3358960.3375791
Bib @Inproceedings{daly2020, series = {ICPE ’20}, title = {The Use of Change Point Detection to Identify Software Performance Regressions in a Continuous Integration System}, url = {https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.1145/3358960.3375791}, doi = {10.1145/3358960.3375791}, booktitle = {Proceedings of the ACM/SPEC International Conference on Performance Engineering}, publisher = {ACM}, author = {Daly, David and Brown, William and Ingo, Henrik and O’Leary, Jim and Bradford, David}, year = {2020}, month = {apr}, collection = {ICPE ’20} }</description></item></channel></rss>