<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Bailey on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/chris-bailey/</link><description>Recent content in Chris Bailey on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/chris-bailey/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Being Bored</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a108d728-7af8-4698-82d2-09ec1ffdf807/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a108d728-7af8-4698-82d2-09ec1ffdf807/</guid><description>Answer this question honestly: When was the last time you were bored?
Really think about it. Can you remember?
Chances are it was a long time ago, maybe before welcoming devices into your life.
Never in human history have we divided our attention among so many things. In the moment this can feel like a benefit — we always have something to do—but the disadvantage is that distracting devices have basically eliminated boredom from our lives.</description></item><item><title>Distractions Notebook</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e9307a00-5ad2-4a97-9ac2-7957fe04f868/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/e9307a00-5ad2-4a97-9ac2-7957fe04f868/</guid><description>Whenever I have to focus, I adopt the two tactics mentioned above — and I also bring a pen and a notepad with me. In the notepad I write every distraction that makes its way into my mind—things I need to follow up on, tasks I can’t forget, new ideas, and so on.
Maintaining a distractions list as you read will capture the important things that float to the surface of your consciousness. Writing them down to make sure they don’t slip through the cracks will let you refocus on the task at hand.</description></item><item><title>Hyperfocus: How to Be More Productive in a World of Distraction</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-hyperfocus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-hyperfocus/</guid><description>Boring and lengthy book. The content can be easily five times shorter. Advise like &amp;ldquo;Bad focus - drink coffee, bad creativity - have a little booze.&amp;rdquo; The opposite of hyperfocus is presented as scatterfocus (the brainstorming mode).</description></item><item><title>List of Boring Activities</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/6a21ae71-b0a9-4105-aa4e-cd447fabcc05/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/6a21ae71-b0a9-4105-aa4e-cd447fabcc05/</guid><description> During a monthlong experiment I intentionally made myself bored for an hour a day. In that period I shut off all distractions and spent my time and attention on an excruciatingly boring task, based on the thirty weirdest ideas suggested by my website readers:
Reading the iTunes terms and conditions Staringattheceiling Watching C-SPAN 3 Waiting on hold with Air Canada’s baggage claim department Watching C-SPAN 2 Watching my turtle, Edward, swim back and forth in her tank Staringataslowlyrotatingfanblade Painting a tiny canvas with one color Watchingpaintdry Looking out my office window Removing and counting the seeds on a strawberry with a pair of tweezers 12.Watching grass grow Staring out a train window Watching an online chess tournament Watching one cloud in the sky Waiting at the hospital Watching a dripping faucet Ironing every piece of clothing I own Counting the 0s in the first 10,000 digits of pi Watching my girlfriend read Making dots on a sheet of paper Eating alone in a restaurant, without a book or phone Reading Wikipedia articles about rope Watching a clock Watching every file transfer from my computer to an external hard drive (and back) Peeling exactly five potatoes Watching a pot boil Attending a church service in Latin Watching C-SPAN Moving small rocks from one place to another, repeatedly</description></item><item><title>Right Thing in Each Moment</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8975c9e5-f082-484e-bd2c-3d8f3ecfd4bd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/8975c9e5-f082-484e-bd2c-3d8f3ecfd4bd/</guid><description>If our plan today is to write three thousand words, rock a presentation with our leadership team, and catch up on our email, and we successfully accomplish all of those, we were perfectly productive. Likewise, if we intend to have a relaxing day and manage to do absolutely nothing, we’re again perfectly productive. Being busy doesn’t make us productive. It doesn’t matter how busy we are if that busyness doesn’t lead us to accomplish anything of importance. Productivity is not about cramming more into our days but about doing the right thing in each moment.</description></item><item><title>The Productivity Project: Accomplishing More by Managing Your Time, Attention, and Energy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-the-productivity-project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bailey-the-productivity-project/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>