<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Discrete Distributions on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/discrete-distributions/</link><description>Recent content in Discrete Distributions on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/discrete-distributions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to build a smooth density estimation for a discrete sample using jittering</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have a sample with tied values.
If you draw a kernel density estimation (KDE) for such a sample,
you may get a serrated pattern like this:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/img/intro-light.png" target="_blank" alt="intro">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/img/intro-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/img/intro-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="intro">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-sample-jittering/img/intro-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>


&lt;p>KDE requires samples from continuous distributions
while tied values arise in discrete or mixture distributions.
Even if the original distribution is continuous,
you may observe artificial sample discretization due to the limited resolution of the measuring tool.
This effect may lead to distorted density plots like in the above picture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem could be solved using a nice technique called &lt;em>jittering&lt;/em>.
In the simplest case, jittering just adds random noise to each measurement.
Such a trick removes all ties from the sample and allows building a smooth density estimation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, there are many different ways to apply jittering.
The trickiest question here is how to choose proper noise values.
In this post, I want to share one of my favorite jittering approaches.
It generates a non-randomized noise pattern with a low risk of noticeable sample corruption.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>