<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Psychology on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/psychology/</link><description>Recent content in Psychology on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Study of Prisoners and Guards in a Simulated Prison</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zimbardo1973/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/zimbardo1973/</guid><description>The famous Stanford Prison Experiment (SPE).
Debuked by:
texier2019 The Stanford Prison Experiment was massively influential. We just learned it was a fraud. Reference Philip Zimbardo, Craig Haney, Curtis Banks, E Aronson “A study of prisoners and guards in a simulated prison” (1973)
Bib @Article{zimbardo1973, title = {A study of prisoners and guards in a simulated prison}, author = {Zimbardo, Philip and Haney, Craig and Banks, Curtis and Aronson, E}, year = {1973}, custom-url-pdf = {https://www.simplypsychology.org/wp-content/uploads/zimbardo-paper.pdf} }</description></item><item><title>Antibrain</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/spitzer-antibrain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/spitzer-antibrain/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Assessing Bimodality to Detect the Presence of a Dual Cognitive Process</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/freeman2012/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/freeman2012/</guid><description>Reference Jonathan B. Freeman, Rick Dale “Assessing bimodality to detect the presence of a dual cognitive process” (2012) // Behavior Research Methods. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 45. No 1. Pp. 83–97. DOI: 10.3758/s13428-012-0225-x
Bib @Article{freeman2012, title = {Assessing bimodality to detect the presence of a dual cognitive process}, volume = {45}, issn = {1554-3528}, doi = {10.3758/s13428-012-0225-x}, number = {1}, journal = {Behavior Research Methods}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Freeman, Jonathan B. and Dale, Rick}, year = {2012}, month = {jul}, pages = {83–97} }</description></item><item><title>Behavioral Study of Obedience</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/milgram1963/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/milgram1963/</guid><description>The famous Milgram experiment.
Criticized in:
Behind the Shock Machine by Gina Perry The book is also criticized in russell2013 Electric Schlock: Did Stanley Milgram&amp;rsquo;s Famous Obedience Experiments Prove Anything? Reference Stanley Milgram “Behavioral Study of obedience” (1963) // The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 67. No 4. Pp. 371–378. DOI: 10.1037/h0040525
Bib @Article{milgram1963, title = {Behavioral Study of obedience}, volume = {67}, issn = {0096-851X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/h0040525}, doi = {10.1037/h0040525}, number = {4}, journal = {The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Milgram, Stanley}, year = {1963}, month = {oct}, pages = {371–378} }</description></item><item><title>Believability of Relative Risks and Odds Ratios in abstracts: Cross Sectional Study</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/g%C3%B8tzsche2006/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/g%C3%B8tzsche2006/</guid><description>Reference Peter C Gøtzsche “Believability of relative risks and odds ratios in abstracts: cross sectional study” (2006) // BMJ. Publisher: BMJ. Vol. 333. No 7561. Pp. 231–234. DOI: 10.1136/bmj.38895.410451.79
Bib @Article{gøtzsche2006, title = {Believability of relative risks and odds ratios in abstracts: cross sectional study}, volume = {333}, issn = {1468-5833}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bmj.38895.410451.79}, doi = {10.1136/bmj.38895.410451.79}, number = {7561}, journal = {BMJ}, publisher = {BMJ}, author = {Gøtzsche, Peter C}, year = {2006}, month = {jul}, pages = {231–234} }</description></item><item><title>Blink: The Power of Thinking Without Thinking</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-blink/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-blink/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Consider It done! Plan Making Can Eliminate the Cognitive Effects of Unfulfilled Goals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/masicampo2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/masicampo2011/</guid><description>Study 1 73 undergraduates (49 women; 24 men) Random assignments to one of three conditions: Unfulfilled tasks: thinking of two important tasks that participants need to complete in the next few days Plan: as the previous condition, but participants were asked to make completion plans Control: as the first condition, but participants were asked to think of two tasks they had already completed Reading comprehension task: first 3200 words of &amp;ldquo;The Case of the Velvet Claws&amp;rdquo; by Erle Stanley Gardner One word at a time (hitting the space bar to reveal the next word) Four participants suspected (only four?) relations between parts of the study and were excluded from the analysis Eight reading comprehension questions Discussion claim: Participants who reflected on two important but unfinished tasks were distracted during a later attempt to read a novel. General Discussion The present research examined a phenomenon known to psychology for almost a century: The persistence in the mind of unfulfilled tasks and goals. Our findings suggest the pattern has not been fully understood. Quite reasonably, the standard assumption has been that incomplete goals remain active in the mind until they are fulfilled, but the present studies showed that goal activation can cease much sooner. Once a specific plan for a goal is made, goal-related cognitive activity is drastically reduced.
Statistical Notes Student-t test on 1-7 digital scale No proper speculations on the effect size No available raw data Reference E. J. Masicampo, Roy F. Baumeister “Consider it done! Plan making can eliminate the cognitive effects of unfulfilled goals” (2011) // Journal of Personality and Social Psychology. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 101. No 4. Pp. 667–683. DOI: 10.1037/a0024192
Abstract Unfulfilled goals persist in the mind, as asserted by ample theory and evidence (e.g., the Zeigarnik effect). The standard assumption has been that such cognitive activation persists until the goal is fulfilled.</description></item><item><title>Creatures of a Day: And Other Tales of Psychotherapy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-creatures-of-a-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-creatures-of-a-day/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Debunking the Stanford Prison Experiment</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/texier2019/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/texier2019/</guid><description>Reference Thibault Le Texier “Debunking the Stanford Prison Experiment” (2019) // American Psychologist. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 74. No 7. Pp. 823–839. DOI: 10.1037/amp0000401
Bib @Article{texier2019, title = {Debunking the Stanford Prison Experiment}, volume = {74}, issn = {0003-066X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/amp0000401}, doi = {10.1037/amp0000401}, number = {7}, journal = {American Psychologist}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Texier, Thibault Le}, year = {2019}, month = {oct}, pages = {823–839}, custom-url-pdf = {http://letexier.org/IMG/pdf/LeTexier_Debunking-the-SPE_American-Psychologist_2019.pdf} }</description></item><item><title>Decline of Power in Psychology (1962..1984)</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9eaab253-ea71-4eb4-add2-fc061c448725/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9eaab253-ea71-4eb4-add2-fc061c448725/</guid><description>The long-term impact of studies of statistical power is investigated using J. Cohen&amp;rsquo;s (1962) pioneering work as an example. We argue that the impact is nil; the power of studies in the same journal that Cohen reviewed (now the Journal of Abnormal Psychology) has not increased over the past 24 years. In 1960 the median power (i.e., the probability that a significant result will be obtained if there is a true effect) was .46 for a medium size effect, whereas in 1984 it was only .37. The decline of power is a result of alpha-adjusted procedures. Low power seems to go unnoticed: only 2 out of 64 experiments mentioned power, and it was never estimated. Nonsignificance was generally interpreted as confirmation of the null hypothesis (if this was the research hypothesis), although the median power was as low as .25 in these cases.</description></item><item><title>Do Studies of Statistical Power Have an Effect on the Power of studies?</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/sedlmeier1989/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/sedlmeier1989/</guid><description>Reference Peter Sedlmeier, Gerd Gigerenzer “Do studies of statistical power have an effect on the power of studies?” (1989) // Psychological Bulletin. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 105. No 2. Pp. 309–316. DOI: 10.1037/0033-2909.105.2.309
Bib @Article{sedlmeier1989, title = {Do studies of statistical power have an effect on the power of studies?}, volume = {105}, issn = {0033-2909}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.105.2.309}, doi = {10.1037/0033-2909.105.2.309}, number = {2}, journal = {Psychological Bulletin}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Sedlmeier, Peter and Gigerenzer, Gerd}, year = {1989}, month = {mar}, pages = {309–316} }</description></item><item><title>Drive: The Surprising Truth about What Motivates Us</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-drive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-drive/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Easy to Publish</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9ef2c0c7-a5da-4d76-8169-2d2d97aae36a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9ef2c0c7-a5da-4d76-8169-2d2d97aae36a/</guid><description>Our job as scientists is to discover truths about the world. We generate hypotheses, collect data, and examine whether or not the data are consistent with those hypotheses. Although we aspire to always be accurate, errors are inevitable. Perhaps the most costly error is a false positive, the incorrect rejection of a null hypothesis. First, once they appear in the literature, false positives are particularly persistent. Because null results have many possible causes, failures to replicate previous findings are never conclusive. Furthermore, because it is uncommon for prestigious journals to publish null findings or exact replications, researchers have little incentive to even attempt them. Second, false positives waste resources: They inspire investment in fruitless research programs and can lead to ineffective policy changes. Finally, a field known for publishing false positives risks losing its credibility. In this article, we show that despite the nominal endorsement of a maximum false-positive rate of 5% (i.e., p ≤ .05), current standards for disclosing details of data collection and analyses make false positives vastly more likely. In fact, it is unacceptably easy to publish “statistically significant” evidence consistent with any hypothesis.
(Emphasis is mine.)</description></item><item><title>Escape from Freedom</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/fromm-escape-from-freedom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/fromm-escape-from-freedom/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Everything is F*cked: A Book about Hope</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/manson-everything-is-fcked/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/manson-everything-is-fcked/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Everything is Negotiable: How to Get the Best Deal Every Time</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kennedy-everything-is-negotiable/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kennedy-everything-is-negotiable/</guid><description/></item><item><title>False-Positive Psychology: Undisclosed Flexibility in Data Collection and Analysis Allows Presenting Anything as Significant</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/simmons2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/simmons2011/</guid><description>Reference Joseph P Simmons, Leif D Nelson, Uri Simonsohn “False-Positive Psychology: Undisclosed Flexibility in Data Collection and Analysis Allows Presenting Anything as Significant” (2011) // Psychological Science. Publisher: SAGE Publications. Vol. 22. No 11. Pp. 1359–1366. DOI: 10.1177/0956797611417632
Bib @Article{simmons2011, title = {False-Positive Psychology: Undisclosed Flexibility in Data Collection and Analysis Allows Presenting Anything as Significant}, volume = {22}, issn = {1467-9280}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0956797611417632}, doi = {10.1177/0956797611417632}, number = {11}, journal = {Psychological Science}, publisher = {SAGE Publications}, author = {Simmons, Joseph P and Nelson, Leif D and Simonsohn, Uri}, year = {2011}, month = {oct}, pages = {1359–1366} }</description></item><item><title>Feeling Good: The New Mood Therapy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burns-feeling-good/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burns-feeling-good/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Finding Flow: The Psychology of Engagement with Everyday Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/csikszentmihalyi-finding-flow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/csikszentmihalyi-finding-flow/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Flow: The Psychology of Optimal Experience</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/csikszentmihalyi-flow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/csikszentmihalyi-flow/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Games People Play</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/berne-games-people-play/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/berne-games-people-play/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Go Crazy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/varlamova-go-crazy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/varlamova-go-crazy/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Good Things Peak in pairs: A Note on the Bimodality Coefficient</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/pfister2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/pfister2013/</guid><description>Reference Roland Pfister, Katharina A. Schwarz, Markus Janczyk, Rick Dale, Johnathan B. Freeman “Good things peak in pairs: a note on the bimodality coefficient” (2013) // Frontiers in Psychology. Publisher: Frontiers Media SA. Vol. 4. DOI: 10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00700
Bib @Article{pfister2013, title = {Good things peak in pairs: a note on the bimodality coefficient}, volume = {4}, issn = {1664-1078}, doi = {10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00700}, journal = {Frontiers in Psychology}, publisher = {Frontiers Media SA}, author = {Pfister, Roland and Schwarz, Katharina A. and Janczyk, Markus and Dale, Rick and Freeman, Johnathan B.}, year = {2013} }</description></item><item><title>Guidelines for Reviewers</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/1d8a5c7b-087b-4a6e-b60e-f144dd8a0f0b/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/1d8a5c7b-087b-4a6e-b60e-f144dd8a0f0b/</guid><description>We propose the following four guidelines for reviewers.
Reviewers should ensure that authors follow the requirements. Review teams are the gatekeepers of the scientific community, and they should encourage authors not only to rule out alternative explanations, but also to more convincingly demonstrate that their findings are not due to chance alone. This means prioritizing transparency over tidiness; if a wonderful study is partially marred by a peculiar exclusion or an inconsistent condition, those imperfections should be retained. If reviewers require authors to follow these requirements, they will. Reviewers should be more tolerant of imperfections in results. One reason researchers exploit researcher degrees of freedom is the unreasonable expectation we often impose as reviewers for every data pattern to be (significantly) as predicted. Underpowered studies with perfect results are the ones that should invite extra scrutiny. Reviewers should require authors to demonstrate that their results do not hinge on arbitrary analytic decisions. Even if authors follow all of our guidelines, they will necessarily still face arbitrary decisions. For example, should they subtract the baseline measure of the dependent variable from the final result or should they use the baseline measure as a covariate? When there is no obviously correct way to answer questions like this, the reviewer should ask for alternatives. For example, reviewer reports might include questions such as, “Do the results also hold if the baseline measure is instead used as a covariate?” Similarly, reviewers should ensure that arbitrary decisions are used consistently across studies (e.g., “Do the results hold for Study 3 if gender is entered as a covariate, as was done in Study 2?”).5 If a result holds only for one arbitrary specification, then everyone involved has learned a great deal about the robustness (or lack thereof) of the effect. If justifications of data collection or analysis are not compelling, reviewers should require the authors to conduct an exact replication.</description></item><item><title>Heaven and Hell</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/huxley-the-heaven-and-hell/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/huxley-the-heaven-and-hell/</guid><description/></item><item><title>How to Develop Self-Confidence and Influence People by Public Speaking</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-develop-self-confidence-and-influence-people-by-public-speaking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-develop-self-confidence-and-influence-people-by-public-speaking/</guid><description/></item><item><title>How to Stop Worrying and Start Living: Time-Tested Methods for Conquering Worry</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-stop-worrying-and-start-living/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-stop-worrying-and-start-living/</guid><description/></item><item><title>How to Win Friends and Influence People</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/carnegie-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>How We Decide</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/lehrer-how-we-decide/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/lehrer-how-we-decide/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Investigating the Probability of Rejecting Null Hypotheses in Abnormal-Social Research</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fcecf1bc-d282-46ec-b32a-86dc4b053695/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/fcecf1bc-d282-46ec-b32a-86dc4b053695/</guid><description>The results indicate that the investigators contributing to Volume 61 of the Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology had, on the average, a relatively (or even absolutely) poor chance of rejecting their major null hypotheses, unless the effect they sought was large. This surprising (and discouraging) finding needs some further consideration to be seen in full perspective.
First, it may be noted that with few exceptions, the 70 studies did have significant results. This may then suggest that perhaps the definitions of size of effect were too severe, or perhaps, accepting the definitions, one might seek to conclude that the investigators were operating under circumstances wherein the effects were actually large, hence their success. Perhaps, then, research in the abnormal-social area is not as &amp;ldquo;weak&amp;rdquo; as the above results suggest. But this argument rests on the implicit assumption that the research which is published is representative of the research undertaken in this area. It seems obvious that investigators are less likely to submit for publication unsuccessful than successful research, to say nothing of a similar editorial bias in accepting research for publication. Consider this paradigm: 100 investigations are undertaken in which, in fact, there is actually a medium population effect. From the above findings, about SO get positive results and are likely to come to publication; the other SO fail to reject their (assumed false) null hypotheses and are unlikely to come to publication. Thus, the general success of the articles in the volume under review does not successfully argue for their antecedent probabilities of success being any higher than the results of the analysis suggest, or, equivalently, that the criteria for size of effect used were overly stringent.&amp;quot;</description></item><item><title>LSD: My Problem Child – Reflections on Sacred Drugs, Mysticism and Science</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/hofmann-lsd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/hofmann-lsd/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lying on the Couch</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-lying-on-the-couch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-lying-on-the-couch/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Man’s Search for Meaning</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/frankl-mans-search-for-meaning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/frankl-mans-search-for-meaning/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mastery</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/greene-mastery/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/greene-mastery/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Maybe You Should Talk to Someone</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gottlieb-maybe-you-should-talk-to-someone/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gottlieb-maybe-you-should-talk-to-someone/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mental Traps: The Overthinker's Guide to a Happier Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kukla-mental-traps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kukla-mental-traps/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mistakes Were Made, but Not by Me: Why We Justify Foolish Beliefs, Bad Decisions, and Hurtful Acts</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/tavris-mistakes-were-made/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/tavris-mistakes-were-made/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Never Split the Difference: Negotiating as If Your Life Depended on It</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/voss-never-split-the-difference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/voss-never-split-the-difference/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Noise: A Flaw in Human Judgment</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kahneman-noise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kahneman-noise/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Nonviolent Communication: A Language of Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/rosenberg-nonviolent-communication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/rosenberg-nonviolent-communication/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Normal Subjects</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca964333-044c-4fec-8d89-145921696525/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/ca964333-044c-4fec-8d89-145921696525/</guid><description>Normal or approximately normal subjects are less useful objects of research than their pathological counterparts.</description></item><item><title>Nudge: Improving Decisions about Health, Wealth, and Happiness</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/thaler-nudge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/thaler-nudge/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Outliers: The Story of Success</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-outliers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-outliers/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Positive Affect Facilitates Creative Problem Solving</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/isen1987/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/isen1987/</guid><description>Reference Alice M Isen, Kimberly A Daubman, Gary P Nowicki “Positive affect facilitates creative problem solving” (1987) // Journal of Personality and Social Psychology. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 52. No 6. Pp. 1122–1131. DOI: 10.1037/0022-3514.52.6.1122
Abstract Four experiments indicated that positive affect, induced by means of seeing a few minutes of a comedy film or by means of receiving a small bag of candy, improved performance on two tasks that are generally regarded as requiring creative ingenuity: Duncker&amp;rsquo;s (1945) candle task and M. T. Mednick, S. A. Mednick, and E. V. Mednick&amp;rsquo;s (1964) Remote Associates Test. One condition in which negative affect was induced and two in which subjects engaged in physical exercise (intended to represent atfectless arousal) failed to produce comparable improvements in creative performance. The influence of positive affect on creativity was discussed in terms of a broader theory of the impact of positive affect on cognitive organization.
Bib @Article{isen1987, title = {Positive affect facilitates creative problem solving}, abstract = {Four experiments indicated that positive affect, induced by means of seeing a few minutes of a comedy film or by means of receiving a small bag of candy, improved performance on two tasks that are generally regarded as requiring creative ingenuity: Duncker&amp;#39;s (1945) candle task and M. T. Mednick, S. A. Mednick, and E. V. Mednick&amp;#39;s (1964) Remote Associates Test. One condition in which negative affect was induced and two in which subjects engaged in physical exercise (intended to represent atfectless arousal) failed to produce comparable improvements in creative performance. The influence of positive affect on creativity was discussed in terms of a broader theory of the impact of positive affect on cognitive organization.}, volume = {52}, issn = {0022-3514}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.52.6.1122}, doi = {10.1037/0022-3514.52.6.1122}, number = {6}, journal = {Journal of Personality and Social Psychology}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Isen, Alice M and Daubman, Kimberly A and Nowicki, Gary P}, year = {1987}, pages = {1122–1131} }</description></item><item><title>Power failure: Why Small Sample Size Undermines the Reliability of Neuroscience</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/button2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/button2013/</guid><description>Reference Katherine S Button, John P A Ioannidis, Claire Mokrysz, Brian A Nosek, Jonathan Flint, Emma S J Robinson, Marcus R Munafò “Power failure: why small sample size undermines the reliability of neuroscience” (2013) // Nature Reviews Neuroscience. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 14. No 5. Pp. 365–376. DOI: 10.1038/nrn3475
Bib @Article{button2013, title = {Power failure: why small sample size undermines the reliability of neuroscience}, volume = {14}, issn = {1471-0048}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrn3475}, doi = {10.1038/nrn3475}, number = {5}, journal = {Nature Reviews Neuroscience}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Button, Katherine S and Ioannidis, John P A and Mokrysz, Claire and Nosek, Brian A and Flint, Jonathan and Robinson, Emma S J and Munafò, Marcus R}, year = {2013}, month = {apr}, pages = {365–376} }</description></item><item><title>Power to the People: A Beginner’s Tutorial to Power Analysis Using Jamovi</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bartlett2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bartlett2022/</guid><description>Reference James Bartlett, Sarah Charles “Power to the People: A Beginner’s Tutorial to Power Analysis using jamovi” (2022) // Meta-Psychology. Publisher: Linnaeus University. Vol. 6. DOI: 10.15626/mp.2021.3078
Bib @Article{bartlett2022, title = {Power to the People: A Beginner’s Tutorial to Power Analysis using jamovi}, volume = {6}, issn = {2003-2714}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.15626/MP.2021.3078}, doi = {10.15626/mp.2021.3078}, journal = {Meta-Psychology}, publisher = {Linnaeus University}, author = {Bartlett, James and Charles, Sarah}, year = {2022}, month = {nov}, custom-url-pdf = {https://eprints.gla.ac.uk/285103/1/285103.pdf} }</description></item><item><title>Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces that Shape Our Decisions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/ariely-predictably-irrational/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/ariely-predictably-irrational/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Requirements for Authors</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2915ea66-476d-46bc-a79a-43ebe0c730e2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/2915ea66-476d-46bc-a79a-43ebe0c730e2/</guid><description>We propose the following six requirements for authors.
Authors must decide the rule for terminating data collection before data collection begins and report this rule in the article. Following this requirement may mean reporting the outcome of power calculations or disclosing arbitrary rules, such as “we decided to collect 100 observations” or “we decided to collect as many observations as we could before the end of the semester.” The rule itself is secondary, but it must be determined ex ante and be reported. Authors must collect at least 20 observations per cell or else provide a compelling cost-of-data-collection justification. This requirement offers extra protection for the first requirement. Samples smaller than 20 per cell are simply not powerful enough to detect most effects, and so there is usually no good reason to decide in advance to collect such a small number of observations. Smaller samples, it follows, are much more likely to reflect interim data analysis and a flexible termination rule. In addition, as Figure 1 shows, larger minimum sample sizes can lessen the impact of violating Requirement 1. Authors must list all variables collected in a study. This requirement prevents researchers from reporting only a convenient subset of the many measures that were collected, allowing readers and reviewers to easily identify possible researcher degrees of freedom. Because authors are required to just list those variables rather than describe them in detail, this requirement increases the length of an article by only a few words per otherwise shrouded variable. We encourage authors to begin the list with “only,” to assure readers that the list is exhaustive (e.g., “participants reported only their age and gender”). Authors must report all experimental conditions, including failed manipulations. This requirement prevents authors from selectively choosing only to report the condition comparisons that yield results that are consistent with their hypothesis.</description></item><item><title>Sex Bias in Graduate Admissions: Data from Berkeley: Measuring Bias is Harder Than is Usually assumed, and the Evidence is Sometimes Contrary to Expectation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bickel1975/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bickel1975/</guid><description>Reference P. J. Bickel, E. A. Hammel, J. W. O’Connell “Sex Bias in Graduate Admissions: Data from Berkeley: Measuring bias is harder than is usually assumed, and the evidence is sometimes contrary to expectation” (1975) // Science. Publisher: American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS). Vol. 187. No 4175. Pp. 398–404. DOI: 10.1126/science.187.4175.398
Abstract Examination of aggregate data on graduate admissions to the University of California, Berkeley, for fall 1973 shows a clear but misleading pattern of bias against female applicants. Examination of the disaggregated data reveals few decision-making units that show statistically significant departures from expected frequencies of female admissions, and about as many units appear to favor women as to favor men. If the data are properly pooled, taking into account the autonomy of departmental decision making, thus correcting for the tendency of women to apply to graduate departments that are more difficult for applicants of either sex to enter, there is a small but statistically significant bias in favor of women. The graduate departments that are easier to enter tend to be those that require more mathematics in the undergraduate preparatory curriculum. The bias in the aggregated data stems not from any pattern of discrimination on the part of admissions committees, which seem quite fair on the whole, but apparently from prior screening at earlier levels of the educational system. Women are shunted by their socialization and education toward fields of graduate study that are generally more crowded, less productive of completed degrees, and less well funded, and that frequently offer poorer professional employment prospects.
Bib @Article{bickel1975, title = {Sex Bias in Graduate Admissions: Data from Berkeley: Measuring bias is harder than is usually assumed, and the evidence is sometimes contrary to expectation}, abstract = {Examination of aggregate data on graduate admissions to the University of California, Berkeley, for fall 1973 shows a clear but misleading pattern of bias against female applicants.</description></item><item><title>Sir. Ronald Fisher</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/01015429-2154-45e1-b36d-9e11757643ca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/01015429-2154-45e1-b36d-9e11757643ca/</guid><description>You may say, “But, Meehl, R. A. Fisher was a genius, and we all know how valuable his stuff has been in agronomy. Why shouldn’t it work for soft psychology?” Well, I am not intimidated by Fisher’s genius, because my complaint is not in the field of mathematical statistics, and as regards inductive logic and philosophy of science, it is well-known that Sir Ronald permitted himself a great deal of dogmatism. I remember my amazement when the late Rudolf Carnap said to me, the first time I met him, “But, of course, on this subject Fisher is just mistaken: surely you must know that.” My statistician friends tell me that it is not clear just how useful the significance test has been in biological science either, but I set that aside as beyond my competence to discuss.</description></item><item><title>So Good They Can't Ignore You: Why Skills Trump Passion in the Quest for Work You Love</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-so-good-they-cant-ignore-you/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/newport-so-good-they-cant-ignore-you/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Talent is Overrated: What Really Separates World-Class Performers from Everybody Else</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/colvin-talent-is-overrated/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/colvin-talent-is-overrated/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Talking to Crazy: How to Deal with the Irrational and Impossible People in Your Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/goulston-talking-to-crazy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/goulston-talking-to-crazy/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The (mis)reporting of Statistical Results in Psychology Journals</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bakker2011/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/bakker2011/</guid><description>Reference Marjan Bakker, Jelte M. Wicherts “The (mis)reporting of statistical results in psychology journals” (2011) // Behavior Research Methods. Publisher: Springer Science and Business Media LLC. Vol. 43. No 3. Pp. 666–678. DOI: 10.3758/s13428-011-0089-5
Bib @Article{bakker2011, title = {The (mis)reporting of statistical results in psychology journals}, volume = {43}, issn = {1554-3528}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.3758/s13428-011-0089-5}, doi = {10.3758/s13428-011-0089-5}, number = {3}, journal = {Behavior Research Methods}, publisher = {Springer Science and Business Media LLC}, author = {Bakker, Marjan and Wicherts, Jelte M.}, year = {2011}, month = {apr}, pages = {666–678} }</description></item><item><title>The 48 Laws of Power</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/greene-the-48-laws-of-power/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/greene-the-48-laws-of-power/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The 5 Elements of Effective Thinking</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burger-the-5-elements-of-effective-thinking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burger-the-5-elements-of-effective-thinking/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Art of Procrastination: A Guide to Effective Dawdling, Lollygagging and Postponing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/perry-the-art-of-procrastination/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/perry-the-art-of-procrastination/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Attention Revolution, Unlocking the Power of the Focused Mind</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/wallace-the-attention-revolution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/wallace-the-attention-revolution/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Better Angels of Our Nature: Why Violence Has Declined</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pinker-the-better-angels-of-our-nature/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pinker-the-better-angels-of-our-nature/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Choice: Embrace the Possible</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/eger-the-choice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/eger-the-choice/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Courage to Be Disliked: How to Free Yourself, Change Your Life and Achieve Real Happiness</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kishimi-the-courage-to-be-disliked/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kishimi-the-courage-to-be-disliked/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Disordered Mind: What Unusual Brains Tell Us about Ourselves</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kandel-the-disordered-mind/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kandel-the-disordered-mind/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Doors of Perception</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/huxley-the-doors-of-perception/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/huxley-the-doors-of-perception/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Drunkard's Walk: How Randomness Rules Our Lives</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/mlodinow-the-drunkards-walk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/mlodinow-the-drunkards-walk/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Gift of Therapy: An Open Letter to a New Generation of Therapists and Their Patients</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-gift-of-therapy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-gift-of-therapy/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Gift: 12 Lessons to Save Your Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/eger-the-gift/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/eger-the-gift/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Happiness Advantage: The Seven Principles of Positive Psychology that Fuel Success and Performance at Work</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/achor-the-happiness-advantage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/achor-the-happiness-advantage/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat and Other Clinical Tales</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/sacks-the-man-who-mistook-his-wife-for-a-hat/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/sacks-the-man-who-mistook-his-wife-for-a-hat/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Neuroscience of Low Statistical Power</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/76c951e9-c936-4b30-919f-d3d3fd7f7227/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/76c951e9-c936-4b30-919f-d3d3fd7f7227/</guid><description>A study with low statistical power has a reduced chance of detecting a true effect, but it is less well appreciated that low power also reduces the likelihood that a statistically significant result reflects a true effect. Here, we show that the average statistical power of studies in the neurosciences is very low. The consequences of this include overestimates of effect size and low reproducibility of results. There are also ethical dimensions to this problem, as unreliable research is inefficient and wasteful. Improving reproducibility in neuroscience is a key priority and requires attention to well-established but often ignored methodological principles.</description></item><item><title>The Null Hypothesis is Always False</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9d1c1cff-0bdb-4fd7-b146-da704a7caa82/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/9d1c1cff-0bdb-4fd7-b146-da704a7caa82/</guid><description>I believe is generally recognized by statisticians today and by thoughtful social scientists, the null hypothesis, taken literally, is always false.</description></item><item><title>The Psychology of Invention in the Mathematical Field</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/hadamard-the-psychology-of-invention-in-the-mathematical-field/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/hadamard-the-psychology-of-invention-in-the-mathematical-field/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Psychopathology of Everyday Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/freud-the-psychopathology-of-everyday-life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/freud-the-psychopathology-of-everyday-life/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Schopenhauer Cure</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-schopenhauer-cure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-schopenhauer-cure/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Scout Mindset: Why Some People See Things Clearly and Others Don't</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/galef-the-scout-mindset/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/galef-the-scout-mindset/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Search for Existential Identity: Patient-Therapist Dialogues in Humanistic Psychotherapy</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bugental-the-search-for-existential-identity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/bugental-the-search-for-existential-identity/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Spinoza Problem</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-spinoza-problem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-the-spinoza-problem/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Statistical Power of abnormal-social Psychological research: A Review</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cohen1962/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/cohen1962/</guid><description>Reference Jacob Cohen “The statistical power of abnormal-social psychological research: A review” (1962) // The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology. Publisher: American Psychological Association (APA). Vol. 65. No 3. Pp. 145–153. DOI: 10.1037/h0045186
Bib @Article{cohen1962, title = {The statistical power of abnormal-social psychological research: A review}, volume = {65}, issn = {0096-851X}, url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/h0045186}, doi = {10.1037/h0045186}, number = {3}, journal = {The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology}, publisher = {American Psychological Association (APA)}, author = {Cohen, Jacob}, year = {1962}, month = {sep}, pages = {145–153} }</description></item><item><title>The Stress Solution: The 4 Steps to Reset Your Body, Mind, Relationships and Purpose</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/chatterjee-the-stress-solution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/chatterjee-the-stress-solution/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F*ck: A Counterintuitive Approach to Living a Good Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/manson-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fck/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/manson-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fck/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Tale of the Dueling Neurosurgeons: The History of the Human Brain as Revealed by True Stories of Trauma, Madness, and Recovery</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kean-the-tale-of-the-dueling-neurosurgeons/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kean-the-tale-of-the-dueling-neurosurgeons/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Tipping Point: How Little Things Can Make a Big Difference</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-the-tipping-point/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/gladwell-the-tipping-point/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Theoretical Risks and Tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the Slow Progress of Soft Psychology</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1978/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/meehl1978/</guid><description>Reference Paul E Meehl “Theoretical risks and tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the slow progress of soft psychology” (1978) // Publisher: American Psychological Association. DOI: 10.1037/0022-006X.46.4.806
Bib @Article{meehl1978, title = {Theoretical risks and tabular asterisks: Sir Karl, Sir Ronald, and the slow progress of soft psychology}, author = {Meehl, Paul E}, year = {1978}, publisher = {American Psychological Association}, doi = {10.1037/0022-006X.46.4.806} }</description></item><item><title>Thinking, Fast and Slow</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kahneman-thinking-fast-and-slow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kahneman-thinking-fast-and-slow/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Unconditional Parenting: Moving from Rewards and Punishments to Love and Reason</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kohn-unconditional-parenting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/kohn-unconditional-parenting/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding Human Nature</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/adler-understanding-human-nature/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/adler-understanding-human-nature/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Understanding Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/adler-understanding-life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/adler-understanding-life/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Unimpressive Theories in Psychology</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a877a820-1fcb-4944-99ad-5f888320ea8d/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/quotes/a877a820-1fcb-4944-99ad-5f888320ea8d/</guid><description>I consider it unnecessary to persuade you that most so-called “theories” in the soft areas of psychology (clinical, counseling, social, personality, community, and school psychology) are scientifically unimpressive and technologically worthless.</description></item><item><title>When Nietzsche Wept</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-when-nietzsche-wept/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yalom-when-nietzsche-wept/</guid><description/></item><item><title>When Panic Attacks: The New, Drug-Free Anxiety Therapy that Can Change Your Life</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burns-when-panic-attacks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/burns-when-panic-attacks/</guid><description/></item><item><title>When: The Scientific Secrets of Perfect Timing</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-when/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pink-when/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Why is It so Hard to Do My work? The Challenge of Attention Residue When Switching Between Work Tasks</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</guid><description>One of the main insights from this research: in switching between tasks, the performance on the subsequent tasks increases when the previous task was finished and performed under high time pressure. The statistical analysis was performed unsatisfactorily, but the effect size is decent and the results look believable. However, it is not clear to which extent the results can be generalized to other tasks and other populations (some of the possible concerns are discussed in the &amp;ldquo;Limitations&amp;rdquo; section on page 179).
Introduction There is a nice overview of the problem with a rich set of references.
Study 1 (Attention residue) The author introduces two research propositions:
RP1: People who do not finish Task A before switching to Task B experience more attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A prior to switching to Task B.
RP2: People who finish Task A under high time pressure exhibit less attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A under low time pressure.
Design:
84 undergraduate students (26 men; 58 women) random assignment to the (finished/unfinished) X (high/low time pressure) between-participants design The participants were told that they were going to participate in two separate studies crafted by different researchers. Procedure:
Task A (5 minutes; framing on intelligence): solving 17 clues in a fixed number of one-word answers (Appendix A) Three manipulation check questions (Table 1) If Task A is completed Satisfaction with own performance (7-point Likert scale) Consistency with the experimental conditions Lexical decision task (measures attention residue): quick distinguishing of real words from fake words (Table 2) Debriefing Task B (5 minutes): reviewing 4 CVs Manipulations:
Finished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 13 unique words Unfinished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 5 unique words (non-solvable) High time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work as fast as you can&amp;rdquo;; background timer with announcement of remaining time every minute Low time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work at your own pace&amp;rdquo; The study design feels good and is formed according to well-established recommendations by other research teams.</description></item><item><title>Will and Self-Control</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yakutenko-will-and-self-control/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/yakutenko-will-and-self-control/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance: An Inquiry Into Values</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pirsig-zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/books/pirsig-zen-and-the-art-of-motorcycle-maintenance/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>