<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research: Gamma Effect Size on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-gamma-es/</link><description>Recent content in Research: Gamma Effect Size on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-gamma-es/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Nonparametric effect size: Cohen's d vs. Glass's delta</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-cohen-glass/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-cohen-glass/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-gamma-es/">previous posts&lt;/a>,
I discussed the idea of nonparametric effect size measures
consistent with Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d under normality.
However, Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d is not always the best effect size measure, even in the normal case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we briefly discuss a case study in which a nonparametric version of Glass&amp;rsquo;s delta is preferable
than the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/">previously suggested&lt;/a> Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d-consistent measure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gamma effect size powered by the middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-mnzqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-mnzqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-gamma-es/">previous posts&lt;/a>, I covered the concept of the gamma effect size.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nonparametric effect size which is consistent with Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d under the normal distribution.
However, the original definition has drawbacks: this statistic becomes zero
if half of the sample elements are equal to each other.
Last time, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/zero-mad-gamma-es/">suggested&lt;/a>) a workaround for this problem:
we can replace the median absolute deviation by the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>.
Unfortunately, this trick requires parameter tuning:
we should choose a proper quantile position to make this approach work.
Today I want to suggest a strategy that provides a way to make a generic choice:
we can use the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/">middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Calculating gamma effect size for samples with zero median absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/zero-mad-gamma-es/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/zero-mad-gamma-es/</guid><description>&lt;p>In previous posts, I discussed the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/">gamma effect size&lt;/a>
which is a Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d-consistent nonparametric and robust measure of the effect size.
Also, I discussed &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size2/">various ways to customize this metric&lt;/a>
and adjust it to different kinds of business requirements.
In this post, I want to briefly cover one more corner case that requires special adjustments.
We are going to discuss the situation when the median absolute deviation is zero.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Customization of the nonparametric Cohen's d-consistent effect size</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size2/</guid><description>&lt;p>One year ago, I publish a post called &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/">&lt;svg class="rating-icon">&lt;use xlink:href="https://aakinshin.net/img/fa/all.svg#note">&lt;/use>&lt;/svg>Nonparametric Cohen&amp;#39;s d-consistent effect size&lt;/a>.
During this year, I got a lot of internal and external feedback from
my own statistical experiments and
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ViljamiSairanen/status/1400457118340108293">people&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://sherbold.github.io/autorank/autorank/">who&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Ramon-Diaz/Thesis-Project/blob/85df6b11050c7e05c4394d873585f701a7e3f32e/_util.py#L100">tried&lt;/a>
to use the suggested approach.
It seems that the nonparametric version of Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d works much better with real-life not-so-normal data.
While the classic Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d based on
the non-robust arithmetic mean and
the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/misleading-stddev/">non-robust standard deviation&lt;/a>
can be easily &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/cohend-and-outliers/">corrupted by a single outlier&lt;/a>,
my approach is much more resistant to unexpected extreme values.
Also, it allows exploring
&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/comparing-distributions-using-gamma-es/">the difference between specific quantiles of considered samples&lt;/a>,
which can be useful in the non-parametric case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t satisfied with the results of all of my experiments.
While I still like the basic idea
(replace the mean with the median; replace the standard deviation with the median absolute deviation),
it turned out that the final results heavily depend on the used quantile estimator.
To be more specific, the original Harrell-Davis quantile estimator is not always optimal;
in most cases, it&amp;rsquo;s better to replace it with its &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/trimmed-hdqe/">trimmed&lt;/a> modification.
However, the particular choice of the quantile estimators depends on the situation.
Also, the consistency constant for the median absolute deviation
should be adjusted according to the current sample size and the used quantile estimator.
Of course, it also can be replaced by other dispersion estimators
that can be used as consistent estimators of the standard deviation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I want to get a brief overview of possible customizations of the suggested metrics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Comparing distribution quantiles using gamma effect size</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/comparing-distributions-using-gamma-es/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/comparing-distributions-using-gamma-es/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are several ways to describe the difference between two distributions.
Here are a few examples:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Effect sizes based on differences between means (e.g., Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d, Glass&amp;rsquo; Δ, Hedges&amp;rsquo; g)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/shift-and-ratio-functions/">The shift and ration functions&lt;/a> that
estimate differences between matched quantiles.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In one of the previous post, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/">described&lt;/a>
the gamma effect size which is defined not for the mean but for quantiles.
In this post, I want to share a few case studies that demonstrate
how the suggested metric combines the advantages of the above approaches.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A single outlier could completely distort your Cohen's d value</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cohend-and-outliers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/cohend-and-outliers/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effect_size#Cohen's_d">Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d&lt;/a> is a popular way to estimate
the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effect_size">effect size&lt;/a> between two samples.
It works excellent for perfectly normal distributions.
Usually, people think that slight deviations from normality
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t produce a noticeable impact on the result.
Unfortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s not always true.
In fact, a single outlier value can completely distort the result even in large samples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I will present some illustrations for this problem and will show how to fix it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nonparametric Cohen's d-consistent effect size</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update: the second part of this post is available &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size2/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The effect size is a common way to describe a difference between two distributions.
When these distributions are normal, one of the most popular approaches to express the effect size is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effect_size#Cohen's_d">Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d&lt;/a>.
Unfortunately, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work great for non-normal distributions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I will show a robust Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d-consistent effect size formula for nonparametric distributions.&lt;/p>





&lt;div class="row">
&lt;div class="mx-auto">
 &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/img/blackboard.png" target="_blank" alt="blackboard">
 &lt;img
 class="mx-auto d-block img-fluid"
 width='800'
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/nonparametric-effect-size/img/blackboard.png" />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;br /></description></item></channel></rss>