<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Frank E Harrell on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/frank-e-harrell/</link><description>Recent content in Frank E Harrell on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/frank-e-harrell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A new distribution-free quantile estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/harrell1982/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/harrell1982/</guid><description>Reference Frank E Harrell, C E Davis “A new distribution-free quantile estimator” (1982) // Biometrika. Vol. 69. No 3. Pp. 635–640. DOI: 10.1093/biomet/69.3.635
Abstract A new distribution-free estimator Qp of the pth population quantile is formulated, where Qp is a linear combination of order statistics admitting a jackknife variance estimator having excellent properties. The small sample efficiency of Qp is studied under a variety of light and heavy-tailed symmetric and asymmetric distributions. For the distributions and values of p studied, Qp is generally substantially more efficient than the traditional estimator based on one or two order statistics.
Bib @Article{harrell1982, title = {A new distribution-free quantile estimator}, volume = {69}, issn = {0006-3444}, url = {https://academic.oup.com/biomet/article/69/3/635/221346}, doi = {10.1093/biomet/69.3.635}, abstract = {A new distribution-free estimator Qp of the pth population quantile is formulated, where Qp is a linear combination of order statistics admitting a jackknife variance estimator having excellent properties. The small sample efficiency of Qp is studied under a variety of light and heavy-tailed symmetric and asymmetric distributions. For the distributions and values of p studied, Qp is generally substantially more efficient than the traditional estimator based on one or two order statistics.}, language = {en}, number = {3}, urldate = {2020-07-14}, journal = {Biometrika}, author = {Harrell, Frank E and Davis, C E}, month = {dec}, year = {1982}, note = {Publisher: Oxford Academic}, pages = {635--640} }</description></item></channel></rss>