<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pages on Андрей Акиньшин</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/ru/pages/</link><description>Recent content in Pages on Андрей Акиньшин</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/ru/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pro .NET Benchmarking</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/ru/prodotnetbenchmarking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/ru/prodotnetbenchmarking/</guid><description>Learn how to measure application performance and analyze the results! Use this in-depth guide to correctly design benchmarks, measure key performance metrics of .NET applications, and analyze results. This book presents dozens of case studies to help you understand complicated benchmarking topics. You will avoid common pitfalls, control the accuracy of your measurements, and improve performance of your software. Author Andrey Akinshin has maintained BenchmarkDotNet (the most popular .NET library for benchmarking) for five years and covers common mistakes that developers usually make in their benchmarks. This book includes not only .NET-specific content but also essential knowledge about performance measurements which can be applied to any language or platform (common benchmarking methodology, statistics, and low-level features of modern hardware). With this book, you will learn: Be aware of the best practices for writing benchmarks and performance tests Avoid the common benchmarking pitfalls Know the hardware and software factors that affect application performance Analyze performance measurements Apress Amazon US Amazon CA Amazon UK Amazon DE Amazon FR Amazon ES Amazon JP Springer Google Books O’Reilly GoodReads ResearchGate Examples (GitHub) Errata (GitHub) Content The book contains nine chapters:
Chapter 1 “Introducing Benchmarking”
This chapter contains some basic information about benchmarking and other performance investigations, including benchmarking goals and requirements. We will also discuss performance spaces and why it’s so important to analyze benchmark results. Chapter 2 “Common Benchmarking Pitfalls”
This chapter contains 15 examples of common mistakes that developers usually make during benchmarking. Each example is pretty small (so, you can easily understand what’s going on), but all of them demonstrate important problems and explain how to resolve them. Chapter 3 “How Environment Affects Performance”
This chapter explains why the environment is so important and introduces a lot of terms that will be used in subsequent chapters. You will find 12 case studies that demonstrate how minor changes in the environment may significantly affect application performance.</description></item><item><title>Об авторе</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/ru/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/ru/about/</guid><description>Андрей Акиньшин — программист, автор постов и статей про математику и программирование, частый спикер на конференциях (100+ выступлений). Он мейнтейнер BenchmarkDotNet (самая популярная библиотека для написания .NET-бенчмарков) и perfolizer (инструменты для перфоманс-анализа); автор Pro .NET Benchmarking (книга о практиках замеров производительности).
Андрей — Senior Performance Engineer в JetBrains Rider (кроссплатформенная .NET IDE, основанная на платформе IntelliJ и ReSharper). Он также бывший член программного комитета конференции DotNext, бывший Microsoft .NET MVP, серебрянный медалист ACM ICPC.
Андрей имеет степень к.ф.-м.н.. Его текущая область научных интересов — математическая статистика. Раньше работал постдоком в Институте Вейцмана и занимался научными проектами в Институте математики СО РАН в сфере математической биологии и теории бифуркаций.</description></item></channel></rss>