<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research: Quantile absolute deviation on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-qad/</link><description>Recent content in Research: Quantile absolute deviation on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-qad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Preprint announcement: 'Quantile absolute deviation'</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-qad/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/preprint-qad/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have just published a preprint of a paper &amp;lsquo;Quantile absolute deviation&amp;rsquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s based on a series of my &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-qad/">research notes&lt;/a>
that I have been writing since December 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The paper preprint is available on arXiv:
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13459">arXiv:2208.13459 [stat.ME]&lt;/a>.
The paper source code is available on GitHub:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/AndreyAkinshin/paper-qad">AndreyAkinshin/paper-qad&lt;/a>.
You can cite it as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Andrey Akinshin (2022)
&amp;ldquo;Quantile absolute deviation&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13459">arXiv:2208.13459&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The median absolute deviation (MAD) is a popular robust measure of statistical dispersion.
However, when it is applied to non-parametric distributions (especially multimodal, discrete, or heavy-tailed),
lots of statistical inference issues arise.
Even when it is applied to distributions with slight deviations from normality and these issues are not actual,
the Gaussian efficiency of the MAD is only 37% which is not always enough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this paper, we introduce the &lt;em>quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em> (QAD) as a generalization of the MAD.
This measure of dispersion provides a flexible approach to analyzing properties of non-parametric distributions.
It also allows controlling the trade-off between robustness and statistical efficiency.
We use the trimmed Harrell-Davis median estimator based on the highest density interval of the given width
as a complimentary median estimator that gives
increased finite-sample Gaussian efficiency compared to the sample median
and a breakdown point matched to the QAD.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a rule of thumb, we suggest using two new measures of dispersion
called the &lt;em>standard QAD&lt;/em> and the &lt;em>optimal QAD&lt;/em>.
They give 54% and 65% of Gaussian efficiency having breakdown points of 32% and 14% respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Standard trimmed Harrell-Davis median estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sthdme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sthdme/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/sqad/">one of the previous posts&lt;/a>, I suggested a new measure of dispersion called
&lt;em>the standard quantile absolute deviation around the median&lt;/em> ($\operatorname{SQAD}$) which can be used as an alternative
to the median absolute deviation ($\operatorname{MAD}$) as a consistent estimator for the standard deviation under normality.
The Gaussian efficiency of $\operatorname{SQAD}$ is $54\%$ (comparing to $37\%$ for MAD),
and its breakdown point is $32\%$ (comparing to $50\%$ for MAD).
$\operatorname{SQAD}$ is a symmetric dispersion measure around the median:
the interval $[\operatorname{Median} - \operatorname{SQAD}; \operatorname{Median} + \operatorname{SQAD}]$
covers $68\%$ of the distribution.
In the case of the normal distribution, this corresponds to the interval $[\mu - \sigma; \mu + \sigma]$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we use $\operatorname{SQAD}$, we accept the breakdown point of $32\%$.
This makes the sample median a non-optimal choice for the median estimator.
Indeed, the sample median has high robustness (the breakdown point is $50\%$),
but relatively poor Gaussian efficiency.
If we use $\operatorname{SQAD}$, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to require a breakdown point of more than $32\%$.
Therefore, we could trade the median robustness for efficiency
and come up with a complementary measure of the median for $\operatorname{SQAD}$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we introduce the standard trimmed Harrell-Davis median estimator which shares
the breakdown point with $\operatorname{SQAD}$ and provides better finite-sample efficiency comparing
to the sample median.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Optimal quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/oqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/oqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>We consider the quantile absolute deviation around the median defined as follows:&lt;/p>
$$
\newcommand{\E}{\mathbb{E}}
\newcommand{\PR}{\mathbb{P}}
\newcommand{\Q}{\operatorname{Q}}
\newcommand{\OQAD}{\operatorname{OQAD}}
\newcommand{\QAD}{\operatorname{QAD}}
\newcommand{\median}{\operatorname{median}}
\newcommand{\Exp}{\operatorname{Exp}}
\newcommand{\SD}{\operatorname{SD}}
\newcommand{\V}{\mathbb{V}}
\QAD(X, p) = K_p \Q(|X - \median(X)|, p),
$$
&lt;p>where $\Q$ is a quantile estimator,
and $K_p$ is a scale constant which we use to make $\QAD(X, p)$ an asymptotically consistent estimator
for the standard deviation under the normal distribution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, we get the exact values of the $K_p$ values,
derive the corresponding equation for the asymptotic Gaussian efficiency of $\QAD(X, p)$,
and find the point in which $\QAD(X, p)$ achieves the highest Gaussian efficiency.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile absolute deviation of the Pareto distribution</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post,
we derive the exact equation for the quantile absolute deviation around the median of the Pareto(1,1) distribution.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/img/qad-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/img/qad-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/img/qad-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-pareto/img/qad-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Quantile absolute deviation of the Exponential distribution</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post,
we derive the exact equation for the quantile absolute deviation around the median of the Exponential distribution.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/img/qad-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/img/qad-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/img/qad-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-exp/img/qad-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Quantile absolute deviation of the Uniform distribution</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post,
we derive the exact equation for the quantile absolute deviation around the median of the Uniform distribution.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/img/qad-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/img/qad-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/img/qad-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-uniform/img/qad-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Quantile absolute deviation of the Normal distribution</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this post,
we derive the exact equation for the quantile absolute deviation around the median of the Normal distribution.&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/img/qad-light.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/img/qad-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/img/qad-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="qad">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-normal/img/qad-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Standard quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/sqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>The median absolute deviation (MAD) is a popular robust replacement of the standard deviation (StdDev).
It&amp;rsquo;s truly robust: its breakdown point is $50\%$.
However, it&amp;rsquo;s not so efficient when we use it as a consistent estimator for the standard deviation under normality:
the asymptotic relative efficiency against StdDev (we call it the &lt;em>Gaussian efficiency&lt;/em>) is only about $\approx 37\%$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In practice, such robustness is not always essential, while we typically want to have the highest possible efficiency.
I already described the concept of the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">&lt;em>quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em>&lt;/a> which aims
to provide a customizable trade-off between robustness and efficiency.
In this post, I would like to suggest a new default option for this measure of dispersion
called the &lt;em>standard quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em>.
Its Gaussian efficiency is $\approx 54\%$ while the breakdown point is $\approx 32\%$&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Asymptotic Gaussian efficiency of the quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-are/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-are/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have already discussed the concept of the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>
in &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-qad/">several previous posts&lt;/a>.
In this post, we derive the equation for the relative statistical efficiency of the quantile absolute deviation
against the standard deviation under the normal distribution (so call Gaussian efficiency).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Caveats of using the median absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mad-caveats/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mad-caveats/</guid><description>&lt;p>The median absolute deviation is a measure of dispersion
which can be used as a robust alternative to the standard deviation.
It works great for slight deviations from normality
(e.g., for contaminated normal distributions or slightly skewed unimodal distributions).
Unfortunately, if we apply it to distributions with huge deviations from normality,
we may experience a lot of troubles.
In this post, I discuss some of the most important caveats which we should keep in mind
if we use the median absolute deviation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Degenerate point of dispersion estimators</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/degenerate-point/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/degenerate-point/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, I have been working on searching for a robust statistical dispersion estimator
that doesn&amp;rsquo;t become zero on samples with a huge number of tied values.
I have already created a few of such estimators like
the &lt;em>middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em> (&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/">part 1&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad2/">part 2&lt;/a>) and
the &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/uqad/">untied quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>&lt;/em>.
Having several options to compare, we need a proper metric that allows us to perform such a comparison.
Similar to the breakdown point (that is used to describe estimator robustness),
we could introduce the &lt;em>degenerate point&lt;/em> that describes the resistance of a dispersion estimator to the tied values.
In this post, I will briefly describe this concept.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Untied quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/uqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/uqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the previous posts, I tried to adapt the concept of the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>
to samples with tied values so that this measure of dispersion never becomes zero for nondegenerate ranges.
My previous attempt was the &lt;em>middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation&lt;/em>
(&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/">modification 1&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad2/">modification 2&lt;/a>).
However, I&amp;rsquo;m not completely satisfied with the behavior of this metric.
In this post, I want to consider another way to work around the problem with tied values.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation, Part 2</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In one of the previous posts, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/">described&lt;/a> the idea of the
middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation.
It&amp;rsquo;s defined as follows:&lt;/p>
$$
\operatorname{MNZQAD}(x, p) = \operatorname{QAD}(x, p, q_m),
$$
$$
q_m = \frac{q_0 + 1}{2}, \quad
q_0 = \frac{\max(k - 1, 0)}{n - 1}, \quad
k = \sum_{i=1}^n \mathbf{1}_{Q(x, p)}(x_i),
$$
&lt;p>where $\mathbf{1}$ is the indicator function&lt;/p>
$$
\mathbf{1}_U(u) = \begin{cases}
1 &amp; \textrm{if}\quad u = U,\\
0 &amp; \textrm{if}\quad u \neq U,
\end{cases}
$$
&lt;p>and $\operatorname{QAD}$ is the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
$$
\operatorname{QAD}(x, p, q) = Q(|x - Q(x, p)|, q).
$$
&lt;p>The $\operatorname{MNZQAD}$ approach tries to work around a problem with tied values.
While it works well in the generic case, there are some corner cases
where the suggested metric behaves poorly.
In this post, we discuss this problem and how to solve it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gamma effect size powered by the middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-mnzqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/gamma-es-mnzqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/research-gamma-es/">previous posts&lt;/a>, I covered the concept of the gamma effect size.
It&amp;rsquo;s a nonparametric effect size which is consistent with Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d under the normal distribution.
However, the original definition has drawbacks: this statistic becomes zero
if half of the sample elements are equal to each other.
Last time, I &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/zero-mad-gamma-es/">suggested&lt;/a>) a workaround for this problem:
we can replace the median absolute deviation by the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>.
Unfortunately, this trick requires parameter tuning:
we should choose a proper quantile position to make this approach work.
Today I want to suggest a strategy that provides a way to make a generic choice:
we can use the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/">middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Middle non-zero quantile absolute deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mnzqad/</guid><description>&lt;p>Median absolute deviation ($\operatorname{MAD}$) around the median is a popular robust measure of statistical dispersion.
Unfortunately, if we &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/discrete-performance-distributions/">work&lt;/a> with discrete distributions,
we could get zero $\operatorname{MAD}$ values.
It could bring some problems if we &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/zero-mad-gamma-es/">use&lt;/a> $\operatorname{MAD}$ as a denominator.
Such a problem is also relevant to some other quantile-based measures of dispersion
like interquartile range ($\operatorname{IQR}$).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This problem could be solved using the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/">quantile absolute deviation&lt;/a> around the median.
However, it&amp;rsquo;s not always clear how to choose the right quantile to estimate.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to suggest a choosing approach that is consistent with the classic $\operatorname{MAD}$
under continuous distributions (and samples without tied values).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantile absolute deviation: estimating statistical dispersion around quantiles</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are many different metrics for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistical_dispersion">statistical dispersion&lt;/a>.
The most famous one is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_deviation">standard deviation&lt;/a>.
The standard deviation is the most popular way to describe the spread around the mean when
you work with normally distributed data.
However, if you work with non-normal distributions, this metric may be misleading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the world of non-parametric distributions,
the most common measure of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_tendency">central tendency&lt;/a> is the median.
For the median, you can describe dispersion using the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Median_absolute_deviation">median absolute deviation around the median&lt;/a> (MAD).
It works great if the median is the only &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summary_statistics">summary statistic&lt;/a> that you care about.
However, if you work with multimodal distributions
(they can be detected using the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/lowland-multimodality-detection/">lowland multimodality detector&lt;/a>),
you may be interested in other quantiles as well.
So, it makes sense to learn how to describe dispersion around the given quantile.
Which metric should we choose?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, I came up with a great solution to this problem.
We can generalize the median absolute deviation into the quantile absolute deviation (QAD) around the given quantile based on the Harrell-Davis quantile estimator.
I will show how to calculate it, how to interpret it, and how to get insights about distribution properties
from images like this one:&lt;/p>








&lt;div class="flex my-7 justify-center">
 &lt;a class="img-light hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/img/modal5-light.png" target="_blank" alt="modal5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/img/modal5-light.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
 &lt;a class="img-dark hidden" href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/img/modal5-dark.png" target="_blank" alt="modal5">
 &lt;img
 src="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad/img/modal5-dark.png" 
 width='800'
 />
 &lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>