<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shamos Estimator on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/shamos-estimator/</link><description>Recent content in Shamos Estimator on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/shamos-estimator/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Finite-sample Gaussian efficiency: Shamos vs. Rousseeuw-Croux Qn scale estimators</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/shamos-vs-qn/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/shamos-vs-qn/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/posts/qad-vs-rc/">Previously&lt;/a>, we compared the finite-sample Gaussian efficiency of
the &lt;a href="https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/rousseeuw1993/">Rousseeuw-Croux scale estimators&lt;/a> and the QAD estimator.
In this post, we compare the finite-sample Gaussian efficiency of the Shamos scale estimator
and the Rousseeuw-Croux $Q_n$ scale estimator.
This is a particularly interesting comparison.
In the famous &amp;ldquo;Alternatives to the Median Absolute Deviation&amp;rdquo; (1993) paper by Peter J. Rousseeuw and Christophe Croux,
the authors presented $Q_n$ as an improved version of the Shamos estimator.
Both estimators are based on the set of pairwise absolute differences between the elements of the sample.
The Shamos estimator takes the median of this set and, therefore,
has the asymptotic breakdown point of $\approx 29\%$
and the asymptotic Gaussian efficiency of $\approx 86\%$.
$Q_n$ takes the first quartile of this set and, therefore,
has the asymptotic breakdown point of $\approx 50\%$ (like the median)
and the asymptotic Gaussian efficiency of $\approx 82\%$.
It sounds like a good deal: we trade $4\%$ of the asymptotic Gaussian efficiency
for $21\%$ of the asymptotic breakdown point.
What could possibly stop us from using $Q_n$ everywhere instead of the Shamos estimator?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, here is a trick.
The breakdown point of $29\%$ is actually a practically reasonable value.
If more than $29\%$ of the sample are outliers, we should probably consider them not as outliers but as a separate mode.
Such a situation should be handled by a multimodality detector and lead us to a different approach.
The usage of dispersion estimators in the case of multimodal distributions is potentially misleading.
When such a multimodality diagnostic scheme is used, there is no practical need for a higher breakdown point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thus, the breakdown point of $50\%$ is not so impressive property of $Q_n$.
Meanwhile, the drop in Gaussian efficiency is not so enjoyable.
$4\%$ may sound like a negligible difference, but it is only the asymptotic value.
In real life, we typically tend to work with finite samples.
Let us explore the actual finite-sample Gaussian efficiency values of these estimators.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Median absolute deviation vs. Shamos estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mad-vs-shamos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/posts/mad-vs-shamos/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are multiple ways to estimate statistical dispersion.
The standard deviation is the most popular one, but it&amp;rsquo;s not robust:
a single outlier could heavily corrupt the results.
Fortunately, we have robust measures of dispersions like the &lt;em>median absolute deviation&lt;/em> and the &lt;em>Shamos estimator&lt;/em>.
In this post, we perform numerical simulations and
compare these two estimators on different distributions and sample sizes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Alternatives to the Median Absolute Deviation</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/rousseeuw1993/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/rousseeuw1993/</guid><description>Reference Peter J Rousseeuw, Christophe Croux “Alternatives to the Median Absolute Deviation” (1993) // Journal of the American Statistical Association. Vol. 88. No 424. Pp. 1273–1283. DOI: 10.1080/01621459.1993.10476408
Abstract In robust estimation one frequently needs an initial or auxiliary estimate of scale. For this one usually takes the median absolute deviation MAD n = 1.4826 med, \textbarxi − med j x j \textbar, because it has a simple explicit formula, needs little computation time, and is very robust as witnessed by its bounded influence function and its 50% breakdown point. But there is still room for improvement in two areas: the fact that MAD n is aimed at symmetric distributions and its low (37%) Gaussian efficiency. In this article we set out to construct explicit and 50% breakdown scale estimators that are more efficient. We consider the estimator Sn = 1.1926 med, med j \textbar xi − xj \textbar and the estimator Qn given by the .25 quantile of the distances \textbarxi − x j \textbar; i \textless j. Note that Sn and Qn do not need any location estimate. Both Sn and Qn can be computed using O(n log n) time and O(n) storage. The Gaussian efficiency of Sn is 58%, whereas Qn attains 82%. We study Sn and Qn by means of their influence functions, their bias curves (for implosion as well as explosion), and their finite-sample performance. Their behavior is also compared at non-Gaussian models, including the negative exponential model where Sn has a lower gross-error sensitivity than the MAD.
Bib @Article{rousseeuw1993, title = {Alternatives to the Median Absolute Deviation}, volume = {88}, issn = {0162-1459}, url = {https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01621459.1993.10476408}, doi = {10.1080/01621459.1993.10476408}, abstract = {In robust estimation one frequently needs an initial or auxiliary estimate of scale. For this one usually takes the median absolute deviation MAD n = 1.</description></item><item><title>Geometry and Statistics: Problems at the Interface</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/shamos1976/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/shamos1976/</guid><description>Reference Michael Ian Shamos “Geometry and Statistics: Problems at the Interface” (1976) // In Algorithms and Complexity: New directions and recent results. Citeseer.
Abstract In this paper we approach the analysis of statistics algorithms from a geometric viewpoint and use techniques from computational geometry to develop new, fast algorithms for computing familiar statistical quantities. Such fundamental procedures as sorting and selection play an important role in nonparametric estimation as well as in correlation and regression and we use known results to obtain lower bounds on the time required to perform various statistical tests. For some problems, computing the test statistic is NP-hard. While geometric insight is helpful in understanding statistical calculations, the reverse is also true-we employ statistical methods to analyze the average case of geometric al gorithms.
Bib @Article{shamos1976, title = {Geometry and Statistics: Problems at the Interface}, abstract = {In this paper we approach the analysis of statistics algorithms from a geometric viewpoint and use techniques from computational geometry to develop new, fast algorithms for computing familiar statistical quantities. Such fundamental procedures as sorting and selection play an important role in nonparametric estimation as well as in correlation and regression and we use known results to obtain lower bounds on the time required to perform various statistical tests. For some problems, computing the test statistic is NP-hard. While geometric insight is helpful in understanding statistical calculations, the reverse is also true-we employ statistical methods to analyze the average case of geometric al gorithms.}, author = {Shamos, Michael Ian}, booktitle = {In Algorithms and Complexity: New directions and recent results}, year = {1976}, organization = {Citeseer} }</description></item><item><title>Investigation of finite-sample Properties of Robust Location and Scale Estimators</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/park2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/park2020/</guid><description>Reference Chanseok Park, Haewon Kim, Min Wang “Investigation of finite-sample properties of robust location and scale estimators” (2020) // Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation. Vol. 51. No 5. Pp. 2619–2645. DOI: 10.1080/03610918.2019.1699114
Bib @Article{park2020, title = {Investigation of finite-sample properties of robust location and scale estimators}, volume = {51}, issn = {0361-0918, 1532-4141}, url = {https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/03610918.2019.1699114}, doi = {10.1080/03610918.2019.1699114}, language = {en}, number = {5}, urldate = {2022-06-23}, journal = {Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation}, author = {Park, Chanseok and Kim, Haewon and Wang, Min}, year = {2020}, pages = {2619--2645} }</description></item></channel></rss>