<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thomas Nagler on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/thomas-nagler/</link><description>Recent content in Thomas Nagler on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/library/authors/thomas-nagler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Generic Approach to Nonparametric Function Estimation with Mixed Data</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nagler2018/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nagler2018/</guid><description>The paper contains a nice literature overview.
Reference Thomas Nagler “A generic approach to nonparametric function estimation with mixed data” (2018) // Statistics &amp;amp; Probability Letters. Publisher: Elsevier BV. Vol. 137. Pp. 326–330. DOI: 10.1016/j.spl.2018.02.040
Abstract Most nonparametric function estimators can only handle continuous data. We show that making discrete variables continuous by adding noise is justified under suitable conditions on the noise distribution. This principle is widely applicable, including density and regression function estimation.
Bib @Article{nagler2018, title = {A generic approach to nonparametric function estimation with mixed data}, abstract = {Most nonparametric function estimators can only handle continuous data. We show that making discrete variables continuous by adding noise is justified under suitable conditions on the noise distribution. This principle is widely applicable, including density and regression function estimation.}, volume = {137}, issn = {0167-7152}, doi = {10.1016/j.spl.2018.02.040}, arxiv = {1704.07457}, journal = {Statistics \&amp;amp; Probability Letters}, publisher = {Elsevier BV}, author = {Nagler, Thomas}, year = {2018}, month = {jun}, pages = {326–330} }</description></item><item><title>Asymptotic Analysis of the Jittering Kernel Density Estimator</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nagler2018a/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/nagler2018a/</guid><description>Reference Thomas Nagler “Asymptotic Analysis of the Jittering Kernel Density Estimator” (2018) // Mathematical Methods of Statistics. Publisher: Allerton Press. Vol. 27. No 1. Pp. 32–46. DOI: 10.3103/s1066530718010027
Abstract Jittering estimators are nonparametric function estimators for mixed data. They extend arbitrary estimators from the continuous setting by adding random noise to discrete variables. We give an in-depth analysis of the jittering kernel density estimator, which reveals several appealing properties. The estimator is strongly consistent, asymptotically normal, and unbiased for discrete variables. It converges at minimax-optimal rates, which are established as a by-product of our analysis. To understand the effect of adding noise, we further study its asymptotic efficiency and finite sample bias in the univariate discrete case. Simulations show that the estimator is competitive on finite samples. The analysis suggests that similar properties can be expected for other jittering estimators.
Bib @Article{nagler2018a, title = {Asymptotic Analysis of the Jittering Kernel Density Estimator}, abstract = {Jittering estimators are nonparametric function estimators for mixed data. They extend arbitrary estimators from the continuous setting by adding random noise to discrete variables. We give an in-depth analysis of the jittering kernel density estimator, which reveals several appealing properties. The estimator is strongly consistent, asymptotically normal, and unbiased for discrete variables. It converges at minimax-optimal rates, which are established as a by-product of our analysis. To understand the effect of adding noise, we further study its asymptotic efficiency and finite sample bias in the univariate discrete case. Simulations show that the estimator is competitive on finite samples. The analysis suggests that similar properties can be expected for other jittering estimators.}, volume = {27}, issn = {1934-8045}, doi = {10.3103/s1066530718010027}, arxiv = {1705.05431}, number = {1}, journal = {Mathematical Methods of Statistics}, publisher = {Allerton Press}, author = {Thomas Nagler}, year = {2018}, month = {jan}, pages = {32–46} }</description></item></channel></rss>