<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>P-Value on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/p-value/</link><description>Recent content in P-Value on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/p-value/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A dirty dozen: twelve p-value misconceptions</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/goodman2008/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/goodman2008/</guid><description>Steven Goodman “A dirty dozen: twelve p-value misconceptions” (2008) // Seminars in hematology. Elsevier. Vol. 45. No 3. Pp. 135–140. DOI: 10.1053/j.seminhematol.2008.04.003
Abstract The P value is a measure of statistical evidence that appears in virtually all medical research papers. Its interpretation is made extraordinarily difficult because it is not part of any formal system of statistical inference. As a result, the P value&amp;rsquo;s inferential meaning is widely and often wildly misconstrued, a fact that has been pointed out in innumerable papers and books appearing since at least the 1940s. This commentary reviews a dozen of these common misinterpretations and explains why each is wrong. It also reviews the possible consequences of these improper understandings or representations of its meaning. Finally, it contrasts the P value with its Bayesian counterpart, the Bayes&amp;rsquo; factor, which has virtually all of the desirable properties of an evidential measure that the P value lacks, most notably interpretability. The most serious consequence of this array of P-value misconceptions is the false belief that the probability of a conclusion being in error can be calculated from the data in a single experiment without reference to external evidence or the plausibility of the underlying mechanism.
Bib @Inproceedings{goodman2008, title = {A dirty dozen: twelve p-value misconceptions}, author = {Goodman, Steven}, abstract = {The P value is a measure of statistical evidence that appears in virtually all medical research papers. Its interpretation is made extraordinarily difficult because it is not part of any formal system of statistical inference. As a result, the P value&amp;#39;s inferential meaning is widely and often wildly misconstrued, a fact that has been pointed out in innumerable papers and books appearing since at least the 1940s. This commentary reviews a dozen of these common misinterpretations and explains why each is wrong. It also reviews the possible consequences of these improper understandings or representations of its meaning.</description></item></channel></rss>