<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Multi-tasking on Andrey Akinshin</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/tags/multi-tasking/</link><description>Recent content in Multi-tasking on Andrey Akinshin</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://aakinshin.net/tags/multi-tasking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why is It so Hard to Do My work? The Challenge of Attention Residue When Switching Between Work Tasks</title><link>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aakinshin.net/library/papers/leroy2009/</guid><description>One of the main insights from this research: in switching between tasks, the performance on the subsequent tasks increases when the previous task was finished and performed under high time pressure. The statistical analysis was performed unsatisfactorily, but the effect size is decent and the results look believable. However, it is not clear to which extent the results can be generalized to other tasks and other populations (some of the possible concerns are discussed in the &amp;ldquo;Limitations&amp;rdquo; section on page 179).
Introduction There is a nice overview of the problem with a rich set of references.
Study 1 (Attention residue) The author introduces two research propositions:
RP1: People who do not finish Task A before switching to Task B experience more attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A prior to switching to Task B.
RP2: People who finish Task A under high time pressure exhibit less attention residue from Task A while working on Task B than do people who finish Task A under low time pressure.
Design:
84 undergraduate students (26 men; 58 women) random assignment to the (finished/unfinished) X (high/low time pressure) between-participants design The participants were told that they were going to participate in two separate studies crafted by different researchers. Procedure:
Task A (5 minutes; framing on intelligence): solving 17 clues in a fixed number of one-word answers (Appendix A) Three manipulation check questions (Table 1) If Task A is completed Satisfaction with own performance (7-point Likert scale) Consistency with the experimental conditions Lexical decision task (measures attention residue): quick distinguishing of real words from fake words (Table 2) Debriefing Task B (5 minutes): reviewing 4 CVs Manipulations:
Finished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 13 unique words Unfinished task: Task A is completed only if all 17 clues are solved in no more than 5 unique words (non-solvable) High time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work as fast as you can&amp;rdquo;; background timer with announcement of remaining time every minute Low time pressure: &amp;ldquo;Work at your own pace&amp;rdquo; The study design feels good and is formed according to well-established recommendations by other research teams.</description></item></channel></rss>